Have you ever had the experience of going to a computer training
center and realized how much computer stuff you don't know? I
know when I started in the computer industry in the early 90's I
had trouble just remembering my password after 15 minutes of one-on-
one instruction, much less how the computer actually worked. Let's
face it, no one wakes up one day and says, I am a genius with this
computer stuff. We all had to start some where and for most people,
computers can be very confusing and intimidating. And that is where
the computer trainer comes in.

Oh yeah, the computer trainer. The person that knows everything
about computers and will make learning your new computer skills easy
and quick. Yeah, right, fat chance of that happening. Have you ever
visited a large computer training center and wondered why computers
are so confusing for the client or student? The answer is usually
because of the computer trainer. Most trainers seemed to have
forgotten what it was like when they first tackled the "wonder
box". But over time, they developed magical knowledge that no one
else seemed to have.

So why would someone with so much so-called smarts not want to share
their knowledge with their students? The answer is very simple. It
makes them look smarter. All they have to do is through out a couple
of big fancy-smancy computer words to the class and you are a
genius. That is fine and dandy if a computer trainer wants to
impress Bill Gates, but to the new computer user that just pulled
the computer out of the box or was told by the boss they better
learn that computer stuff, the trainer does the student no good.

So what does a computer trainer need to do? The main thing is to
remember how they felt when they first started using the computer
and how they wanted to pull their hair out when they thought they
would never learn the stuff. How they were afraid to even touch the
computer. Computer trainers fail to realize not all the students
want to become computer geeks and nerds. The everyday user want to
know how to do the simple stuff like how to do a letter, track their
finances with a spreadsheet, develop a slide presentation for their
company or club, or make a simple website. A trainer needs to make
the complicated world of a computer simple, easy and fun for the
client or student. Let's face it, not everyone is or wants to
become a systems administrator or has enough certifications to cover
a wall a Subway. The majority of computer users are beginners that
want to learn how to be more productive at home or in the work
place.

So what does it take for a computer trainer to help students learn
the computer? Try keeping the computer sessions and information
simple and fun. Every trainer has a big responsibility to teach
others what they know so the student can be more productive.
Trainers need to realize you have got to keep the training simple
because if the student can't learn, you do them no good. So keep
it simple
How many times have you heard someone say I want to work for myself
or I want to be self-employed and be free from working for others?
If you are like me and own your own business you hear that a lot.
Now let us be honest. How many times do you get sick of those same
people telling you that and don't do anything about it.
Personally I get tired of hearing it. So why don't others do the
steps to start their own business? There are a variety of reasons
but to me the reason boils down to one reason and that reason is
fear.

So what are they afraid of? Many times it is the fear of change and
failure. Sure, no one wants to fail but that is a chance that all
new business owners face. The fear of failure is a very powerful
emotion. All new business owners not only have to face the chance of
a business not being successful they have to face the fact that many
of their family and friends and watching to see if the business will
be a success. The sad thing is most of the people we hope will
support us in our new venture are sometimes the ones that help
destroy the dream of owning your own business. So what do you do to
eliminate the fear of failure in a new business? You basically seek
out others who have started their business to gain insight into how
they did it.

Most business owners started some where and most likely they
observed other successful business owners to figure out how they
started. Like the old say goes "don't reinvent the
wheel". The key is for new business owners to do their homework.
Yes I said homework. There is work involved in starting, maintaining
and continuing a successful business. Think about it. If it were
easy everyone would be doing it.

Having your own business can be one of the most rewarding aspects of
your life. You get the freedom to your own boss. But with that you
are responsible for the failure and success of the business. There
in no one to blame but yourself.

So the next time some one tells you they want to start their own
business. Do what I do. Tell them that talking the talk gets you no
where. So have to walk the walk and your success is all up to you. 
Have you ever attended a computer course at a computer training
center and really thought about much money they make on teaching
students? I know when I first started taking classes it just amazed
me on how much money the training centers make for teaching many of
the most popular Microsoft Office courses offered today. Of course
there is big money in certification courses, but the majority of the
home and small business users just want to learn how to use products
like Microsoft Word, Excel, Outlook FrontPage and Access. That is
were the computer trainer comes in to the equation.

You see, many people do take courses at computer centers but many
don't like to or have to travel to the centers. Some students
don't like the large classroom environments so many don't
even go. Don't even get me started on Computer Based Training
(CBT) and Web Based Training (WBT) methods of teaching. Don't
get me wrong, computer training centers are good and very attractive
to the public. Many of the centers offer very good courses and have
very knowledgeable instructors. The problem is they can't offer
one-on-one assistance to the customer like personal computer trainer
can.

The computer training business can be a very profitable and enjoyable
business for a new business owner. For example, no too long ago I
attended a course myself and realized I was sitting in a class full
of students. After calculating the number students by the price of
the course, I realized the center just made over $2000.00 for only
seven hours of work (the class could have been done in half that
time). That is good money for a computer trainer that could have gone
on-site and conducted the same training. Not only did the center make
over $2000.00, they did it for only one level. There were four more
levels for the same course. Someone is making some very serious
money, don't you think?

Whether you know a lot or a little about computers, you can become a
computer trainer in not just Microsoft Office products but in a
variety of computer related fields. My advice is finding your niche
by looking at not only your talents but your passion. If you do
decide to become a computer trainer, nothing can stop you if you have
the drive and desire to be successful. 
An Ethiopian proverb states - "When spider webs unite, they can tie up a
lion." When one considers that small businesses accounted for 53 percent of
the private workforce and 50 percent of the nation's entire private gross
domestic product, it becomes clear that small business plays a large role in
our nation's economy. Small business owners gain an enormous power when they
join ranks. It is for this reason that networking plays an integral role in
the success of each small business.

As 2002 advances, it is imperative that we embraces the power of networking.
Whether you are a business owner or work for another firm, stepping outside
our comfort zone brings promise. Networking is one of the leading ways
businesses learn about upcoming trade shows, business expos, conferences and
cultural events where vendors can reach specific audiences. For example, at
www.chistell.com we learned about heavily trafficked events around the
country through networking channels we are active in. We attended a few of
those events as a vendor last year and moved more books at each of these
events in one to two days than we moved in a month at our website. Of
course, we are planning to network and attend more of these events in 2002!
You don't have to be a marketing guru or a world class speaker to network
effectively. In fact, two of the most important keys to networking are:
respect for self and respect for others. I highly recommend that you network
strongest in areas closely tied in with the products that you market and
sell. Not only will you discover what does and does not work in your field,
you will also hear about events that pull in your target audience in large
numbers.

Whether your business operates on or offline or both, your business' success
must involve effective networking. At times networking can appear to be no
more than chit chatting. Networking can be considered - communicating with
purpose. It is not a tool that allows one business owner to take advantage
of another. It is also more than passing out business cards. To be
effective, networking requires give and take. A business owner alerts you to
an upcoming event; you, in turn, direct the business owner to a graphic
artist who produces unforgettable web-site banners and clip art. Besides
your local business associations (which can be found in the yellow pages of
the telephone book) and the small business association, following are online
networking resources you could benefit from checking into: Small Business
Association (www.sba.org) or Fortune Small Business (www.fsb.com). Strive to
network (both on and offline) at least once a day. At the end of 2001 the
results will astound you. 
Ok, so you've got a website, and you're ready to tell the world
about it. Before you do, review these tips and create copy that
turns browsers into buyers.

Talk to Your Customers

Use the word "you" throughout your web site. Liberally. I've
seen hundreds and hundreds of sites with copy that reads, "We
serve our clients by developing high technology products and we
make sure to meet the needs of our clients." Does that sound
like your web copy? Please change it! Immediately!

Who are you writing to anyway? When your copy reads like that,
it sounds like you're telling a disinterested party what you do.
It's boring, and it doesn't involve your reader at all. TALK to
your potential customers throughout your site. Tell them, "We
serve YOU by developing high technology products that meet YOUR
business objectives."

You can, and should, use this principle everywhere, even in your
"Services" page. Tell your readers what you can, and will, do
for them. For example, "At XYZ Web Design, we'll take your idea,
and mold it and shape it to meet the needs of your customers.
Then we'll create a unique design and help brand your name, and
build a complete site that's a perfect fit for your company."

Keep it Short and Sweet

Web browsers have short attention spans. Write in short, punchy
sentences, and save the flowery and wordy prose for your next
novel. Break your copy into short paragraphs too, maybe with
only 3 to 5 sentences each. It's hard enough looking at a book
filled with solid text-forget looking at a web page like that!

And if you're confronted with a choice between a $1 word and a
25-cent word, use the 25-cent word. After all, there's no sense
telling potential customers that, "In the event of an
unsatisfactory occurrence, we will be most obliged to remedy the
situation as speedily as is humanly possible," when what you
really mean is, "We'll take care of any problems that happen-
quickly."

Read through your copy and cut every unnecessary word. It's easy
to get carried away with adjectives and adverbs, but they add fat
instead of muscle. Look at this sentence: "We'll do a very high
quality job at a really great affordable price." See anything
wrong with it? Start your editing by cutting each adjective or
adverb. Once you've got them all cut, your sentence reads like
this: "We'll do a quality job at an affordable price." Isn't
that sexier? I think so, too!

Benefits, Benefits, Benefits

Tell your potential customers about the benefits of your product
or service, NOT the features! Like the founder of Kodak said,
"We don't sell film, we sell memories." If you're selling a
ladies hat, don't tell customers about the wide rim and mesh
material. Tell them how the wide rim will reduce their chances
of skin cancer, and how the mesh will keep them cool on the
hottest day. Benefits sell-not features!

Here's how to find the benefits of your products or services.
First, list all the features on one side of a piece of paper. If
you're a web developer, for example, the features you offer could
be customized database design, Internet marketing services, and
e-Commerce capable sites. Those aren't benefits. Benefits are
what your customers will GET from those services.

On the other side of the paper, list what those features will do
for your customer. For instance, what will a customized database
design do if your customer uses one? Tell them! Tell them how
they can collect registration data and analyze it to make
informed business decisions. Tell them how your Internet
marketing services will drive targeted customers to their site-
and increase their sales. And, tell them how an e-Commerce
capable site will increase sales by more than 50 percent because
many people with credit cards prefer to pay online.

Other Things To Know

* Use bulleted lists to break up long copy. * It's easy to read,
and draws the eye down the page. * See?

Try to keep your most important copy on the first half of the
page. Many browsers won't scroll down, so if you have good stuff
that you want them to see at the bottom of the page, they may
miss it.

Write like you talk, and be conversational. If your web copy
sounds like a legal tome or prudish stiff, the only readers
you'll have are legal eagles...and prudish stiffs!

Don't count on your spell checker two catch you're miss steaks.
But don't let it rule your copy, either. My spell checker hates
the way I write so I ignore it...most of the time. Spell check
hates fragments. Like this. And this. But you know what?
That's how people talk. And that's one of the keys to creating
clear, conversational, and professional web copy that draws your
reader in and makes them feel like you're talking directly to
them-one on one. It builds confidence. And that, in my opinion,
is the best way to cinch a sale.
I have done it, and still do it unconsciously. It can
be something as subtle as simple look in your eyes or a
facial gesture. It can be more obvious as an eloquent
string of harsh words or even the tone of the words you
speak. Nevertheless, telling them they're wrong, is the
wrong foot forward. Nobody appreciates an attack on
their intelligence, on their rational judgment, and
especially their pride. You're looking for a positive
outcome, and most likely going to receive a negative
response. Why not just challenge them to a duel and
decide it there?

Whenever you begin by turning it into an opposition of
"smarter vs. dumber" you automatically begin a battle
between you and the listener before you even start.
>From this point on it is most difficult to make any
impressions or change their minds in a positive manner.

If you are going to prove your point, do it very
subtly. So subtly that they hardly realize it's
happening.

When I am positive about something and want to get it
across, I often use a statement such as, "Well, I'm
sure I'm right, but who knows, I've been wrong before.
I could be again". I am stressing two important facts
in this statement. One, being that I am almost 100%
certain that I am right, and two, that there is a
slight possibility that I am wrong. This means that I
am leaving room for doubt, but stressing the fact that
I am sure. You will always come out on top by admitting
that their is room for error. This will inspire your
opponent to be as open-minded as you seem to be. It
will make him/her think twice about admitting that they
may be wrong in part or whole.

Nothing good can come of telling a person straight out,
that he or she is wrong. You will only succeed in
stripping that person of self-dignity and making
yourself an unwelcome part of any discussion.

Final thought:

Don't argue with your clients. Don't argue with your
Husband or Wife. Don't argue with an Adversary! Please
don't get them all riled up by telling them they're
"wrong"! Use patience, tact, and a little diplomacy!
The Unforgiven 2 
Lay beside me, tell me what they've done 
Speak the words i wanna hear, to make my demons run 
The door is locked now, but it's open if you're true 
If you can understand the me, than i can understand the you 

Lay beside me, under wicked sky 
The black of day, dark of night, we share this paralyze 
The door cracks open, but there's no sun shining through 
Black heart scarring darker still, but there's no sun shining through 
No, there's no sun shining through 
No, there's no sun shining... 

What i've felt, what i've known 
Turn the pages, turn the stone 
Behind the door, should i open it for you.... 

What i've felt, what i've known 
Sick and tired, i stand alone 
Could you be there, 'cause i'm the one who waits for you 
Or are you unforgiven too? 

Lay beside me, this won't hurt i swear 
She loves me not, she loves me still, but she'll never love again 
She lay beside me, but she'll be there when i'm gone 
Black heart scarring darker still, yes she'll be there when i'm gone 
Yes, she'll be there when i'm gone 
Dead sure she'll be there... 

What i've felt, what i've known 
Turn the pages, turn the stone 
Behind the door, should i open it for you.... 

What i've felt, what i've known 
Sick and tired, i stand alone 
Could you be there, 'cause i'm the one who waits for you 
Or are you unforgiven too? 

Lay beside me, tell me what i've done 
The door is closed, so are you're eyes 
But now i see the sun, now i see the sun 
Yes now i see it 

What i've felt, what i've known 
Turn the pages, turn the stone 
Behind the door, should i open it for you.... 

What i've felt, what i've known 
Sick and tired, i stand alone 
Could you be there, 'cause i'm the one who waits, 
The one who waits for you.... 

Oh what i've felt, what i've known 
Turn the pages, turn the stone 
Behind the door, should i open it for you.... (So i dub thee unforgiven....) 

Oh, what i've felt.... 
Oh, what i've known.... 

I take this key (Never free...) 
And i bury it (Never me...) in you 
Because you're unforgiven too.... 

Never free.... 
I don't know about you, but sometimes it seems like all of the
best domain names have already been taken. On more than one
occasion, I've come up with a great domain name for a site,
only to find that someone else had already purchased it. I can
live with that, but sometimes I've found that it has been
purchased by some scum domain scavenger, and that's really
annoying.

A domain scavenger is someone who purchases a whole bunch of
domain names under the theory that people will want to purchase
some of them during the year or two that they own them. These
people are bottom feeders, as they hold many useful domains,
demand huge prices, and do not provide any real value. It's not
uncommon to find that a domain name is not available, to check
the WHOIS information and find it is owned by "this domain is
for sale". In fact, some of these scum have been known to
purchase thousands of domain names made of up the first and last
names from a phone book, in the hopes that at least some of the
people will want their names as a dot com.

Anyway, domains are only purchased for a specific time period,
and they do come up for renewal regularly. Quite often they are
not renewed, and at that time the domain names may be purchased
by others. Even the so-called "good names" are occasionally not
renewed.

Sometimes domain names do not get renewed because the business
that owned them is no longer operational. Sometimes the business
still exists but has found it no longer wants or needs a domain
name. Quite often the bottom feeders will allow their
unpurchased domain names to expire because they don't have the
funds to purchase them again or they feel the domains are no
longer marketable or profitable.

Occasionally, the domain name holder has died or lost interest
in their business or the internet. Once in a while a domain is
allowed to expire because it has attracted some maliciousness
and it cannot be maintained, and most often of all, the domain
name holder simply does not realize that it needs to be renewed.
In this last instance, the domain name is unintentionally
expired and someone can purchase it before the owner realizes
it.

In any event, regardless of why a domain name expires, you can
often find yourself in a position to purchase one that has been
previously owned. Note that in addition to expired domains, you
can also purchase domain names on the after-market (by making
bids) or from the domain name resellers (the bottom feeders
mentioned above).

Some Advantages Of Using Pre-Owned Names

The name was part of a link exchange - Webmasters work hard to
get their sites involved in link exchanges. This means the
domain names are listed on other sites, and this is useful for
getting traffic. If you take over a domain name, you can inherit
these incoming links and the resulting traffic.

It was listed in Yaho, DMOZ and/or Looksmart - A small industry
has sprung up recently, which consists simply of selling tools
and reports to allow people to quickly find domain names which
are listed in Yahoo, DMOZ, Looksmart or other directories yet
have expired. By expiring, these domain names are up for grabs,
and all of the resulting benefits for the original site transfer
to the new site. For a well placed entries, this can literally
mean hundreds of thousands of hits per month.

There are hundreds of thousands of sites listed in Yahoo and
millions in DMOZ. Anywhere from a few dozen to a few hundred
expire each month. Eventually the expiration would be discovered
and the entry removed. However, if someone purchases the domain
name quickly enough, the entry will remain and you will gain
that traffic.

It has a good page rank in Google - Another thing that
webmasters work very hard on is gaining page rank with Google,
the number one search engine. A high page rank implies that the
site appears nearer the top in search results pages. When you
purchase a domain, you can inherit the resulting page rank and
traffic. Note that you will need to duplicate the page or pages
referred to by Google in order for this to work properly.

The Downside Of Using Pre-Owned Names

You inherit spam - If the previous owner received spam email,
then when you take over the domain you may very well inherit it.
Why is this? Well, when you own a domain name, you get the email
sent to every single username on that domain. Of course, most
email servers are smart enough to "bounce" email messages for
users who do not exist, but that email still gets sent to the
server. For a domain which received a lot of spam, it could mean
a significant amount of bandwidth used just for junk messages to
non-existent users.

You can inherit robot activity - I got a domain once which
someone had listed with a number of robots (programs which
perform automatic functions). These robots were exceptionally
active and caused a tremendous amount of traffic - so much so
that I had to give up using the domain for a couple of months
until the robots stopped visiting.

You might inherit enemies - Sometimes people give up domain
names for a reason. One of those reasons might be an enemy -
someone (or a group) that is targeting the name for some
malicious act. For example, the name might be the target of
email bombs or denial-of-service attacks. In these instances,
you could find yourself inheriting these issues.

The domain could be banned - If a site gets involved in
spamming search engines (attempting to fool them for higher
placement on the results pages), it can be banned. By purchasing
these old domain names, you might be similarly banned. This
normally would not effect your existing domains, but it might
reduce the value of the domain name that you purchased.

Things to do before giving up a domain name

Be sure you really want to expire the domain - Once someone
else purchases your domain name, you may find it impossible or
very expensive to get it returned. You will lose access to the
use of the name entirely. So be sure that you want to give it up
before you actually allow it to expire.

Be aware of expiration dates - Keep an eye on your domain name
expiration dates as you may not get notified by the registrar
before expiration. This can happen because email is not a
perfect delivery system, because of a glitch in the registrar
system or even because you didn't check your mail or email for
the renewal. Don't accidentally lose your domain names.

Change your email addresses - Once you lose access to a domain,
you will lose access to any email that is going to that domain.
Think of all of the private emails that you get, and imagine
them going to strangers. Well, once someone else gets the domain
he may receive those private emails.

Change any links that you can - If you are allowing a domain to
expire, be sure you salvage any links that you might want to
keep. While you can do this after a domain name expires, it
makes more sense to do it beforehand. For example, if you had
owned three domains that all went to the same web site and you
allowed two of them to expire, you might want to spend the time
to change the links to the domain name that you keep.
Recently, I was asked "What are the core basics that someone
who wants to move beyond 'beginner' needs?"

Well, that's an interesting question that I actually get asked
quite a bit. You see, I have been "in the business" for 25
years. I started as a programmer on the old 16-bit PDP-11
computers (when 128KB of memory cost $10,000 and fit in a
refrigerator box, and a 10mb disk was HUGE) back in the late
'70s. I moved up to "operating systems guru" on the "new" 32-bit
operating system called VMS. I was actually quite good, and
could program assembly language faster than virtually everyone
could code BASIC (someone dared me to prove this once so we
took out a stopwatch and programmer a database application, and
I finished it in a quarter the time as the expert BASIC
programmer).

>From there, I moved onwards to design and analysis as well as
project management, then to higher management (working my way
up to a Vice President). Now I am a director of a multi-billion
dollar company (Director of computer operations and technical
services).

Why tell you this? I've managed hundreds of people and have to
deal with the question virtually every day (now I manage about
a dozen). People (from my own department and others) ask me
questions like: What should I do next? What training should I
be doing? Should I be attending conferences? What books should
I be reading? I always answer carefully, as this could mean the
difference between employment or unemployment, or a good raise
and a not-so-good raise. I want people to do well, so I try very
hard to guide them properly.

What is the most important thing I've learned? Perhaps it
sounds corny, but it's the ability to look and to see what's
actually there. To examine a problem and see the problem, with
no bias or assumptions. To look at a project plan and pick out
all of the assumptions (which can then be tested for accuracy),
or to look at a program and see the bugs or flaws.

An example? Sure. Someone I knew worked for one of my peers.
Over a period of several weeks, I kept hearing about a severe,
horrible problem which was delaying a major project. It was not
my project and I did not manage the person, and had my own fires
going, so only heard about this in the weekly meetings. This guy
worked on this problem for weeks, literally weeks. He changed
code over and over, tested and retested, had meeting after
meeting, involved a dozen other people and spent tens of
thousands of dollars of consulting money.

One day I happened to pass him in the halls and got into a
conversation about the problem. I could see he was upset and
decided I could possibly lend a few words of advice. He
described the issue and my jaw dropped open. He was trying to
figure out why some critical numbers were not being transferred
from the payroll system to the general ledger. It was critical
that these numbers show up in the general ledger.

I successfully kept from laughing out loud as I explained that
the payroll numbers didn't show up on the general ledger
because the payroll programs didn't post to the general ledger.
It was quite simple really, and if he had taken the time to
actually ask the users he would have discovered that they
hand-entered the numbers after each payroll. What happened was
one week the numbers didn't get to the general ledger and he
assumed there was a problem. If he had simply looked at what
was there to be seen, he would have discovered that the payroll
person was out sick that week. A temp had run payroll, and
hadn't known to enter the numbers in general ledger. It was
that simple. There actually was not a problem at all, yet we
spent over 200 man-hours and twenty-five thousand dollars to
try and find it!

The second most important lesson is that people are important.
People are not machines, they are not commodities and they are
not objects to be manipulated. People have feelings and they
are to be allowed to be themselves, to have rights and freedoms.
That does not mean you let them do whatever they want (you have
to manage things if you are a manager) but you have to
understand, communicate and respect them.

Why is this important? If you treat people badly or don't
communicate with them you will find them uncooperative and
even belligerent at times.

I've solved so many problems that simply resulted from treating
people like trash that it's mind numbing. I remember a time that
Sam, a colleague of mine, was trying to set up some testing time
with our users. He could not get them to test anything. He
complained over and over that they didn't understand how
important this was and they were sabotaging his project.

I talked to some of these users and found out what was really
going on. Sam was simply not communicating well. He was trying
to set up meetings and get testing from people who were already
overworked because it was quarter-end and they had books to
close. He was demanding their time and kept telling them they
had to help. He didn't seem to care about them, and thus they
didn't care about his project.

I knew this was important so I told him I would get his testing
done. He agreed, and I individually talked to each person, and
found that they really did want to be involved. They just
wanted to be treated like human beings. I called some lunch
meetings and bought everyone pizza and soda to discuss the
issues (even remembering the vegetarian pizza for the
non-meat-eating members of the group). I worked with their
bosses to arrange schedules and sent special thank you notes to
everyone (carefully carbon copying their supervisors). Before
long, the entire team was involved and the tested was completed.

The third most important thing is "be completely and totally
ethical at all times". Never, ever violate your integrity.

For example, I had a boss named Gary who assigned me to create
a warehouse system. I wanted to talk to the customer, find out
what they wanted, then write a proposal, get it approved, write
a specification, get it approved, then write a more detailed
design specification, and finally write the code. My boss didn't
like that at all. He said the customer wanted results, not paper
and words.

He told me to shut up and watch an "expert" at work. Gary then
spent one hour (!) interviewing the customer, then told me to
start writing code. I protested, but was young and dumb and did
what he said.

The effect was catastrophic. The system took ten times longer
than expected, required thousands of man hours to debug and has
been a maintenance nightmare. Why? Because we could not do what
the customer wanted for the simple reason that we did not ask
them, then tell them back what they said (and repeat until
done). That's the only way to be sure you are doing the right
thing. What we wound up doing was writing and rewriting and
rewriting until we got it right.

The final irony? Years later the customer asked me why we
hadn't written a proposal, a specification and a design
specification. They said it would have sure made things a lot
easier for them! Now that I'm older and wiser, I would have
held my ground and done the right thing regardless of what the
"expert" thought.

The next thing to do is to do the best possible job that you
can do. So do whatever you need to do to understand your job.
Read books, attend seminars, network with peers, go to classes
and continue to learn every single day. That's right, set aside
some time every single day to get better at your job.

If you want to be a webmaster, then BE a webmaster. Learn what
it means, learn how to do it, and learn what you need to learn.
Then put your learning to work and be the best webmaster you
can possibly be. Create excellent web sites and deliver
excellent products to your company, your users and your
customers.

The final advice, perhaps the most important thing of all, is
to be happy with what you do. Be happy with your job. After all,
you spend a fair portion of your life, perhaps the majority of
your life, working. If you don't enjoy what you do, then are you
truly happy?

I've seen more people miserable with their jobs that I like to
think about. People who are hanging on to collect a pay check
instead of doing something they really like.

I know none of this appears to have anything to do with
computers or the internet or anything else, but it does,
believe me.

We IT people tend to be introverted, we tend to think of
computers as more important than people, and we tend to have
these huge, silly biases which do nothing but make our lives
difficult. All of this gets in the way of doing our jobs and,
more importantly, being happy with what we do.

So learn and continue to learn. Be happy and stay ethical.
Treat others with respect and communicate freely and opening
with everyone. And be the best that you can possibly be. That's
the advice that I will give anyone who asks.
I'm sure you've all heard the expression, "the customer is
king". Some companies live by this rule - and those tend to do
very well. Others say the words but, well, they're just words.
These companies do not do as well. And other companies don't
have a clue. These companies might be huge, but they tend to
fall without warning. Many times the clueless companies turn
out to be made of paper - one ill wind is all it takes to cave
them in entirely.

I know you've run into those companies do not have a clue that
this datum even exists. These are the web hosting firms that do
not return support requests (and sometimes even requests for
quotations), free hosts which shut off accounts that have more
than a dozen page views and email providers who delete emails
with minimal notice.

These are the grocery stores with incredibly long lines, yet
there are registers closed and workers loafing. These are the
consulting firms that charge for every single thing (rounded up
to the hour, of course), yet never seem to be there when you
need them. And these are those that only allow returns within a
week, exchanges only, with receipt and a little begging thrown
in.

Then there are those corporations which mouth the words, yet
seem to have misunderstandings on what they mean. This is the
huge company which creates licensing contracts which require an
advanced degree in law and an ancient Latin dictionary to
decipher. The massive, 184KB long privacy policy put out by
another company comes to mind. This also includes the auto maker
who refuses to acknowledge the placement of their gas tanks
kills people, and the tire maker who will not admit their tires
are unsafe.

And sometimes, very occasionally, you will run across a company
which knows exactly what it means to say "the customer is
king". This includes the most fantastic auto maker of them
all - Saturn. These people know how to run a company. I've
owned two Saturns, and both ran perfectly. The dealer fixed
problems under warranty on several occasions even though the
warranty had run out. When they took too long on a completion
estimate for service, they did the work for free. And on every
visit to the service department, they have given me soda and
snacks for free and went to great pains to ensure that I was
happy and satisfied. And you know what, I have bought two
Saturns and I know that my next car will be one as well.

I hired a consulting company recently to do quite a bit of
work for me. The project manager made it completely clear to
me that if I was unhappy about anything he would personally go
out of his way to fix, at his cost, what was wrong. He has come
through on several occasions, including refunding our money on
half a dozen occasions. The result: when I needed something
done I called them first.

I've been a programmer, designer, analyst, manager, VP and
director for various companies over the past twenty years.
I've always lived by this rule, and I've always demanded it
from vendors and companies with which I do business.

You always treat customers well. Good, paying customers are
like gold in the world, and you always treat them right. You
don't need to "take it" from them, you simply treat them with
respect. Treat your customers well.

When I managed a shop of 12 consultants we had a strict policy:
the customer must be happy with our work. If the customer is
unhappy, we would work for free or give the money back or come
to some agreement to make him happy. Sometimes, of course,
there were those customers who could never be happy with
anything - those we simply didn't do business with at all. The
customer must treat us with a measure of respect, after all,
but we always felt we were in the drivers seat.

This applies to the job as well. In my organization, my
"customers" are my users, the people who use the computers
which we support. We practice "the customer is king" all of
the time, every day of the week. If I get a call from a user on
a weekend at 2 am, I make sure he gets the help he needs. When
the CEO's laptop breaks, he gets a new one as fast as possible;
and when the receptionist needs a new program installed it's
done just as quickly.

I've written about this before, and one person wrote back, "In
my experience, kowtowing to clients or customers, bending to
their every whim no matter how ludicrous, and keeping a fake
smile plastered on your face while you utter 'Thank you sir!
May I have another?' is a sure-fire recipe for misery."

Ah, the poor fool simply does not understand. You don't
"kowtow". You provide service and give respect to your
customers.

But what about those abusive customers? The customer who is
never satisfied or demands his money back or whatever?

These are the exceptions. Most people are good, honest and
hard working. They want to do good, and they want a good
product or service. Most people are perfectly willing to pay
for value received, and most people do not make life difficult.

Those that do are exceptions to this rule. Most people are
good, not evil. So treat the vast majority as good, and treat
the exceptions appropriately. Remember, you don't have to
accept money from anyone, but once you do they are customers.

If you are a consultant, give the best value that you can,
then give a little more. If the customer is a complete jerk,
then don't do business with him at all. You don't have to
accept the money!

And that's what I've got to say about that.
Wired magazine recently reported (on July 27, 2002), "Afraid
that Peru may adopt a bill decreeing the use of open-source
software in all government systems, Microsoft apparently
enlisted the American ambassador in Lima to help try to
convince the Peruvians to kill the legislation."

Many people have stated they feel it was wrong (even evil) for
a US ambassador to "lobby for Microsoft". Playing the devil's
advocate for a moment, let me ask the following question: if
an American citizen was having trouble in a foreign country
would it be okay for an ambassador to help him or her out?
What if an American company needed help in a foreign country?
Is it okay then? Why would Microsoft be excluded? What is the
purpose of an ambassador? My understanding is these people
exist to further the goals and objectives of their country:
including the government, individuals and companies.

What is the job of the US government? To support it's citizens
(a government has no other valid purpose). You could argue that
supporting corporations directly or indirectly supports
citizens.

Ambassadors do not exist to stop wars or make war talk.
They exist to further the goals of a government, and a
government exists to further the goals of the majority of
it's citizens. If I owned a company I would totally expect any
US government organization to cooperate fully with my business,
especially if by cooperating the goals of my country were also
furthered.

This bill seems to say that the government wants to use open
source for it's systems. This is perfectly fine as a government
should use whatever software it feels is the best fit for it's
goals.

Open source is not a product, it describes an idealized way to
develop and maintain a product. Most so called open source is
worthless junk that most people would not dare put on their
computers. By far the great majority of this kind of code is
never finished, poorly documented, virtually unmaintained and
so full of bugs and security holes that it's laughable.

That being said, the same is true, of course, of all other
forms of software.

Now there are some great open-source products, and when people
speak of open source they usually mean something like Apache,
Linux, Unix, OpenOffice and the hundreds (and perhaps thousands)
of tools and utilities available. These are the products that
have given open source a good name.

However, I have never heard of open source accounting packages,
SCADA systems (systems that control water, power and oil
systems), factory control systems, military systems and so on.
These things are either developed in house or purchased from a
company.

Peru may be making an error because they are thinking
"open-source means good programs not created by Microsoft". It
will be interesting to see what happens when they attempt to
find an open source SCADA system to control a hydro-electric
dam or an open source payroll system.

Personally, I don't care whether or not something is open
source, closed source, proprietary, GNU or anything else. The
software must meet the needs of the project or it's useless.
The Software must be maintainable and have a reasonable promise
of future maintenance. It must perform all required functions
and as many optional functions as needed. The product must have
a good ROI (return on investment) as well.

I've been managing large projects for 25 years, and return on
investment is usually the part that is missed by most technical
people. We look at the cost of a product and think, "wow, this
is free and this is $425, I'll get the free one".

That equation, unfortunately, does not work. The cost of a
product must be measured over it's entire lifetime and includes
many variables. These include training (teaching people how to
use it and keep it going as well as changing it), maintenance,
security, hardware, "fit" to the requirements, and dozens (if
not hundreds) of other things. I've found that once ALL of the
variables are factored in, Microsoft does not come out as bad
as most people would like to think.

Microsoft is being a little heavy handed here, and I'm somewhat
surprised that the US Government is playing along. I don't see
any vital US interests threatened.

However, one must remember that there were no vital US interests
threatened in Guatemala in the 1950s. There were just the Dole
banana farms, which were in danger of being taken over by the
democratic government. So good old president Eisenhower ordered
the CIA to overthrow that government and replaced it with a much
less democratic version, which, of course, was "smart enough" to
leave the Dole banana farms alone. Don't believe me, read your
history books. (This is one of the more despicable chapters in
American history - aiding in the overthrow of a legitimate
government so that some banana company would not be
inconvenienced.)

Point being the government may not in actually have a vital
interest at stake, but the officials may, or large corporations
which have contributed lots of money may as well. This might
make the government do things which, on the face of it, make no
sense (and on deeper analysis still don't make any sense).

So am I opposed to Microsoft's attempt to stop Peru? Of course
as it is meddling in the affairs of another country. Do I
understand why it's doing this? Of course. And do I understand
why the US government is playing along? Sure, it's pretty
obvious. 
I've been following the discussion about Google and mirrored
information for some time. It is "common knowledge" that Google
penalizes page rank when it determines that content is
duplicated somewhere else. In fact, I've read many experts
stating that there should be no duplicate domain names and no
duplicate content anywhere.

On the face of it the arguments appear to be sound. Google
obviously has several billion pages in it's database and could,
it appears, easily determine if content is duplicated. It also
seems, again on the face of it, that it's reasonable to check
for duplicate content, as this is the "mark of a spammer" and
not necessary on the web with hyperlinking available. At least,
this is the common wisdom.

However, sometimes what seems reasonable and possible is not:
not by a long shot.

Let's begin with the technical side of things. You've got
domain x and domain y with exactly the same content. How on
earth would Google be able to figure that out? Let's say Google
had 3 billion pages in it's database. To compare every page to
every page would be an enormous task - quadrillions of
comparisons.

Now, if site x had page "page1" which linked to site y which
also had "page1", then it would be possible for Google to
determine the duplicate content. Conceivably, it could check
this out.

Not only is the task enormous, but the benefit is so tiny as to
be insignificant. Duplicate content does not imply in any way
shape or form spamming. In actual fact, a duplicate site is
generally going to lower page rank of BOTH sites. Instead of
having 100 links to one site, there will presumably be 50 links
to one and 50 to another. This would tend (all things being
equal) to lower the page ranking of both sites. So Google gains
nothing by this incredible expenditure of resources.

There are several reasons for duplicate content which have
nothing to do with spamming. Sometimes the content is actually
duplicated, and sometimes it's just that there are several
different domains (at least the www and non-www versions) for
the same website

Mirroring a site for load balancing - This is very common. The
purpose is to split up the traffic between two copies of the
site.

Mirroring for region - Sometimes site mirroring is done simply
to make it more efficient on the internet backbone itself. You
might put an identical copy of a site in Europe, for example,
to reduce traffic across the Atlantic, which should make it
faster in European countries.

Viral marketing - It's extremely common to allow other sites to
republish articles in return for a link.

Different domain names - Sometimes a site might be referenced
on many different domain names. You might want to allow the
.com,.net and.org versions of the name to all work the same,
you might allow for common misspellings or you might cover
different keywords (sewing-tips and sewing-secrets are examples
of possible combinations).

Different domain names for different markets - you might also
want to reference your site by different names in order to
target different markets. You could, for example, have a site
about search engine optimization and want to target both SEO
and web designers. Thus domain names like seo.com and
webdesign.com would make sense.

www - Any good webmaster knows his or her site needs to be
referenced with and without the www.

Okay, so what's the smart thing to do? Well, it is possible
that search engines do compare a limited number of pages to
check for duplication. They could certainly check if someone
reported something, and they might check directly linked pages
(although this is still a heck of a lot of overhead for very
little benefit).

Of course, Google and the other search engines can account for
a hefty percentage of the traffic received by a site. In fact,
sometimes the number can exceed 70 percent. So it's wise to
spend some time ensuring that you are totally clean when it
comes to search engine optimization. In other words, a
technician from any search engine should be able to examine
your site down to it's smallest detail and find no evidence of
any kind of search engine spamming (attempting to get higher
rankings by unethical means). This is absolutely critical to a
site's survival for the long term.

Keeping that in mind, here's what I tend to do.

Multiple domains - Using multiple domains to the same site has
a tremendous number of advantages. Thus, I tend to follow the
advice given by others: take advantage of permanent redirection.
In other words, set up a redirection (a 301 status code) which
simply tells the browser "this page has moved, proceed to this
page, and the move is permanent. This tells the spider about the
redirection with no possibility of misunderstanding, yet allows
for the multiple domains.

Republished articles - I allow others to republish many of my
articles, and at this time I have records of over 10,000 of
them all over the internet on thousands of web sites. This is
not a problem, as these articles are sent in text format. The
webmaster must then drop this text into his site, which requires
some reformatting and shuffling around. Thus, the finished
articles may have the same text but the formatting is very, very
different. This is a highly respected method of gaining a large
number of incoming links: I give you something (an article,
i.e., content) and you give me something (a link back to my
site).

Mirroring - I haven't needed to do this yet, so I have no advice
as to what to do if a site requires actual, physical multiple
versions of itself. I would tend to just do it overtly (out in
the open) and not worry about it.

