It never turns fall, but I think about my mother, and how she disliked the cold. She grew up in the south, and we ended up on the North Shore of Chicago, on Lake Michigan. It's in the snow belt, where the winters are dark and grey for months and the wind off the Lake gives the city it's other name, "The Windy City." When the funkia started to bloom, a sure sign that winter was coming, I cannot but remember how she would start to withdraw, like the woman Edna St. Vincent Millay writes about in her poem, "When the Year Grows Old."

I cannot but remember
When the year grows old --
October - November --
How she disliked the cold!

She used to watch the swallows
Go down across the sky,
And turn from the window
With a little sharp sigh.

And often when the brown leaves
Were brittle on the ground,
And the wind in the chimney
Made a melancholy sound,

She had a look about her
That I wish I could forget -
The look of a scared thing
Sitting in a net!
Oh, beautiful at nightfall
The soft spitting snow!
And beautiful the bare boughs
Rubbing to and fro!
But the roaring of the fire,
And the warmth of fur,
And the boiling of the kettle
Were beautiful to her!
I cannot but remember
When the year grows old --
October - November --
How she disliked the cold!
There's no reason you can't add the roaring of a fire, the warmth of fur and the boiling of the kettle to your home in the winter to help lift your spirits. The way you feel as the dark, cold winter progresses is now called SAD (seasonal affective disorder.) It has to do with the change in the levels of sunlight and affects some people more than others. Like the bear in hibernation, those most affected would like to stay curled up all day, on the edge of sleep, with no energy for people, sex, or exercise, layering their body with fat because they crave carbohydrates.

There's no need to feel like a scared thing sitting in a net, when you've made your house cheery and cozy, and warmth, beauty and rich colors surround you. You know you'll be inside more in the winter, and doing less, so make it as lovely as you can. We can take a tip from the Russians, who really know winter.

Here (http://www.zinos.com/authors/1/AU01703/AR008456_img ) is a photo of my tour group in Russia, on the Island of Kizhi. The cabins feature one large room, with a very low ceiling and ceiling, wall and floor are all made of wood. You can imagine the glow from the fireplace. In the corner opposite the hearth, which is considered sacred, there's an icon.

Homes in Russian villages are brightly painted on the outside as you can see here: http://www.webstrategies.cc/nancy_and_babushka.jpg. The windows, which are not standardized, are ornate, and the villages look like fairylands against the snow. We do not want to camouflage ourselves in the snow. We want to shout out like the bright red cardinal: "Hey! I'm here! I'm alive! I'm surviving!"

Sitting there in the primitive cabins on Kizhi, it was easy to imagine Neanderthals huddled around a fire, getting as close together as they could to one another and to their animals, borrowing body heat and limbic connection. When it's very cold, the Eskimos refer to a "three-dog night." In the Kidzhi larger cabins, one of the "rooms" was a winter barn for the livestock where the animals spent the winter.

I always start "nesting" in the fall. I want to stay home more, and start doing handwork again - sometimes knitting sweaters, sometimes needlepoint pillow or pictures. I keep the home fires burning, cooking more, making heart stews and steamy chilis, and bake homemade bread--the staff of life.

What can you do to make your home "warmer" in the winter? Work with that primitive scene - the furs, the closeness, the color of fire, the need to hunker down.

1. Being prepared helps us feel secure.
Signal change is coming by changing things like slip covers, throw pillows, afghans, accent pieces and towels. Have winter slip covers in fabrics with pile, such as velvet and corduroy, in deep colors of the fire. Deep jewel tones, dark golds, rich magentas and burnt oranges, and a splash of ultraviolet blue, the floor of fire at its hottest.

1. Have winter slip covers in fabrics with pile, such as velvet or corduroy, in deep colors of the fire. Deep jewel tones, dark golds, rich magentas and burnt oranges, a splash of ultraviolet blue, the color of fire at its hottest.
Bring out warm accent pieces like pillows with your handwork, and afghans with large chunky cable stitches. Make use of fur.

2. Bring the furniture in closer to other pieces and to the fireplace, so people can figuratively "huddle." Add throw rugs for extra depth.

3. Buy a Lab to curl up by the fireplace. J.k. about buying one for the occasion, but since its such a comforting and visible scene get him a special winter bed.

4. Change out the bedspreads and duvets to winter fabrics and color scheme. Use flannel sheets.

5. Put something bright on the outside of your home - door mat, door decoration, mailbox cover, or wall mounting to signal your haven from the cold as you enter from the outside.

6. Build a collection of winter photos - the kids playing in the snow, family skiing, etc. Happy winter memories warm the tummy.

7. Don't forget the bathroom. If you keep a neutral wallpaper and carpeting, it's an easy to room to change because it's small. Change towels, soaps and shower curtain when the season changes using the same warm, enveloping colors and fabrics.

8. Work with the lighting. Change lamp shades in the living areas so they "glow". Choose warm colors of yellow, orange and red. Better yet buy one of those salt lamps from Czechoslovakia. The lamp itself is a block of salt which makes the prettiest glow, and is said to ionize as well.

9. If you don't have a fireplace, buy a wood stove or space heaters.

12. Make it smell good. Do some real cooking on the weekends when everyone's home. Few of us get to walk in the door at night and smell the pot roast cooking or the wonderful odor of stew simmering on the back burner any more, but you can do this on the weekend. Make special breads as well. If you're not allergic to candle aromas, work with those. Cinnamon and vanilla are favorite homey scents.
Even a touch or two can make a difference.

13. Have fireplace accessories of gold, brass or pewter, metals you sink into, not bounce off of.

14. Comfort depends on safety. Get the carbon monoxide detectors, escape ladders, smoke alarms, smoke guards, creosote removers, stove boards and hearth extenders, and choose a hearth rug for safety as well as ambiance.

15. Put a bird feeder in one window. There's nothing like watching a cardinal hop around on the window sill to cheer.
Stay warm! 
Are you bracing yourself for December, unsure what to celebrate and how? Here's what you can do:
D... iversity
In today's multicultural world, and office, there will likely be many faiths represented during the holiday season. You can't assume any longer that everyone's celebrating Christmas, or even Christmas and Hannukah. Familiarize yourself with all the holidays coming up: Bodhi Day or Rohatsu (Buddhist), December 8th; Fiesta of Our Lady of Guadalupe (Mexican), December 12th; St. Lucia Day (Swedish), December 13th; Hannukah (Jewish), December 16th-23rd; Winter Solstice (various-Shabe Yalda in Iran, Dong Shi in China, Yule), December 221/22; Christmas, December 25th; Kwanzaa (African American), December 26th; Boxing Day (Australia, Canada, England, Ireland, Scotland), December 26th; and Omisoka (Japanese), December 29th, Hajj begins (Islam); Eid al Adha, Islam, 31st; Christmas in Russia, January 7th.
E... mphasize education
It isn't an either/or thing, nor is it a matter of who's right or wrong, or which is better. If we approach it as learning about other people's celebrations, and other cultures, then everyone wins. I'm reminded of my small friend Emilio who heard about Hanukkah at preschool and decided 7 nights of presents was a better deal than Christmas, "Can we switch?" he asked. OK, that's a bit materialistic, but I liked his enthusiasm and inclusivity.
C... elebrate
There's a reason why many cultures have a winter religious or cultural celebration. It's because we need it in the depth of winter. Apparently it all began with the Winter Solstice celebrations (lunar, around December 22nd) when early people were dreadfully concerned that the dying light meant the end of things if they didn't do something about it. They would burn Yule logs, dance and decorate their dwellings with evergreens in the hopes the sun would return one day.
E... cumenical
Many of the December holidays are religion-based. Ecumenical comes from the Greek word oikoumenikos meaning the inhabited world; worldwide or general in extent, influence or application, and more particularly representing the whole body of churches, or shall we say institutions of worship. Having chaired the Development Board for the Ecumenical Center in San Antonio, TX., which was designed to focus on what the different religions have in common, rather than what they do not, I can assure there are commonalities. These December celebrations focus on celebrating life and goodness, family, kindness, comfort in the cold, darkness of the winter season, and, in some cases, the deity.
M... enorahs next to Christmas trees?
Charles Haynes, executive director of First Liberty Institute at George Mason University says neither imposing one's faith on others, nor removing all traces of religion should be the goal. "Neither position makes sense in a multicultural society," he says. "And significantly, neither approach has successfully resolved the 'December dilemma.' What is at stake is far more than a school nativity pageant or Christmas concert in December. At issue is an urgent question that runs through modern experience: How will we live with our deepest differences in an increasingly pluralistic society?"
B... liny (Russia), Black and White Pudding (France), Biscuits of Gingerbread (Germany)
Food is an integral part of any celebration. If you have a multicultural office, or want to bring this out and encourage it, include different national festive foods at the Holiday Office party. But remember, it's counter-productive to ask the Hungarian to bring goulash, etc. Make a list of different foods as suggestions; then ask people to volunteer. If Alexei then wants to bring bliny, he can. If not, he can choose something else.
The spirit is openness to having fun, learning something, tasting some fabulous food and celebrating community together! This is a long tradition in many offices because of the cost of different items. Just as you have things on the list such as paper plates and plastic ware, leave your multicultural party list open to accommodate for different culinary skills, preferences and budgets.
E... nlightenment comes with celebrating.
Mary Baldwin, who is a Volunteer Director at a Homeless Shelter says "We celebrate Christmas and any other winter holidays, in all their diversity. With decorations, stories, food and music, we share our traditions of Santa, the Nativity, the dreidel, Kwanzaa, ski trips, cruises to the Bahamas, or hunting trips."
R... ituals and traditions
It's our traditions and rituals that shape us as a people and as a society. The more we know about, understand, and respect one another's rituals, the better chance we have of living in harmony. 
We're coming down to the wire. How's it feeling to you?

Why do I ask that? Well, whatever you're celebrating, and whatever your religious orientation, Christmas is a celebration, a celebration that for many has a spiritual basis to it. That is, it's supposed to be merry, at the least, and meaningful at the most. What's it for you this year?

There may not be much you can do to put on the brakes now, but note how you're feeling so you can see how it's working for you. This has to be tested against the purpose of this celebration, which is personal to each of us, but surely it isn't to be exhausted, stressed, hateful, resentful, materialistic, imprudent, overwhelmed, obligatory, or "just going through the motions." If you're feeling "the thrill is gone," it's time to get mindful. Don't be the victim of your own holiday.

Remember, it's all about choice. Intentionality is the EQ competency for the holidays. What do you intend? How do your intend to feel? What do you intend to accomplish?

If you feel like you want to stop the world and get off, take note. When Christmas is over, process.

Ask yourself:

1. What worked and what didn't? In other words, what make you feel good. Feeling good can be pleasure, joy, but also the feeling of a job well done.

2. What did I do out of obligation, or to keep up with the Joneses that needs to be let go next year?

3. Did I feel the way I wanted to? If not, what will I do differently next year?

4. Take each element and analyze it - - did you really enjoy it, or were you just going through the paces? Was it "because we've always done it this way"?

5. Is there some traditional that's outworn it's welcome? If so, eliminate it. Kiss it goodbye, remembering it fondly, but let it go.

6. Whether you're a parent, grandparent, or uncle or aunt, there are children around. What kind of example are you setting? If you yell at your kid because you're stress out over Christmas, ho ho ho?

7. How materialistic were your gifts? How much did you bust your budget? Change this next year.

8. Did you spend time the way you wanted to? Did you spend time with the people you wanted to be with? Whether or not its family, you have a choice.

9. Did you actually have time to enjoy each thing - the smells, the touches, the sights, the sounds? Or were you like a hamster on his wheel?

10. What part of the negatives was due to your attitude rather than external events or circumstances? Controlling your mood and emotions with emotional intelligence can add tremendously to your life, not just at Christmas time.

The best gift in life is to be able to learn from your experiences and this is a great time to apply this. If you don't like what's going on, don't be a victim of your own circumstances or attitude. Change one or both! 
AT NINE o'clock on the morning of September 11th 2001, President George Bush sat in an elementary school in Sarasota, Florida, listening to seven-year-olds read stories about goats. “Night fell on a different world,” he said of that day. And on a different America.

At first, America and the world seemed to change together. “We are all New Yorkers now,” ran an e-mail from Berlin that day, mirroring John F. Kennedy's declaration 40 years earlier, “Ich bin ein Berliner”, and predicting Le Monde's headline the next day, “Nous sommes tous Américains”. And America, for its part, seemed to become more like other countries. Al-Qaeda's strikes, the first on the country's mainland by a foreign enemy, stripped away something unique: its aura of invulnerability, its sense of itself as a place apart, “the city on a hill”.

Two days after the event, President George Bush senior predicted that, like Pearl Harbour, “so, too, should this most recent surprise attack erase the concept in some quarters that America can somehow go it alone.” Francis Fukuyama, a professor at Baltimore's Johns Hopkins University, suggested that “America may become a more ordinary country in the sense of having concrete interests and real vulnerabilities, rather than thinking itself unilaterally able to define the nature of the world it lives in.”

Both men were thinking about foreign policy. But global terrorism changed America at home as well. Because it made national security more important, it enhanced the role of the president and the federal government. Twice as many Americans as in the 1990s now say that they are paying a lot of attention to national affairs, where they used to care more about business and local stories. Some observers noted “a return to seriousness”—and indeed frivolities do not dominate television news as they used to.

But America has not become “a more ordinary country”, either in foreign policy or in the domestic arena. Instead, this survey will argue that the attacks of 2001 have increased “American exceptionalism”—a phrase coined by Alexis de Tocqueville in the mid-19th century to describe America's profound differences from other nations. The features that the attacks brought to the surface were already there, but the Bush administration has amplified them. As a result, in the past two years the differences between America and other countries have become more pronounced.

Yet because America is not a homogeneous country—indeed, its heterogeneity is one of its most striking features—many of its people feel uneasy about manifestations of exceptionalism. Hence, as this survey will also argue, the revival and expansion of American exceptionalism will prove divisive at home. This division will define domestic politics for years to come.

Not all New Yorkers any more

From the outside, the best indication of American exceptionalism is military power. America spends more on defence than the next dozen countries combined. In the nearest approach to an explicit endorsement of exceptionalism in the public domain, the National Security Strategy of 2002 says America must ensure that its current military dominance—often described as the greatest since Rome's—is not even challenged, let alone surpassed.

In fact, military might is only a symptom of what makes America itself unusual. The country is exceptional in more profound ways. It is more strongly individualistic than Europe, more patriotic, more religious and culturally more conservative (see chart 1). Al-Qaeda's assaults stimulated two of these deeper characteristics. In the wake of the attacks, expressions of both love of country and love of God spiked. This did not necessarily mean Americans suddenly became more patriotic or religious. Rather, the spike was a reminder of what is important to them. It was like a bolt of lightning, briefly illuminating the landscape but not changing it.

The president seized on these manifestations of the American spirit. The day after he had defined America's enemies in his “axis of evil” speech, in January 2002, Mr Bush told an audience in Daytona Beach, Florida, about his country's “mission” in the world. “We're fighting for freedom, and civilisation and universal values.” That is one strand of American exceptionalism. America is the purest example of a nation founded upon universal values, such as democracy and human rights. It is a standard-bearer, an exemplar.

But the president went further, seeking to change America's culture and values in ways that would make the country still more distinctive. “We've got a great opportunity,” he said at Daytona. “As a result of evil, there's some amazing things that are taking place in America. People have begun to challenge the culture of the past that said, ‘If it feels good, do it'. This great nation has a chance to help change the culture.” He was appealing to old-fashioned virtues of personal responsibility, self-reliance and restraint, qualities associated with a strand of exceptionalism that says American values and institutions are different and America is exceptional in its essence, not just because it is a standard-bearer.

On this view, America is not exceptional because it is powerful; America is powerful because it is exceptional. And because what makes America different also keeps it rich and powerful, an administration that encourages American wealth and power will tend to encourage intrinsic exceptionalism. Walter Russell Mead of the Council on Foreign Relations dubs this impulse “American revivalism”. It is not an explicit ideology but a pattern of beliefs, attitudes and instincts.

The Bush administration displays “exceptionalist” characteristics to an unusual extent. It is more openly religious than any of its predecessors. Mr Bush has called Jesus his favourite philosopher. White House staff members arrange Bible study classes. The president's re-election team courts evangelical Protestant voters. The administration wants religious institutions to play a bigger role in social policy.

It also wears patriotism on its sleeve. That is not to say it is more patriotic than previous governments, but it flaunts this quality more openly, using images of the flag on every occasion and relishing America's military might to an unusual extent. More than any administration since Ronald Reagan's, this one is focused narrowly on America's national interest.

Related to this is a certain disdain for “old Europe” which goes beyond frustrations over policy. By education and background, this is an administration less influenced than usual by those bastions of transatlanticism, Ivy League universities. One-third of President Bush senior's first cabinet secretaries, and half of President Clinton's, had Ivy League degrees. But in the current cabinet the share is down to a quarter. For most members of this administration, who are mainly from the heartland and the American west (Texas especially), Europe seems far away. They have not studied there. They do not follow German novels or French films. Indeed, for many of them, Europe is in some ways unserious. Its armies are a joke. Its people work short hours. They wear sandals and make chocolate. Europe does not capture their imagination in the way that China, the Middle East and America itself do.

Mr Bush's own family embodies the shift away from Euro-centrism. His grandfather was a senator from Connecticut, an internationalist and a scion of Brown Brothers Harriman, bluest of blue-blooded Wall Street investment banks. His father epitomised the transatlantic generation. Despite his Yale education, he himself is most at home on his Texas ranch.

Looked at this way, the Bush administration's policies are not only responses to specific problems, or to demands made by interest groups. They reflect a certain way of looking at America and the world. They embody American exceptionalism.

American exceptionalism is nothing new. But it is getting sharper

“EVERYTHING about the Americans,” said Alexis de Tocqueville, “is extraordinary, but what is more extraordinary still is the soil that supports them.” America has natural harbours on two great oceans, access to one of the world's richest fishing areas, an abundance of every possible raw material and a huge range of farmed crops, from cold-weather to tropical. Not only is it the fourth-largest country in the world, but two-thirds of it is habitable, unlike Russia or Canada. Any country occupying America's space on the map would be likely to be unusual. But as de Tocqueville also said, “Physical causes contribute less [to America's distinctiveness] than laws and mores.”

In his 1995 book “American Exceptionalism,” Seymour Martin Lipset enumerates some of these laws and social features. In terms of income per head, America is the wealthiest large industrial country. It is also the only western democracy to have practised slavery in the industrial era. It has the highest crime rate and highest rate of imprisonment (though crime, at least, is falling towards European levels). Its society is among the most religious in the world. Perhaps less obviously, Americans are more likely than almost anyone else to join voluntary associations.

America has a highly decentralised political system, with federal, state and local governments all collecting their own taxes, writing their own laws and administering their own affairs. Its federal government spends a relatively low share of national income. The country has more elective offices than any other, including, in some states, those of judges, which means that in each four-year cycle America holds about 1m elections. Not surprisingly, perhaps, it also has one of the lowest voter turn-outs, making it at once the most and the least democratic democracy.

It has no large socialist party, and never has had. Nor has it ever had a significant fascist movement. Unlike conservative parties in Europe, its home-grown version has no aristocratic roots. America has one of the lowest tax rates among rich countries, the least generous public services, the highest military spending, the most lawyers per head, the highest proportion of young people at universities and the most persistent work ethic.

But the term “exceptionalism” is more than a description of how America differs from the rest of the world. It also encompasses the significance of those differences and the policies based upon them. People have been searching for some wider meaning to the place since its earliest days. In 1630, the year the Massachusetts Bay Company was founded, John Winthrop, the colony's governor, described his new land as “a city upon a hill, the eyes of all people are upon us.”

And as they have looked, people have found two quite different reasons for thinking that America is special. One is that it is uniquely founded on principles to which any country can aspire. In 1787, Alexander Hamilton wrote in the first Federalist Paper that “It seems to have been reserved to the people of this country, by their conduct and example, to decide the important question, whether societies of men are really capable or not of establishing good government from reflection and choice, or whether they are forever destined to depend for their political constitutions on accident and force.”

That is America-as-model. George Bush has embraced the idea. Commemorating the first anniversary of the attacks of September 11th 2001, he said that “the ideal of America is the hope of all mankind.” He was echoing Lincoln, who called America “the last, best hope of earth”.

But exceptionalism has another meaning: that America is intrinsically different from other countries in its values and institutions, and is therefore not necessarily a model. Thomas Jefferson said that “Every species of government has its specific principles. Ours are perhaps more peculiar than those of any other in the universe.”

In 1929, Jay Lovestone, the head of the American communist party, was summoned to Moscow. Stalin demanded to know why the worldwide communist revolution had advanced not one step in the largest capitalist country. Lovestone replied that America lacked the preconditions for communism, such as feudalism and aristocracy. No less an authority than Friedrich Engels had said the same thing, talking of “the special American conditions...which make bourgeois conditions look like a beau idéal to them.” So had an Italian Marxist, Antonio Gramsci, and a British socialist, H.G. Wells, who had both argued that America's unique origins had produced a distinctive value system and unusual politics.

Lovestone was purged, but his argument still has force: America is exceptional partly because it is peculiar. As usual, de Tocqueville had thought about both meanings of exceptionalism before anyone else. In his book “Democracy in America”, he described not only what is particular to democracy, especially the way in which it changes how people think and act (what he calls “the quiet action of society upon itself”). He also described what was, and is, particular to America: its size, the institutions it had inherited from England, its decentralised administration.

These two versions of American exceptionalism have more in common than might appear at first sight. Both suggest that the experience of America is open to others. The idea of America-as-model implies that other countries can come to be more like America, though American differences may still persist over time. The idea that America is intrinsically different is also consistent with the notion that outsiders can become American, but they must go there to do it and become citizens—hence America's extraordinary capacity to assimilate immigrants.

There are three points to grasp from this gallop through the history of American exceptionalism. First, it is, as Mr Lipset put it, a double-edged sword. It helps explain the best and the worst about the country: its business innovation and its economic inequality; its populist democracy and its low voter turn-out; its high spending on education and its deplorable rates of infant mortality and teenage pregnancy. Exceptionalism is often used either as a boast or as a condemnation—though in reality it is neither.

Second, the two strands help explain why exceptionalism is divisive within America itself. Most Americans are doubtless proud of the “exemplary” qualities of their country. But the non-exemplary, more peculiar features do not always command universal approval.

Third, there should be nothing surprising, or necessarily disturbing, in a revival of exceptionalism. America has almost always been seen as different. The question is: has anything changed recently?

Unparallel tracks

It is always risky to proclaim a break in a trend. Yet evidence is growing that, over the past decade or so, America has been changing in ways that do make it more different from its allies in Europe, and September 11th has increased this divergence.

Most of the previous half-century was a period of convergence. Between 1945 and about 1990, America and Europe seemed to be growing more like one another in almost every way that matters. Economically, Europe began the post-war period in ruins. According to Angus Maddison, an economic historian, in 1950 average incomes in western Europe were 54% of American ones. By the early 1990s, the ratio had passed 80%. Richer EU countries now boast a standard of living comparable to America's. Until the mid-1980s, America and Europe also both had stable populations, declining fertility rates and growing numbers of old people.

In the 1960s, America moved closer towards European levels of government spending through the Great Society programmes. This was the start of Medicaid for the poor and, later, increased regulation of industry through bodies like the Environmental Protection Agency.

With Watergate and the Vietnam war, America started to approach European levels of cynicism about government and military intervention abroad. In 1976, a sociologist, Daniel Bell, wrote a book whose title encapsulated the conventional wisdom of the time: “The End of American Exceptionalism”. Later changes seemed to prove him right. In the 1980s, European countries started to organise their economies on more American lines. Governments privatised and deregulated. Companies listed on the New York Stock Exchange, set up NASDAQ clones and started using share prices to measure a company's or manager's performance.
