Question: In your FAQ's for Ask Jeeves/Teoma's pay inclusion
program (http://ask.ineedhits.com/faq.asp), it states that you
can't change URL's. Why?

Jim: "Because it's considered a new submission. We're not able to
put enough resources against it yet."

Question: So in the future, we'll have the ability to swap out
URLs?

Jim: "We'll see, but I hear you. We are aware of Inktomi's
program."

Question: What's the difference in traffic between the premium
listings and the "regular" search results?

Jim: "Do you mean between Premier Listings (Featured Sponsor) and
Paid Inclusion? There are two differences: 1) You are guaranteed
that your listing will show up; 2) You are guaranteed that it
will show up in a specific location on our page."

Question: Are Premier Listings twice as likely to be clicked on,
for example?

Jim: "Premier Listing is really just an ad. With Paid Inclusion,
you aren't paying for anything other than being included in the
index and then being subjected to the same relevance algorithms
that give us our other results, but with the other benefits that
I mentioned earlier.

"In terms of click ratio, I suppose it depends on how relevant
your site is to a given query. The match rate of a site that buys
ad space on our site is much more significant than one that
purchases via paid inclusion for now."

For more information about Premier Listings, visit:
http://static.wc.ask.com/docs/advertise/premier.html.

Question: Let's say that I have a Web site:
http://myownwebsite.com, and let's say that my goal is for it to
become an "authoritative" site in Teoma. Could you give us some
tips on what we can do to try to be considered by Teoma as an
authoritative or expert site on a particular subject?

Jim: "Our recommendations are as follows: 1) you allow people to
link to you; 2) you offer quality content so that you become
popular among other sites of the same subject (i.e., experts).
Basically, that's it. None of our expert sites or authorities are
manually decided. It's based on our algorithms."

Question: On Teoma, are Teoma and Ask Jeeves results combined?

Jim: "Well, there really is no such thing as an Ask Jeeves
result. There are pre-fab, editorially selected `answers' to
certain queries that may appear at the top of the page if we have
a high level of confidence that we have the right answer. But as
far as the actual search results go, it's all Teoma...and we'll
layer in the Direct Hit click-pop at some point soon."

Question: But Teoma results ARE being shown at Ask Jeeves?

Jim: "That's exactly right. The part of the AJ page that says,
`You may find these search results helpful' has the Teoma
results. They were launched in January (and by no coincidence, we
immediately saw a 30% increase in picks to those results.)"

Question: The "Featured Sponsor" section of Ask Jeeves, is that
the Premier Listings?

Jim: "Yes it is."

(End of interview/chat session)

Let's take a longer look at Teoma

If you haven't visited Teoma yet and performed a few searches,
you need to do so (http://www.teoma.com/). It's a really cool
engine with some very interesting and helpful features.

For example, it's a no-nonsense engine like Google with one
purpose only: search.

When you search at Teoma, you're given three sets of results:

* Results, which are relevant Web pages from the Teoma index;

* Refine, which are suggestions for narrowing your search;

* Resources, which are link collections from experts and
enthusiasts.

So with Teoma, if your search results are too broad, you can
immediately narrow them down by choosing one of the suggestions
in the Refine section.

And, in the Resources area, you'll find "experts" in that
particular focus area. This is an excellent place to find related
and important sites that might be good candidates to contact
about swapping links.

More on Ask Jeeves

Ask Jeeves is the "question answering" search engine, which puts
it into a class of its own. (http://www.askjeeves.com)

At the top of the search results, you'll see a "featured sponsor"
section, which is their Premier Listing advertisement that we've
discussed previously.

With some searches, you'll see a "sponsored links" section, which
are results currently being provided by Overture. However, on
September 3, Ask Jeeves will be switching to Google for their
paid listings.

Then, you'll find search results from Teoma, followed by a
section called, "Other people with your search have also asked:"
In that section, you'll see additional questions that may help
answer your initial question, with results coming from Ask.com.

Like at Teoma, you can narrow your search down by choosing one of
the search terms on the right-hand side of the page.

Ask Jeeves recently entered into an agreement with Google to
display their Google AdWords in Ask Jeeves results effective
September 3, 2002. Those results will be shown at both Ask Jeeves
and Teoma as "sponsored links." For more information, visit:
http://www.nytimes.com/aponline echnology/AP-Ask-Jeeves-
Google.html

In Conclusion

Teoma has taken over the old Direct Hit site, and I believe we'll
see some big things out of this fascinating engine in the future.

Ask Jeeves is as it's always been: unique - a place where you can
go and ask a question and be presented with several possible
answers.

If you haven't submitted your site to Ask Jeeves/Teoma, and if
your site isn't found in the Teoma index, I strongly suggest that
you consider their pay inclusion program and become a part of
their index.
We've all heard of dismal banner click-throughs of less than 1%
as being the industry standard.

This means that less than 1 person in 100 will actually click on
the banner displayed on the web page he's
looking at!

If you're an Associate selling a product via banners on your web
site, this is simply not good news.

Because you will never close 100% of your prospects. And if your
traffic count is only 100 a day, it would mean you only have 30
actual prospects a month (one a day). And assuming your
Principal's Killer Sales Letter sells one prospect out of every
10 (which is a great conversion rate, by the way),
you'll be making only 3 sales for the month.

But what if you could get all or almost all of those 100
visitors to click on your banner? You'll
have close to 3000 prospects, and 300 sales for the month based on the same
conversion rate!

You've just increased your sales by 100 times! But are we
dreaming here?

Here's the good news:

You CAN get almost ALL, if not all, your visitors to click on
the banners while they're at your site!

All you need to do is to understand a little psychology. Because
when you know the reasons why very few prospects ever click on a
banner when they see it, you'll be able to devise a strategy and
the right tactics to override their reasons and achieve whatever
you wanted them to do all along.

Get ready now. This is proven, exciting stuff!;-)

==============================================
THE REAL REASONS FOR LOW BANNER CLICK-THROUGHS
====================================================

They are so simple that
I'm still surprised why nobody even
thought of them, as I simply don't
see anything radical being
done to solve this problem. Here they are:

1. Most Banners Look Like An Ad
================================
Your visitors are not at your web site to look at banners. If
they are, you don't have to provide any content on your site.
Just slap up a web site containing banners, submit it to the
search engines and sit back and watch the millions come rolling
in.

Yeah, right.

2. Most Banners Are Placed In The Same Positions
==================================================
It's usually at the top of the web page, before the content of
the page is seen, or at the bottom, after the content of the
page. Now when you know that these 2 positions are usually where
banner ads are found, would your visitors even look at them when
they're waiting for your web page to load?

Of course not. They'll immediately scroll down or look elsewhere
to the first available text that make up your content! And
what's worst, your visitors are doing this subconsciously due to
habit. They quite simply and literally don't
see your banners!

That's it! With this knowledge, we can create miracles.

And I have.;-)

=========================
THE AMAZING, SIMPLE CURE
================================================

Now for the simple, magic "cure" that makes low banner
click-throughs a thing of history. It'll
require some work, but it's nothing you cannot do.

1. Re-Design Your Web Site
===========================
That's right. Keep your content, but:

i. dump the design where you have your banners at the top or
bottom of your web pages; AND

ii. dump the usual navigational buttons or links on the top,
left, right or bottom of your web pages

Do BOTH of the above. Then:

2. Make Your Content The Main Focus Of Your Site
=================================================
You can have a series of great original articles, with each
article having its own heading and web page. "Content" can take
many forms, however. Articles are only one form. A tutorial is
another. Whatever it is, your content takes center stage simply
because your visitors are there for your content, not your
banners. And you should give it to them first prior to leading
them on to clicking on your banners eventually.

3. Create A Table That Is Of The Same Width As Your Banner
========================================================
This table should have at least 3, 5 or 7 rows.

4. Put Your Banner In The Middle Row
========================================================
That's the reason for the table being at least the same width as
the banner. If your table has 3 rows, place your banners in the
2nd row. If it has 5 rows, place it in the 3rd row. If it has 7
rows, place it in the 4th row.

5. If You Have More Than One Banner To Display:
========================================================
Insert a javascript that rotates your banners within the table
with a new banner appearing every time a new page is loaded.

6. Now Fill Up The Other Rows With...
========================================================
...links to your other web pages on your site! You'll
need to divide these rows into several columns to accommodate the number
of links to your other pages. The more web pages you have, the
more rows and columns you'll need.

7. Then Place This Table At The BOTTOM Of Each Of Your Web Pages!
========================================================
By doing this, your visitors will first and foremost see your
content, before arriving at the navigational table that contains
the banner.

Putting it at the top of your page doesn't
make senze as we've established that he'll likely not click on
it in that position. Therefore your mission is to interest him immediately with your
content so that he'll want to navigate your site further,
subscribe to your e-zine or otherwise "warm up" to your site.

And once he's interested, and since he cannot otherwise navigate
around your web site without clicking on your table containing
links to the other pages on your site, he'll have to look at
your table of links containing the banner - with the banner
staring straight at him!

This will increase your banner click-throughs simply because
it's a novel way of displaying banners, and
he's now looking at your banner when previously he's been
ignoring it.

In addition, because the banner is in close proximity with the
links, you'll also get some "accidental" clicks!

See exactly how this is done on my site at http://www.senze.com
right now! (Note: I'm not putting up banners for products that
I'm an Associate of because that is not the business model for
my site. However, the principle is the same.)

===============================
HOW TO GET ALMOST 100% CLICKS ON YOUR BANNERS!
=====================================================

The above technique on its own will increase your banner clicks
many times over.

However, if you want to get almost ALL of your visitors to click
on your banners, take the following extra steps:

1. Re-Design The Banners Given To You!
======================================
Don't just put up banners given to you by the Associate Program
owner - because they all look like banners!
You'll need to create your own banners using your own words and make it blend
within the color and theme of your site.

If the color of your web site background is white, design the
banner in white. Don't even put a border around it!

Your mission is to make your banners not look like a banner.
Simple enough?

(Actually, a better solution is to dump the banner graphic and
simply put up a text link - but since
we're discussing how to increase banner clicks, we're not going
to do that.)

2. Dump The Animation!
============================
Animation is used by banner artists to draw attention to them.
However, they are synonymous with banners, and where they used
to work, they don't work now because animation screams
advertising.

Make your banners as plain as you can, as if it's
a link to another area of your site - which is the reason why their
background color should be the same as the background color of
your web site. Just don't make it look and sound like banners
normally do, and you've won half the battle already even at this
stage!

(Note: the banner on my site is animated, but I can afford to do
this because I'm selling a free subscription to my e-zine - which
forms my overall site in the first place. This reason overrides
the "disadvantage" of animating my banners - but if you're

placing your Principal's banner - make sure it's not animated
for the reason discussed here.)

====================
THE REFRESHINGLY SPECTACULAR END RESULT
==============================================
You'll get close to 100% click-throughs with a combination of
all the tactics above! Which means you'll
be a far happier, richer Associate, as well as being one of the rare breed of web
site owners out there who truly understand what Internet
Marketing is all about.

Try it out and see just what a HUGE difference a little brain
power can do! 
There are lots of excellent affiliate programs
out there and even lots more affiliates. But the
average guy hardly holds more than 3 sales to
his name.

All those top ranking marketing courses and
ebooks advise you to have your own mailing list-
'hot leads' as they call them. But to be able
to develop one responsive list you need to be a
'mini guru' yourself. It takes lots of
dedication, time and 'appetite' to be able to
build such a list.

Frankly, the average Joe hopped on the internet
in the first place to be able to grab some of
the gold floating around cyberspace and earn
some extra 'grub' anonymously...

Yes using the anonymity of a faceless email and
without all the hassles of an ordinary business...
building a 'mailing list' is simply a
non-attainable goal.

Other Stumbling blocks are:

- Loss of affiliate revenue due to affiliate
link theft.

- Non acceptance of affiliate links by search
engines.

- Loss of advertising revenue - Even though the
program claims for eg. 'sales copy is so good
every 6th person is signing up or buying' - the
affiliate orders guaranteed hits using traffic
exchanges only to be disappointed or feel a
temporary elation with a few sales...

All that advertising simply helps to create a
'buzz' about the program with no positive
impact to the affiliate...

Rarely if ever does anyone buy on a first visit
to the site and by the time they have been
'buzzed into hypnotic action' to buy, it's
definitely not from the first, second or even
third sites they visited. Also they usually buy
from someone who has an 'up-sell' offer,
someone to whose mailing list they already
belong or someone they have come to trust.

All is not lost however, you can master the
affiliate game yet... Without a mailing list.

So lets get started:

1. Prepare an independent web page for each
affiliate program with

- A magnetically irresistible title;

- followed by a bulleted list of benefits using
'grab them by the gut' writing.

- A link to the programs testimonial page.

- Provide third party validation with a link to
any other website such as epinions.com or scam
reporter or BBB etc that has some positive
comments listed about the program.

- If the program has a Newsletter or forum to
discuss expansion plans etc provide a link to it.

- Write about your own success you have had with
this program and add a link to some form of
proof such as photos of payment checks received.

- State your own 'up-sell' offer clearly and
make it time sensitive... (if you order through
my link by midnight you also get the following
ebooks, advertising, software etc).

- Make an offer of 'guaranteed' assistance - one
on one interaction through email or phone.

- State your full contact information clearly.

2. Compile the above page in an ebook format. You
can use any number of low cost ebook compilers
available out there.

3. Create another web page with an irresistible
headline, a bulleted list of benefits and a free
download link to your ebook.

4. Advertise the web page created in step 3 on
all the free traffic exchanges. You may order
real cheap guaranteed visitors to this page
(Just confirm with your web-host that your
website can handle the deluge of guaranteed
visitors).

Also make sure to monitor the number of times
your ebook is downloaded and which traffic
service gives you the maximum downloads - you
may use any of the link tracking services out
there.

Does this technique work... believe me it does.

Just pay special attention to steps 3 and 4.
Your copy in step 3 should make the kill, and in
step 4 create the loudest 'buzz' you possibly
can... even the most die hard web surfers will
not be able to resist the temptation to download
your free ebook and find out what it is all
about - then the rest depends on your 'upsell'
offer and sales letter in step 1.

Can you do this... you don't need a mailing list!
Yeah just drop the right bait and create a
'feeding frenzy' among the information hungry
fishes on the internet. 
Winter is just around the corner (except if you live
in Australia or New Zealand). As you already know
winter is the time for the sales fiesta on the
internet.

Yes online business starts booming with bumper to
bumper traffic on the e-freeways. Characterized by a
lack of good parking spots, loads of enthusiastic
first timers and a renewed vitality and surge of life
pulsating and throbbing it`s way along the e-super
highway.

Are you ready to meet this challenge head on and
harvest your share of this super bonanza?

Yes... if you have an interest in a better financial
flow you had better get set ready and go!

1. Tweak up your website for a better visitor to
sales conversion ratio - check your headlines, sales
letter, ultimate selling proposition - Does it
deliver your most wanted response?

2. Plan out a marketing strategy:

- What`s the bait you are going to use?

- How are you going to make the hungry fish to bite?

- Where will you get a strong steady flow of
targeted traffic?

- How will you time and manage your advertising to
maintain a synergistic flow of traffic without
aggravating your web host?

- Which advertising mediums you plan on using (ezines,
guaranteed visitors, viral techniques, site blasts,
articles...)?

3. Get set and ready to push into full gear at a
moments notice - Start placing the orders for your
advertising or at least shortlist the ad services you
plan to use. Remember it will be a busy time for every
one, with a rush to meet deadlines, blood pressures
surging, tempers flaring... so better get in the line
up well ahead to avoid any pitfalls.

Also Remember you only need a good sales page,
irresistible bait and a strong gushing tributary to
direct a heavy flood of potential shoppers from the
main stream to your shop.

Just make your shop as magnetic as possible and get
as many `tourists` to go through it as you can.
Crash! your half filled coffee cup shatters the
silence splitting into smithereens and splattering the still
hot coffee in all directions. You sit up straight
ignoring the spilled cup, ignoring the coffee stain
soaking into your carpet, with your heart racing and a
slight tremor in your hand, you quickly type in your
passwords to log in to your web account.

Thank goodness your web host enables raw statistics,
you will soon catch the cheating thieves. What! 10,000
visitors and not one sale... Not one measly sale.
What�s incredible... no one even signed up to your
mailing list! That`s not possible! Didn`t you use that
excellent sales letter software.

Yes your sales letter is just perfect and your
headline is a hypnotic beauty... you have gone to
great lengths to provide top rated testimonials, the
sense of deadly urgency, the free gifts are all
there... yes your sales letter is perfect, yet no
sales!

Hold on... Did you design your sales page to deliver
the `most wanted response` dictated by your traffics
psychological mind set?

What`s that?

Consider where will you get your site traffic from:

- From ezine/ email advertising � This is usually very
highly targeted traffic. The people coming to your
site already know what to expect and are looking
forward to it. Here your regular sales letter will
work well.

- From search engines � This traffic is more complex.
People are coming to your site looking for
information in response to certain search terms. Your
`killer sales letter` may not be sufficient � you
need to be able to satisfy their thirst for
information. Thus more informative and bigger sites
work well instead of `killer mini sites`.

- From other sites linking to you- This again is very
highly targeted traffic. The important point here is
why is this site linking to you... is it because of
your ebook or newsletter listings, your article or
classified ad etc.

Here the response is usually dependant on the link
through which the visitor arrived � his mind is
already made up as to the action to be taken on your
site � such as download your ebook, join your
mailing list, read your articles etc.

- Guaranteed hits from Lotto or other gaming sites �
Here you have only a few seconds to capture your
visitors attention, the visitors are coming with a
need to `win some fabulous prize` 
 Hence the regular
sales letter does not usually work, Nor will you get
any commendable signups to your mailing list. Thus
you need to give them what they want: Some
irresistible viral gift.

- Guaranteed hits from traffic exchanges Here You
have less than 30 seconds to capture interest. The
regular sales letter does not work very well unless
if you are advertising other free traffic/ advertising
program.

Also most surfers are surfing several exchanges at the
same time and usually do so in the night or early
morning � they are just clicking away robotically or
like a zombie, with their minds befogged or numbed
with sleep and not more than a passing glance to your
incredible headline.

Here you need a `six pack` to jolt/electrify them and
make them look at your sales page with their hearts
racing wildly and a mad gush of adrenaline.

Thus based on the psychological mindset of your
traffic
you need to determine your Most Wanted Response: What
will work best: sales, signup to your mailing list or
a free viral give away. You are now ready to write your
headlines and sales letter.

Here`s a recap:

1.Determine the psychological make up of your traffic.

2.Establish your most wanted response
Hey buddy, lets go shopping to the internet mall.

This shop looks cool c`mon lets step in. Goodness...
why is the door so tight is the shop crowded?

Cool... look at that gaudy interior.

Yuks! those blinkers... It`s driving me crazy.

What are they selling?

C`mon let`s get out before I have a seizure.

This joint here looks more promising... Whew that`s
better!

Hey...What the...

"Can we have your email address sir?"

But why... we have just come in, let us at least look
around first?

"Well sir... It`s company policy that our customers
first sign up to our mailing list before they can
explore shop"

No... thank you then...You see it`s my privacy...

"Sorry Sir, Company Policy".

Great... On to the next one then.

Wow look at that widget... Just what I need... And
the price is right too.

Oh but you need to get Ma to select the color...

Come to think of it, better wait for the next
paycheck.

Uh- Oh... then let�s take the business card, we will
come back again.

What... No business card! Heck is this a business or
what?

Goodness man! A business is a business is a business
whether you do it offline or online there are certain
codes of conduct to follow for sure fire success.

What happens when a potential customer steps in to
your realm?

Consider How would you feel say:

- If you entered a shop and immediately felt
uncomfortable, dizzy, lost in the chaos...

- If you just stepped in to a shop and you are asked
for your email address without being given the chance
to look around first � I for one value my privacy and
will rather step out then reveal my personal info.
[The concept of mailing list/newsletter works well
with information products but if you are selling
other goods you need to do better]

- If you entered a shop and saw a cool gadget but do
not know why/ how to use it / where to use it /
advantages etc. Will you buy it without a demo?

- If you like the shop, you like the merchandise, but
you are not ready to buy just yet, maybe you want to
compare prices or you are waiting for your paycheck or
you want your wife/husband/partner to approve of your
choice... (any no of thousand and one reasons), so
what do you do... you pick a business card and leave
unobtrusively with the option to return later.

- You like the shop, you like the gadget, but you do
not need it, and you know your best friend is
searching for it, so you are itching to tell him/
her about this rare find...

- Or you like the shop, the product and buy it on the
spot, but you would like further information about
upgrades, customer service etc.

Goodness man! A business is a business is a business
whether you do it offline or online there are certain
codes of conduct to follow for sure fire success.
Here are the bare essentials:

- Enable a demonstration of your product...
Haven`t you seen all those ads on TV showing you
how various gadgets work? In online limbo this
corresponds to an auto-responder series, for example:
`How to conquer the world in five easy steps`... here
you demonstrate the virtues of your widget. [You
might even consider embedding video files in to your
website for widget demo].

- Provide a `non threatening` mailing list invitation
to enable updates and customer service for confirmed/
interested customers.

- Your ebusiness card / catalogue or viral give away�
this should be absolutely free to go and not linked up
to your mailing list.

- Provide A Tell your friends script/e-card.

- Make your customer feel relaxed, comfortable and
welcome.

Next concentrate on getting targeted traffic to
your e-shop...

And then watch the sales start pouring in.

3.Write up your sales pitch to deliver your most
wanted response.

If you follow the above technique your websites
visitor to sales conversion ratio is not only going to jump
but will skyrocket like a fire cracker and you will laugh
your way to the bank. 