It's quite common for a site to be referenced by more than one
domain name. In fact, most sites are referenced by at least two:
a www version and a non-www version. These are usually set up to
reference the index page on a site and produce the same results
for a searcher.

It could, however, be argued that these are these same domain
names. So the question remains: why would someone want to have
more than one unique domain name for a single site?

Search engines - First, let's take a brief look at search
engines. In the past, it was a very common spamming technique
to purchase dozens, hundreds or in some really gross cases,
thousands of domain names, all referencing exactly the same
site. These were all submitted to the search engines, and many
of them were indexed and blindly added to the results. This is
how many questionable sites used to get top search results very
quickly and inexpensively.

The search engines have apparently caught onto this technique.
At the very least, it has become common knowledge that this kind
of spamming is not tolerated (sometimes common knowledge can be
just as effective a deterrent as actual enforcement). I know
that in the past it was normal to find many sites of different
domain names but identical content in search engine results;
today it's far more rare.

In fact, the top search engine, Google, bases it's ranking
scheme on quality of links. What this translates to is you must
get popular (higher ranking) sites to link to your site to
raise your ranking. Thus, it's a better strategy to get as
many links to a SINGLE domain name than to many different
domain names.

With this in mind, it's now considered best by most search
engine optimization specialists (at least those that know what
they are doing) to only list a single domain with the search
engines, perhaps with the www and non-www version but nothing
else.

Multiple entry points - One technique that I use on my own site
with great success is to have multiple entry points, each it's
own domain name. Let's consider a mythical site in order to
illustrate how this works.

The site is about homemaking, and thus the main domain is
"homemaking.com". Underneath this are sections about sewing,
housecleaning and cooking. You might use "homemaking.com" for
link exchanges and search engine submissions, then create three
additional domains: "sewing.com", "housecleaning.com" and
"cooking.com" (although if you actually managed to purchase
those domain names you could resell them for quite a chunk of
change).

Each of these domains would use a 301 redirect (this informs
any search engine that the page has permanently moved to a new
location) to a specific page on the site.

Those three domains would then be used in different themed
marketing campaigns. You might submit an article to a cooking
site, for instance, which referencing cooking.com. For a
newsletter about cleaning, you would use housecleaning.com. Each
domain name is merely a shortcut to the master domain, but it is
much more targeted than "homemaking.com".

Protection - If you own a business, it's a great idea to think
of some of the derivations of your site name and purchase those
as well. Thus, if you had a company named "xyz", you might also
purchase "xyzsucks" and "ihatexyz" as well. You may as well
direct these to your site, but be sure to include 301 redirects,
as you definitely do not want them in search engine indices.

Typos - Sometimes people misspell things, and domain names are
no exception. Knowing this, you can get some respectable
traffic by purchasing common misspellings for your domain name.
Just remember to use the 301 redirect method so these
misspellings are not listed in the search engines.

Other TLD's (Top Level Domains) - If possible, it's a good idea
to get the.com,.net and.org version of your domain at a
minimum. I tend to get the.us (or whatever country is
appropriate),.info and.biz versions as well. This ensures that
no matter what people type they will get to your domain. Of
course, remember to 301 redirect these domains so they don't get
listed.

For branding purposes, it's essential to get the other TLD's if
you can. If you don't you may be embarrassed to find some
pornographic or casino site has purchased your name with a
different TLD. The white house site (whitehouse.gov) is a
classic example: the.com version has nothing to do with the
white house (if you type this URL, be sure your kids are not
present).

Other TLD's with different content - In a slight alteration of
the above method, I have purchased the additional TLD's, but
made each one slightly different. To use the above housecleaning
example, housecleaning.com might be a page about housecleaning
in general, housecleaning.us might index articles specific to
the United States, and housecleaning.biz may include
information related to housecleaning businesses. Each of these
is just a page or two, and links back to the main
housecleaning.com domain.

If you use this method, be sure it's honest and sincere. Do NOT
do this to spam search engines (in fact, to be perfectly safe,
set your metatags to stop robots from indexing those pages).
These are not intended for search engines - these pages are
intended for focused marketing campaigns.

Regional content - If your site has regional content, you might
purchase specific domain names to focus on that content. For
example, if you had a stamp collection site, you could purchase
"my-stamps.to" for Tonga related stamps, "my-stamps.us" for
United States stamps and so on. You could also keep it simpler
and purchase "my-tonga-stamps.com" for your general site,
"my-english-stamps.com" for your English stamps and so on. These
should also use 301 redirects to keep the specific domain names
from being indexed.

Uses for the.NAME TLD - You might even consider purchase the
.name TLD for your senior managers. Put up simple web sites
about them, with links to your main site. These SHOULD be
indexed in the search engines, as you want people to find them
if they are looking for information about your personnel.

Don't forget email - Remember you can get email on each and
every one of the domains that your purchase. In fact, this is a
great reason to purchase additional domain names - people can
send you email by different means. So be sure to set up the
email for each and every domain to go to a general, "catch-all"
account. It's a good idea, though, to heavily spam-filter this
account as it can collect a huge amount of junk.

Subdomains - This is a great way to get much of the benefit of
the above listed techniques without purchasing additional
domain names. It does require a little more control of your DNS
entries, however, as most ISPs and web hosts will not be
willing to do these kinds of things for you.

In this case, you could define "housekeeping.com" as the
primary domain, then "cleaning.housekeeping.com",
"sewing.housekeeping.com" and "cooking.housekeeping.com" as the
subdomains. You should continue to use 301 redirects to keep the
search engines from indexing these pages.

Renewals - Don't forget to renew all of these domains each year.
At least examine each one when renewal time comes and
consciously decide whether or not you need the domain. Don't
let them expire without your knowledge. Someone else may then
benefit from your hard work.

Other people's mistakes - Sometimes you might find that the
domain you want is not available. In this case, take a look at
the WHOIS record and see when it expires. Set up a reminder for
30 days from this date and every week or so thereafter. On
those days, try and purchase the domain. Quite often,
(especially these days) you may be surprised to find the domain
has become available.

Other TLD systems - Companies such as new.net are offering many
more pseudo-TLDs such as.SHOP and.XXX to the general public. I
would avoid these new systems like the plague. These are at best
bad ideas and at worst scams. They are attempts to supercede the
official internet standard TLD system by companies with
questionable motivations. They all require browser plug-ins or
other customizations to work, and some of them come piggy-backed
with spyware and other malicious applications.

These alternate TLDs do not get indexed in search engines, and
they may conflict with future TLDs added in the official domain
name structure (and thus become useless). On top of that, they
are extremely expensive.

In my opinion, it is critical that the internet domain name
structure remain under the control of a central governing body.
While this body (currently ICANN) is not operating as desired by
the majority, it's still much better being under one umbrella
than splintering this all over the place.

Straight TCP/IP address - I am always surprised to come across
a site which is listed in search engines, ezines and other
promotions as a straight TCP/IP address. This is not only tacky
and a sign of a spammer, it's not very intelligent as well. If
you do this and move your site (changing it's IP), you will lose
all of the traffic that you have so painfully gained.

Conclusions - The point is that owning more than one domain has
many uses, although it is no longer of much value from a search
engine optimization viewpoint. Instead, you can use the other
domain names to fulfill other types of marketing and to attract
people from specific markets to your site.
Many years ago, when I was a young lad, a wise man gave me the
best advice that anyone has ever given. "Richard", he told me,
"Never lose your integrity." I've followed that advice all of my
life, and it has served me better than just about anything else.
Here on the internet, we webmasters have a substantial amount of
power. Because of that power, we also carry a burden of
responsibility.

My wife has been very sick for several years. In fact, four
years ago she went into a coma for 5 days and came within
seconds of dying. It's a major league miracle that she survived.
Her recovery has been tough on her, both because of pain and
because she has trouble leaving the house. In order to make
things more tolerable for her, I gave her all of the tools she
needed to become a webmaster along with some training and help.

Now she has become a very good webmaster. She has created a site
about how she survived asthma (http://www.survivingasthma.com)
and another about how she survived diabetes
(http://www.survivingdiabetes.com). These sites explain her
experiences, give some advice from her heart and attempt to give
people hope.

Recently, she got an email from someone who just stumbled
across her site and was greatly moved. In fact, that person had
been contemplating suicide, read her site, and decided to live.
Another person was able to get help based upon my wife's advice. Many
others have sent in emails explaining how their lives were
changed or in a few cases even saved.

Wow. Now that's power. And along with that comes an incredible
responsibility.

Now, on one of my web sites I give people advice on the web, the
internet and other related topics. I give people insight on how
to create sites which look good, produce results and perform
their task.

I've received numerous emails from people explaining that I have
changed their life in many ways. Some people have had their
interest rekindled, others have learned things they didn't know.
And still others began to get an understanding of how to be
ethical on the internet. In fact, some people even said they've
learned that it's important to be ethical at all!

I humbly submit that we webmasters have a high responsibility to
the internet community.

- We need to communicate clearly
- We need to communicate accurately
- We must not tolerate unethical behaviors
- We must not promote scams and frauds
- We may make money, we must do it honestly
- We must respect other's opinions
- We must not flame, spam or engage in other unsocial behaviors

All of us need to understand how much power we have and use that
power in a responsible way. 
Be Cautious - Be cautious about anything you read on the web,
in an email or on a newsgroup. There are so many scams and
frauds that the best thing to do is ignore all of them entirely
until you have enough experience and knowledge to be able to
effectively judge what's really going on. Ignore the newest
thing, the "fantastic" money making opportunities and so forth.
When I was a newbie, I fell for the Don Lapre 900 number scam,
lost $700, but learned my lesson. You need to understand there
is no free lunch, no quick get rich scheme and no one tells you
how to make a million for a hundred bucks.

Don't use a debit card on the internet - debit cards are
attached directly to a checking account. If there is fraud,
why not let it be the banks money (with a credit card) instead
of your own money (with a debit card) that's at risk.

Learn to design - Take a web class on web design before you
learn HTML or any other language. Design is much more important
and significant than code.

See "A well designed site is a pleasure and a money maker" -
http://www.internet-tips.net/Webmaster/design.htm

Choose your domain registrar wisely - There are hundreds of
companies that will register your domains. Take your time, read
some reviews and choose a registrar that gives you a good price,
excellent features and that you feel comfortable with. To
register a domain, you should expect to pay less than $10 per
year and you should have a web-account to be able to make
changes at will. Remember, in the case of domain registrars the
biggest and most well known is not the best by any means.

Practice safe computing - Install a hardware firewall appliance
to protect your home computer; Install an anti-virus program and
keep the definitions up-to-date on a weekly basis; Program your
spam filters to block all executable attachments; And, most
importantly, backup, backup and backup (and test your backups to
be sure they work).

See "Backing up your system is an essential part of your
security scheme" -
http://www.internet-tips.net/Security/Backups.htm

Never, ever spam anyone - It might seem attractive to send out
a newsletter to a hundred people who don't know you from Adam,
but don't do it. And, of course, those 200-million email address
CDroms are to be avoided at all costs.

Teach your kids about the dangers of the internet - If you have
children this is a must. Tell them about the dangers of chat
rooms and strangers. Inform them that things are not always what
they seem. And watch everything they do while on the computer.

See "Protecting Your Children" -
http://www.internet-tips.net/Security/Children.htm

Use a domain name - When you set up your site, use a domain
name instead of the URL provided by the web host. This way you
can move your site without losing your search engine rankings,
link exchanges and so forth.

Avoid giving out private information - Very few people need
your address, almost no one needs your social security or
drivers license numbers. Be careful giving out any information
and only give it to trusted sources.

See "Identity Theft" -
http://www.internet-tips.net/Legal/identity.htm

Use good spam filters - Buy an account from spamcop.net and use
that email address for posting to the web. Never, ever use your
own email address for these kinds of things. A Spamcop account
is cheap and very useful, get one today.

See "SPAM - Spamcop" -
http://www.internet-tips.net/Email/SPAM_spamcop.htm

Stay up-to-date - Visit boards like webmasterworld often to get
more information about what's going on. Get on some security
mailing lists to get the scoop on various threats (especially
CERT). And always hunt for more knowledge.

Promote your site wisely - Before submitting your site or
spending a dime on promotion, be sure you understand what you
are doing. There are thousand of promotion methods, including
search engines (especially Google), link exchanges and viral
marketing. Avoid Free-For-All pages and link farms like the
plague, and, I repeat, don't spend any money on advertising
until you are positive you understand what your money is
purchasing.

See "The secrets of how to advertise your web site" -
http://www.internet-tips.net/Advertising/Advertising.htm

Apply your site to web awards programs - If you've created a
good web site, feel free to apply to a few awards programs. Be
sure you read the criteria before you apply so you can validate
your site before sending in your application.

See "Website Awards Worksheet" -
http://www.internet-tips.net/Winawards/awardsworksheet.htm
One of my first tasks when I was hired ten years ago was to
investigate the creation of a disaster recovery site for our
mainframe computer systems. I had already had some experiences
with disasters and recovery. Here are some examples of a few
that we included in our plans.

Major Earthquake - Those of us who live in California understand
earthquakes. I've personally been through at least five
significant quakes (6.8 or greater) without suffering any
damage at all. In many people's mind, a major earthquake is
the disaster scenario.

One day the "big one" will come (in California) and who knows
what will happen at that time. In fact, my boss and I were able
to convince the CEO of our company to create a "hot site" (a
duplicate site which is already ready to take over in the event
of a disaster) because of a recent significant earthquake.

One of the first things that we did is contact Caltech (the
experts on earthquakes) to commission a study to determine
where we should place our disaster site. The primary criteria
was that the site be relatively close (within 50 miles) but on
a different geologic plate so the earthquake would not flatten
both locations.

As we studied the possibility of this disaster, we realized
that the building and computers might emerge from the earthquake
entirely intact, but the infrastructure (power, phone lines
and so forth) might be destroyed. In addition, a major
earthquake is a unique disaster because it's more likely that
your people will be in complete shock and more interested in
their families and homes than in restoring your computer
operations.

The thing to do here is be sure you've got the infrastructure
issues covered cold. This includes phones, power and the
network. Make sure you have a disaster site (or very good
backups kept off-site) ready to go. Rehearse your disaster
plan, and make sure your people know what to do.

Minor Earthquake - A minor earthquake might be easy to survive
(we've been through several of them with no issues) and it
might introduce some interesting quirks on it's own. The power
might be out, phone lines might be down and take weeks to
repair, and the general infrastructure (roads, food shipments
and so on) might be disabled. In addition, earthquakes tend to
put people into a state of shock, so it might be difficult to
get people to recover and get back to work.

Biological Event - When envelops fill of anthrax started
appearing on the news, we were suddenly confronted with a new
type of disaster. What if a biological attack or event occurred
in our building? What if the receptionist opened an envelop
contaminated with anthrax? We would then be confronted with a
unique situation. The building would be sealed and off-limited
for days, weeks or even months; and we would not be allowed
back in under any conditions for any reason for that time.

This situation is probably one of the worst disaster scenarios
of all. The old building and equipment is intact but completely
unreachable. Tantalizing and frustrating. Sigh. What to do?

Hope and pray that you've got an excellent disaster recovery
plan and a very competent team, that's what you do. In this
case, you'd better have a hot site or, at the very least some
excellent backups. Not only that, you're business continuity
plan had better be totally finished and rehearsed. You see, in
this case you will not even be able to look through the ruble
or burned building for papers, disks, CDs or anything else.
Nothing, absolutely nothing, will be available for your use
for a long, long time. In fact, if any of your people are in
the building you may find them unavailable (as in quarantined)
as well.

Lightening - One day a few years ago, when I was just beginning
in the computer field, I was working late, way past midnight.
I was just sitting in the computer room (freezing my butt off),
listening to one of the heaviest rain storms that I'd heard in
a long time. It was kind of eerie, listening to the rain drops
on the roof and the thunder in the distance.

Suddenly, the room lit up and I was blinded for a few seconds.
I instinctively pulled back from the keyboard, and I believe
that saved my life. I felt heat on my face and body, and when
I opened my eyes the computer room was dark.

I soon learned that lightening has struck the power pole just
outside the building. The computer simply melted down - no
circuit breaker in existence could have protected it. I was
lucky to be alive - wow, what a rush that was!

Unfortunately, this company did NOT have a disaster recovery
plan. We had to purchase a new computer system and build it
back up from scratch. Fortunately, we did keep backups off-site,
and within a week or so we were back up and running.

And that's the reason why, now, I have a complete belief and
focus on disaster recovery - if you have a plan and have
prepared well, you will recover just fine (even with the
unexpected bumps and such). If you don't, then you basically
leave it up to fate or whatever else you believe in. Personally,
I would rather be in control of the situation. I find that
makes things much easier.
In the beginning, search engine marketers were only
concerned about top 10 rankings. Do you remember those
days? Then, as things progressed and we began to work
"smarter," we began to take note of how those top 10's were
actually converting to traffic and sales.

After all, in any marketing campaign, the true bottom line
should be your ROI, the return on your investment. That's
how you'll know if your marketing efforts are really
working, or if you need to go back to the drawing board and
try something new.

Recently, I was introduced to a new ROI calculating service
called KeywordTool. It covers both pay-per-click engines
and regular engine results.

To write the article, I interviewed Chris Genge of
KeywordTool (http://www.keywordtool.net), and he took me on
a tour of the service itself.

Question:
Please explain what KeywordTool is and what it really does.

Chris:
"Deciding which keywords best suit each Web site and
which ones specifically will generate
sales/conversions is perhaps the toughest job in SEO.
Tools like Word Tracker are a great help in narrowing
down keyword selection, but then what?

"In the past, decisions were not based on facts but
mostly speculation. This gave people no alternative
but to promote or bid on larger keyword groups. We
used a shotgun approach in hopes of increasing sales,
with no way of telling which keywords were adding to
our bottom line!

"A common saying in advertising is: `In any good
campaign, 50% of all advertising dollars are wasted,
but which 50%?' KeywordTool can answer this question
for keyword promotion campaigns.

"KeywordTool's tracking service tracks the conversion
or sales performance of keywords on search and pay-
per-click engines, showing which keyword phrases are
actually converting into customers and from which
search engines. It is not a visitor tracker; instead,
it determines keyword performance.

"With this keyword referral/conversion rate
information, one can then fine tune their keyword
choices and streamline promotion and bidding expenses
to increase efficiency, sales, and profits, or in
other words...the bottom line.

"KeywordTool is an online service that gathers
information about your Web site referrals and
sales/conversions. Using your private user name and
password, you can then access the stats so you can
review the information and make informed decisions
about how to continue your online promotion.

"KeywordTool is designed for use with SEO and Pay-Per-
Click (PPC) campaigns. It's well suited for both."

Question:
Is there a way that we can see a demo of how the service
really works?

Chris:
"Go to http://www.keywordtool.net At the top of the
page, you will see the log in. Use the username of
"keywordtool" and password of "demo" to access the
demo.

"The first page is the list of search engines that
have sent referrals to the specific Web site you wish
to have monitored. Only search engines that have sent
a referral will appear on the listed sites. New search
engines will appear as referrals are sent.

"The `Create details' or `Edit details' in the first
column is where you would click to configure your
search engine settings. This is where you tell
KeywordTool what your average cost per click is for
each search engine you want to calculate. This can be
filled out after some data has been gathered.

"The search engine column is the list of only those
search engines that have referred visitors to your Web
site. You will notice that KeywordTool will also
differentiate between regions for those search engines
that are regionalized.

"The Column marked "Clicks" tells you the total number
of referrals sent by each SE.

"PPC is the average price per click you have set for
yourself. For those using this for SEO, this can be
left blank. The PPC can be changed or added at any
time, allowing you to re-calculate your PPC using new
information.

"CONV is the number of conversions you have received
from that particular search engine. The details about
the number of conversions are at the next level.

"You can define what a conversion is:

-A "SALE"
-A subscription
-Downloading a file
-Filling out a form
-Or anything you consider to be an acquisition

"The CONV% is where KeywordTool calculates the
percentage of conversions based on the number of
referrals received from that search engine. It's
really just a performance guide of the search engine
for the keywords you have listings for.

"PPA is the `price per acquisition.' It tells you how
much each new customer costs you for that particular
search engine. The number indicated is rounded to the
closest dollar.

"ROI is your potential return on investment. It's
based on the information provided and the referrals
and conversion rates recorded.

"Some of the rows don't have information, because we
haven't defined the cost per click or estimated profit
on that particular search engine. This can be added or
updated at any time.

"Start the next section by clicking on the column
marked `Clicks' to sort the SE's from highest
referrals to lowest. Yahoo US has the highest number
of referrals, so it comes to the top of the list.

"Click on `Yahoo.US.' It will then take you to the
next screen where there are 2 sections marked `search
words' and `categories.' Search words are referrals
from SE', and categories are from directories. Yahoo
displays both so KeywordTool separates the results.

"Click on `Search Words.' The next screen will display
the exact results and performance for each keyword
phrase. Click on CONV to sort to the highest
conversion keywords in this section. This is the
section where you can start seeing which keywords are
working well for you and which ones are not.

"The keywords that work well are ones that you can
focus on to ensure they are also listed on the other
search engines. You can quickly see which of your
initial chosen keywords are working well and which you
might want to consider dropping or reviewing. You can
then work to get improved listings on other search
engines for a small select group of keywords that you
are confident will give you the highest ROI. The
numbers provided in KeywordTool's reports could be
used to make better, informed decisions.

"If a keyword phrase is not working well, it might
either be the wrong keyword for the product offered or
the sales presentation is not working well on that
page. Knowing that this keyword is not working well,
you can then start to make changes to improve
performance. For anyone who has tried tweaking your
Google AdWords Select based on your copy and click
performance, this works in much the same way. With
KeywordTool, it's fairly easy to know which keyword
phrases to work on and which ones are working well for
you already.

"The information KeywordTool provides will tell you
how much potential a keyword phrase has, allowing you
to know how much to invest in SEO or PPC.

"All the information in KeywordTool sections can be
exported to Excel easily so you can manipulate the
data and quickly determine what your strategy should
be for getting better returns from your work. If you
notice the Expert to Excel link at the top right of
the page, it's a very handy little tool."
(Continued from Part 1 -- an interview with Chris Genge about
KeywordTool.)

Question:
What if you have a lot of clients?

Chris:
"Each client would have their own account. You would
want to keep the information separate and private. You
can have multiple accounts under your main account.
There is no limit to the number of accounts or the
number of domains you monitor. Each account does
require a separate license though."

Question:
What do you mean by a separate license?

Chris:
"Pricing for KeywordTool is based on a license fee and
a click-tracking fee."

Question:
So if you use the tool for multiple domains/accounts, you'd
have to purchase it separately for each domain/account?

Chris,
"Yes, you can run all your accounts under your main
account, but they are purchased separately."

Question:
Is there a special setup fee for the main account?

Chris:
"No setup fee. The set up takes about 20 minutes and
just requires adding a small JavaScript into the head
of your entry pages and a small piece of code into
your conversion page. Then it goes live right away and
starts gathering info."

Question:
How much does the service cost?

Chris:
"The service usually runs from about $200/month per
account and up depending on how many search engine
related clicks you are getting per month. There are
several examples of pricing at:
http://keywordtool.net/pricing.asp."

Question:
If I have 20 clients now, what would the cost be per month?

Chris:
"The first client is $150; 2-5 clients is $135 each up
to 20. All clients after 20 are $60 each. It's
progressive pricing."

Question:
If I start with three clients, then add two more later on,
does the total subscription rate get adjusted to 5 clients,
etc.?

Chris:
"Yes."

Question:
If it uses JavaScript and someone has their JavaScript
disabled, they wouldn't be counted? Is it a cookie? What if
someone has cookies disabled?

Chris:
"Yes you are right about the JavaScript. There is also
a cookie place on their browser that keeps track of
people that come take a look and return later to buy."

Question:
What if someone is using both PPC and SEO program. How is
the cost is distributed? Do we have to plug in the cost for
each program to calculate ROI?

Chris:
"If all you want to track is SEO, just don't put the
code into the entry pages you use for PPC or use
separate PPC entry pages. The same is true for PPC.
You can separate these by only placing the code into
unique pages you use for PPC."

Question:
So for the conversion, we need to create two conversion
pages: one for PPC and one for SEO?

Chris:
"No, just differentiate the entry pages. You can use
the same conversion page."

Question:
How do we know if it's the right keyword that generated a
lead since people browse from page to page?

Chris:
"The entry code is placed in all pages the search
engines are referring visitors to. This way Keyword
Tool will track the entry and watch to see if it
converts into a sale. You can place the code in just
one page or as many pages as required--there is no
limit. You can even have the same code in an include
file in your template. This way KeywordTool watches
refers from all your pages."

Question:
Do we need to do the data entry for keywords and PPC?

Chris:
"There is no data entry; KeywordTool looks for the
keywords as they are used on search engines, not how
we think they should be used. This way you can
discover good keywords you got listings for and didn't
know it."

In Conclusion

If your ROI is important to you, which is should be!,
KeywordTool (http://www.keywordtool.net) will certainly
help you determine your conversions rates and the return on
your investment for any traffic through the search engines,
directories, and pay-per-click engines. It's a sharp
program with a lot of handy features. 