Travelers who highly value cheap travel options, including cheap airplane tickets and cheap vacation packages, sometimes feel like they are treated little better than cattle by the airlines. The Department of Transportation (DOT) wants to improve traveler treatment by imposing a series of new rules to protect passengers' rights.

Allegiant, Southwest and Spirit challenged DOT's new consumer right rules in federal court and lost when the U.S. Court of Appeals in Washington, D.C. denied their motion for a stay of some of the new rules.

The court unanimously ruled, without further explanation, that the airlines "have not satisfied the stringent requirements" for a stay. Those requirements include proving that the airlines will suffer immediate and irreparable harm without a stay. Such a claim is weak given that the DOT had already postponed the implementation date of all of the challenged rules until January 24th.

Today airlines are allowed to advertise base fares, without including certain taxes and fees, so long as those charges are properly displayed nearby. DOT's new rule requires advertised and all displayed prices to include all taxes and fees, regardless of whether they are imposed by governments, airlines, or intermediaries.

The airlines also wanted a stay of the following new rules:

• Allow travelers to hold a reservation for up to 24 hours without payment, or to make airlines issues cash refunds for cancellations made within 24 hours of payment.

• Make eticket confirmations spell out airline baggage allowances and fees.

• Prohibit post purchase increases in airline ticket prices or in any part of an air inclusive package.

• Require airlines and all other travel providers inform customers who make a deposit about the potential for a rise in price between the time of the initial deposit and the due date of final payment. Airlines and other travel providers will not be able to pass on any price increase unless they first receive the traveler's written consent.
www.cheapfares.com

Banning Electronic Cigarettes on Planes

Some travelers taking advantage of cheap airplane tickets or cheap vacation packages have started to complain about fellow passengers puffing on electronic cigarettes on flights. Although such activity is currently discouraged, the Department of Transportation (DOT) wants to unequivocally forbid the use of such devices on planes.

The DOT has proposed a rule specifically banning electronic cigarettes in order to protect passenger rights, improve passenger comfort, and do away with any confusion regarding the use of such cigarettes on planes.

Electronic cigarettes look like regular cigarettes, but they are battery operated devices that turn nicotine into a vapor that the user inhales. The DOT is concerned about such cigarettes because "there is a lack of scientific data and knowledge of the ingredients in electronic cigarettes."

The Tobacco Vapor Electronic Cigarette Association maintains the devices only release water vapor. The group's CEO claim's that DOT's recommendation "makes absolutely zero sense." He claims that only the smoker is exposed to nicotine and that other passengers' cologne is often far more intrusive than electronic cigarette vapor.

Although the DOT contends that its existing ban on smoking of tobacco products covers electronic cigarettes, it wants to eliminate any future confusion. Select airline passengers have been "vaping" during flights, contending that electronic cigarettes are exempt from the ban.

The DOT's proposed rule would cover all U.S. and foreign airlines on flights to and from the United States. 
1. Never submit old news
Submitting old news will not help you in becoming a respected user. Yesterday's news is history. But if you still need to submit old stuff, consider feature articles, howtos and similar pieces that are up-to-date for a long time.

2. Check your facts
You must be flattered that users read your postings but you will hardly be flattered when users prove that you haven't got the facts right. In addition to sarcastic comments, you might also receive negative votes for your story, so if you want to avoid this, check you facts - or your readers will do it.

3. Check you spelling
Some sites do not allow to edit your posts later, so if you misspell the title, the URL, or a keyword, it will stay this way forever.

4. Not all topics do well
But sometimes even great content and submitting to the right category do not push you to the top. One possible reason could be that your stories are about unpopular topics. Many sites have topics that their users love and topics that don't sell that well. For instance, Apple sells well on Digg and The War in Iraq on Netscape. Negative stories - about George Bush, Microsoft, evil multinational companies, corruption and crime also have a chance to make it to the front page. You can't know these things in advance but some research on how many stories tagged with keywords like yours have made the front page in the last year or so can give you a clue.

5. Have Related Articles / Popular Articles
Traffic gurus joke that traffic from social bookmarking sites is like an invasion - the crowds pour in and in a day or two they are gone. Unfortunately this is true - after your listing rolls from the front page (provided that you reached the front page), the drop in traffic is considerable. Besides, many users come just following the link to your article, have a look at it and then they are gone. One of the ways to keep them longer on your site is to have links to Related Articles / Popular Articles or something similar that can draw their attention to other stuff on the site and make them read more than one article.

6. RSS feeds, newsletter subscriptions, affiliate marketing
RSS feeds, newsletter subscriptions, affiliate marketing are all areas in which the traffic from social bookmarking sites can help you a lot. Many people who come to your site and like it, will subscribe to RSS feeds and/or your newsletter. So, you need to put these in visible places and then you will be astonished at the number of new subscriptions you got on the day when you were on the front page of a major social bookmarking site.

7. Do not use automated submitters
After some time of active social bookmarking, you will discover that you are spending hours on end posting links. Yes, this is a lot of time and using automated submitters might look like the solution but it isn't. Automated submitters often have malware in them or are used for stealing passwords, so unless you don't care about the fate of your profile and don't mind being banned, automated submitters are not the way to go.

8. Respond to comments on your stories
Social bookmarking sites are not a newsgroup but interesting articles can trigger a pretty heated discussion with hundreds of comments. If your article gets comments, you must be proud. Always respond to commends on your stories and even better - post comments on other stories you find interesting. This is a way to make friends and to create a top-profile.

9. Prepare your server for the expected traffic
This is hardly a point of minor importance but we take for granted that you are hosting your site on a reliable server that does not crash twice a day. But have in mind that your presence on the front page of a major social bookmarking site can drive you a lot traffic, which can cause your server to crash - literally!
I remember one of the times I was on the front page on Digg, I kept restarting Apache on my dedicated server because it was unable to cope with the massive traffic. I have many tools on my site and when the visitors tried them, this loaded the server additionally.
Well, for an articles site getting so much traffic is not so devastating but if you are hosting on a so-so server, you'd better migrate your site to a machine that can handle a lot of simultaneous hits. Also, check if your monthly traffic allowance is enough to handle 200-500,000 or even more visitors. It is very amateurish to attract a lot of visitors and not be able to serve them because your server crashed or you have exceeded your bandwidth!

10. The snowball effect
But despite the differences in the likes of the different social bookmarking communities, there are striking similarities. You will soon discover that if a post is popular on one of the major sites, this usually drives it up on the other big and smaller sites. Usually it is Digg posts that become popular on StumbleUpon and Reddit but there are many other examples. To use this fact to your best advantage, you may want to concentrate your efforts on getting to the front page of the major players only and bet on the snowball effect to drive you to the top on other sites.
An additional benefit of the snowball effect is that if your posting is interesting and people start blogging about it, you can get tons of backlinks from their blogs. This happened to me and the result was that my PR jumped to 6 on the next update.
When you are making an offer on a home you wish to purchase or receiving an offer on the one you are selling, knowing how to negotiate a contract is extremely important. You should be able to get good advise from your licensed realtor but unfortunately they do not always give you all of the information that you should have to make the best decision.
First of all, every market is different and this article is based upon a good strong market where homes are selling at a good pace. Homes in much of the southwest region, especially areas of Phoenix are selling very quickly because of the low inventory and low prices after the housing crash.
When you receive a contract on your home you have a response time and date. If you do not respond within that timeframe then the contract is technically null and void and you may have lost your buyer to another property. You can still resurrect the contract with a counter offer changing the response time if the buyer accepts your terms. You are usually given around twenty four hours to respond and it is usually in your best interest to do so.
Some sellers do not respond that quickly if the just put the home on the market and it is getting a lot of activity because they can see that they are likely to receive multiple contracts. If the home you are trying to acquire is newly on the market and in great condition you may need to be aggressive with your offer since you will not know what other price other offers might be presented. In this case, do not mess around by offering a lower price and expect to play the counter offer game because you can easily not even get a response and lose to a higher offer.
As the buyer who may have received a counter offer, you will also have a response time and date. Many buyers think that during this time they can be very leisure in responding because the ball is in their court. What you need to understand is that during this time the seller could receive a better offer and rescind the counter offer out to you and take the other offer or counter that one instead. Your real estate agent may not be clear as to why it is important to respond in a timely manner. As a realtor myself, I have had my seller change their mind while waiting for one buyer to respond because a better offer presented itself. Same with some of my buyers, the seller pulled their counter from us while the buyer was mulling it over because of a stronger contract.
Recently, my buyers are finding homes that are in the top of the range that they qualify for and a nice home comes on the market, they make a full price offer but another offer actually beats them and they get very discouraged knowing that they put in a full price offer very quickly and still lose the home. In this case, there is not much you can do if you just cannot pay any more, cash offers and higher offers will get the home over yours no matter how quick you are to get your offer in. 
Google the search engine pioneer has recently introduced Google+ which is their version of a social networking service that is similar to the popular Facebook that many people are addicted too. Like any social networking service Google+ offers the ability to connect and share anything from pictures, music to specific personal thoughts with your friends and family, but it's more versatile and geared towards group sharing in many different ways. The new Google+ features categories such as Circles, Hangouts, Huddle, Instant Upload, Sparks, Streaming, Games and Plus 1. The category Circles, gives it's users the ability to integrate their personal contacts into groups pertaining to interests with privacy settings that allow you to hide people's names in the circle and hide the circle all together. This system replaces the well known friend's list function on Facebook that most people are not too crazy about. With the Hangouts feature, Google takes video chatting to a completely different level you can video chat with up to ten people at the same time. It also allows you to watch a video with your friends in the video chat at the same time, just by clicking the share button under the video on you tube. The only downside to this feature is that if someone gets a hold of the URL anyone can join the video chat even if they don't know them. The Huddle feature allows multiple friends to instant message each other in groups through any smart phone or computer. Let's say you and a few friends want to go to a movie. The Huddle feature makes this easy to decide which movie too see because of its ability to instant message in groups like you can do on the well know video conferencing program called Skype.
. The Instant Upload feature allows users to upload their photos from a smart phone anywhere they go and it puts the photos into a private photo album for viewing later where as, Facebook only uploads the photos directly to the front of the users page. Sometimes people don't want to share all their photos with the world so the Google's Instant Upload feature is more practical. Next, on the list of features is the Sparks feature, all you have to do is just type in what you're interested in specifically. Let's say fashion for instance and it will send you stuff it thinks you might be interested in within that category, so when you are free, there will always be something interesting to read share or watch. The Stream feature is just like any other stream except it can be filtered to only show the posts from specific Circles. Like other social networking sites Google+ also has games, but is not its main focus and does not draw attention to them very much. They only have 16 games and there is a specific tab called games that they are all listed under. The Google +1 feature is like the like button on Facebook people click on what interests them and it recommends it to others with the +1 symbol. With such a demand for social media and its ability to rapidly create back links in SEO marketing. It is quickly becoming an integral part of our everyday life and its presence has also become an important component of organic search engine optimization. It is a market any business can't afford to ignore. As you can see Google+ has a lot of similar features as the previously dominating Facebook, but the main difference is its integrating features that may give Facebook a run for its money.
Even if you write the actual check while waiting in line, it will take you forever to pay using a check in most shops. They have to take a look at your driver's license, note down all of your info, encircle your own address and then run it through the system. This isn't the store's fault. The need for all of the double-checking is definitely due to check fraud not to mention identity theft.

A lot of purchasers, like myself, have already turned to debit cards. Debit cards aren't really like plastic cards, they are basically electronic check. But some banks are starting to present frequent flier miles, rebates as well as cash rewards to usual debit card users. The lines are clouding for quite a few shoppers.

As you go shopping along with a debit card, you have to know the ins and outs and also the drawbacks.

There are 2 types of debit cards: PIN cards and signature cards. Through using a PIN card, the cash is easily deducted from your bank account. You have to use your PIN number to utilize the card. At times it's also possible to obtain cash back from the store.

Signature cards are usually called check cards. The money is actually taken off from your bank account within usually two to three days. You don't have to type in a PIN, you only need to sign the receipt.

A lot of cards these days will work as both kinds of cards. You can possibly use it as a Personal identification number card and receive cash back or as a signature card. Each type of card will work in an ATM machine. With a PIN card, the funds comes out of your account quickly. With a signature card, you have to keep track of your own receipts, since, like checks, the money won't come out for some time.

Debit cards are a great alternative to popular credit cards. You will find the efficiency of a card along with a limitation for the funds that is within your bank account. Since you cannot go on a shopping spree, you will need to monitor when using the card. It could be quite unpredictable the way it all adds up.

Debit cards do not have any of the legal protections that credit cards have. Credit cards offer you the right to uphold payments on an product that's substandard. Debit cards don't allow this, therefore you would have to attempt to obtain a replacement for the item or a refund. For large expenses, you happen to be often encouraged to use a credit card. And then simply take a moment and make the payment to your credit card company that same day.

Debit cards demand that you report a theft of your card in just a couple of days of discovering the loss in order to recoup some of your stolen funds. In the event you adhere to all guidelines, you will just be chargeable for $50. Just after two days, you will then be chargeable for $500. After two months, you may be left holding an empty bag.

Credit cards generally will offer way more protection than the law allows. Many cards offer zero liability for unauthorized use of debit cards.

While a debit card often gives you the opportunity to use it in place of a credit card, say for telephone or maybe shopping on the internet, there are times that you ought to utilize a credit card instead. Inns, rental-car companies and in some cases gas stations will place a hold on your account for a specific amount of money until you check out or perhaps return the vehicle. This particular process helps ensure them that you have the money to cover the bill.

If you are using a card that has the available credit, it is likely you won't have any trouble. But when you are using a debit card, be aware. The total amount they put on hold is precisely as if it has already been spent. This can prevent you from having checks go through or maybe withdrawing money from your bank account.

The best advice for utilizing a debit card is to be meticulous about keeping your current receipts and writing them down on your register.

It's so hassle-free, often we loose a record of how and where we have spent the cash. 
Contagion is an upcoming thriller motion picture, starring Matt Damon, Gwyneth Paltrow, along with Jude Law, Kate Winslet, Marion Cotillard, Elliott Gould, and Laurence Fishburne. This film might be much like various other thriller films, which illustrate a group of physicians and researchers, wanting to determine the reason for a disease outbreak, however it is more than what you simply expect it to be. Contagion results in practical group of incidents, which leaves spectators feeling so scared concerning the pandemic. Stream Contagion to see how the medical practitioners deal with the chaotic situation which eventually brings the individuals to a great stress.

If you do Watch Contagion Movie 2011, you will find that the movie's philosophy is very well-versed in some other breathtaking movies. Yet surely, this one is unique. In addition, it concentrates on a fatal airborne strain that could wipe out many people. This virus is passed on rapidly from a single individual to another one, leaving behind thousands of people deceased within a few days. The signs of the spread of the ailment begin with a woman, reaching for a snack bowl and handing her card to the waiter. More of it carries on as the group of business persons share handshakes with one another during a company meeting, and also a person, coughing while on the bus encompassed with plenty of individuals. With just some connection between individuals, really limited connection, a little bit of hacking and coughing, a illness has already been transferred from a single person to numerous people. It can be threatening just how this kind of condition breaks out and advances by itself easily. Because the epidemic continues to blow up, worldwide medical communities united to form a better team that will find a cure for the condition. They've looked at the potential vaccine that could probably cure the patients, yet they resort to figuring out the cause of the ailment.

Are you curious what happened next? Can they discover a method to end the spread of the condition? Or will there never be a remedy for it? Should you be wondering and interested with the resultant situations, I then propose that you Watch Contagion Online. Feel the enjoyment and pressure as increasing numbers of people are getting harmed by simply an immediate exposure to other people. Find out how this airborne ailment explodes to eliminate lots of people from numerous countries, whether they come from Hong Kong, Minneapolis, China, Japan, Chicago, or United States. This motion picture will really leave you thinking how fast and in how many little means this illness might affect the individuals. This film, which is thought to have a similar idea with many other movies, will really leave you with no regrets. Contagion is definitely worth the watch! It is a must see motion picture. And just to persuade you even more, Contagion has been a much talked about motion picture. It has been a trending topic to many curious viewers! If you want to join them and become one of them, then don't hesitate to give it a shot and Watch Contagion Full Movie Online.
Watch The Saints vs Packers Game Online Free Megavideo-Stream the Saints vs Packers Online Game

You can watch the Saints vs Packers nfl 2011 megavideo live stream on your pc using the pc tv software which is available on the internet. It is the best pc tv software that you can get online for streaming live channels on the internet since it comes with the highest quality tv shows and crystal clear packages. You can watch live streaming Saints vs Packers game online this Thursday night football 2011 season from UK, France, Canada, Ireland, Mexico, United Kingdom and all over the world.

Free Streaming live nfl 2011 game Saints vs Packers: The Internet Service

You will need to have a pc tv internet service with speeds of more than 120kbps and this can be a dsl or a broadband connection. It is easy to find a way to watch the live streaming football online with these services since they have a higher capacity to carry the heavy tv images online. The internet should also be stable to avoid the frequent interruptions due to an erratic internet connection.

Your ordinary computer can be used to stream live channels online if you have a speed of more than 500mhz and a virtual memory of more than 700mb. Your hard drive also needs to have a memory of more than 50gb for you to save any important games that you find interesting. It is possible to stream hundreds of channels online for free if you have a normal ordinary computer since these specs are very basic.

Free Streaming live Saints vs Packers 2011 Games: The Operating Software

To be able to stream the saints vs packers game today, you need to have a windows operating software which can be windows 98, 2000, 2003, 2005, XP, Vista and even Windows 7. These are like all the computers that you have in the whole world since most of them use windows.

You can watch the live streaming saints vs packers game tonight from your bedroom without even going to look for a tv set. This means that you can stream the game and over 3000 channels online and at the same time and from the same computer, do your other work online. You will not have to leave your work unattended anymore to go looking for a tv to watch the streaming nfl game.

Pros of watching live streaming tv online nfl 2011 Saints vs Packers

This is the best software to watch live streaming tv on pc online since it has over 3000 channels, has no bandwidth limits, no limitations to accessing any channel, wider variety of channels, crystal clear channels and much more. I would rank it among the top 3 pc tv software to stream live nfl 2011 football games online.

You can decide to try the service that I am using today and get online television streaming shows online here: Saints vs Packers. get online television streaming television shows - Get shows streaming television, movies, nfl preseason football, sports, music, news, documentaries, on dish nfl 2011 live stream Shows Free Stream NFL shows Crime, NEWS television shows online for free monthly fees- get television direct Streaming television Shows Software Download. 
You can watch live nfl football 2011 streaming tv shows online by using the satellite direct tv software. This is a package that is very powerful and can be used to stream nfl football games online including sports, news, movies, weather channels and music shows. You can watch free 2011 football live stream television shows on pc this Sunday on Fox, Abc, Nbc, Cbs, Fox.

Top Websites to Watch Free 2011 NFL Football Live Streaming Television Shows : The System

You need to have a computer with a virtual memory of more than 600mb and a hard drive memory of more than 50gb. The computer speeds can be anywhere from 500mhz and this will allow the pc to stream the heavy tv feeds without a problem. These are very basic specs which any computer will most likely have and yours should not be an exception to this rule either.

The internet connection needed to stream nfl live streaming television shows online should have speeds of more than 128kbps. The internet must be a dsl or broadband service with capacity to handle heavy images online. You will need the internet to be stable to avoid frequent outages.

Ways to Watch Free 2011 NFL Football Live Streaming Television Shows online:Fast Download

Satellite direct tv software is made such that it is easy to use in streaming live tv on internet. It has all the channels arranged in such a manner that they are categorised according to their sources and their contents. This makes the work of browsing and getting a channel to watch much easier.

You can be able to stream hundreds of channels online for free if you have this package in an instant. The software is fast on the download due to the fact that its a very light weight software which is accessible in 2 minutes flat. The package does not contain any unwanted adwares or malwares like most of the other pc tv systems online. This means that its light and that it does not take too much space on your hard drive.

How to Watch Free 2011 NFL Football Live Streaming Television Shows on pc: Safe Package

The software is very safe to use in any pc since it is very strict on what goes into it. The package does not have any other clutter material or files besides those of pc tv. This removes the risk that such harmful programs can be added here. It is one of the most popular pc tv package that you will ever find.

You can decide to try the service that I am using today and get online television streaming shows online here: Football Live Streaming. get online television streaming television shows - Get shows streaming television, movies, nfl regular season football, sports, music, news, documentaries, on dish nfl 2011 live stream Shows Stream NFL Television shows Crime, NEWS television shows online for free monthly fees- get television direct Streaming television Shows Software Download. 
US Open Live Tennis 2011 Stream Online in HD on PC, August 29 - September 11, 2011
Watch and enjoy US Open Tennis 2011 live streaming Tennis tournaments.US Open Tennis 2011 will start on Monday, August 29, 2011 and continue till September 11, 2011. If you are tuned into tennis and want to watch the US Open Tennis 2011 but don't have access to a TV, you can always watch the US Open 2011 matches online live from Flushing Meadows，New York, USA.
US Open Tennis 2011 is the most exciting sports event of the year, so we are sure you don't want to miss it? Thanks to Stream Direct, you can watch the US Open Tennis 2011 streaming online in perfect high definition quality! Watch all the action and excitement live online using any PC or Mac computer. Don't miss your favorite US Open Tennis 2011 Live online on Your Pc.

US Open Tennis 2011
August 29 - September 11, 2011

MATCH DETAILS:

All times ET

Sun. 8/28
Noon-1:30pm Arthur Ashe Kids' Day - CBS
1:30pm-2pm US Open Preview Show - CBS

Mon. 8/29
11am-7pm Opening Round - ]
1pm-7pm Opening Round - ESPN2
7pm-11pm Primetime at the US Open: Opening Round - ESPN2
11pm-12am US Open Tonight - Tnis Chnnel

Tue. 8/30
12am-10am US Open Daily Match Encores - el
10am-11am Breakfast at the Open - Tennis Channel
11am-7pm Opening Round - Tennis Channel
1pm-7pm Opening Round - ESPN2
7pm-11pm Primetime at the US Open: Opening Round - ESPN2
11pm-12am US Open Tonight -

CLICK HERE TO WATCH

Wed. 8/31
12am-10am US Open Daily Match Encores - Tennis Channel
10am-11am Breakfast at the Open - Tennis Channel
11am-7pm Men's First Round/Women's Second Round - Tennis Channel
1pm-7pm Men's First Round/Women's Second Round - ESPN2
7pm-11pm Primetime at the US Open: Men's First Round/Women's Second Round - ESPN2
11pm-12am US Open Tonight - Tennis Channel

Thu. 9/1
12am-10am US Open Daily Match Encores - Tennis Channel
10am-11am Breakfast at the Open - Tennis Channel
11am-7pm* Second Round - Tennis Channel
1pm-7pm Second Round - ESPN2
7pm-11pm Primetime at the US Open: Second Round - ESPN2
11pm-12am US Open Tonight - Tennis Channel

Fri. 9/2
12am-10am US Open Daily Match Encores - Tennis Channel
10am-11am Breakfast at the Open - Tennis Channel
11am-Inside winter months, you will need Spyder Jackets in addition to overcoats along with thermals, knit covers, extended sleeve handles in addition to pants in addition to pleased dresses as well as gowns. You'll be able to pick the real trendy designs which go out style rapidly. Advancements like the bubble snowboarding seldom last higher than a time period.

Following, they are moving in space for storage for a long period. Instead, select classics. Spyder Jackets pants in http://www.spyderjacketscheap.com addition to made of wool gowns inside powerful neutrals is going to be nevertheless, you such as. Consequently may an excellent reduce layer.Power below clothes are usually clothes you would placed on to be able to dying most winter months in addition to probably might hook them up to for a number of winters later on before you decide to aside create them all, as well as all of them are worn-out.

They're the things you have to look for through the several weeks' complete revenue. Clothes that may kind the particular point from the traditional winter months clothes in addition to which you'll want to generally placed on inside long-term several years. Brand new clothes need not cost
About the Author

Watch Argentina vs Nigeria Live Streaming Online Soccer International Friendly Match 6 September 2011

The International Friendly Matches League matches live Watch Nigeria vs Argentina Live Streaming is a great matches.This matches are started on Tuesday,6th of September 2011 from 14:00 GMT of Bangabandhu International Stadium in Bangladesh.
Photobucket
CLICK HERE TO WATCH LIVE ARGENTINA VS NIGERIA

Argentina Vs Nigeria Live Streaming International Friendly From Bangladesh Independent tv Channel will telecast the match Tuesday, September 6, 2011.

Preview:
Lionel Messi will look to transfer his Barcelona goalscoring form to the international stage tomorrow when he captains Argentina for the second time in their friendly against Nigeria in Bangladesh.The prolific Barca forward produced a fine display in leading the Albicelestes to a 1-0 victory over Venezuela in Kolkata on Friday, but it was defender Nicolas Otamendi who grabbed the decisive goal with a second-half header.

WATCH NOW LIVE

WATCH NOW LIVE

Messi has not netted for his country since a 4-0 win against Albania in Buenos Aires in June, going the entire Copa America campaign on home soil without finding the target.He admits the barren run has made him a little anxious, and he will aim to make it a thing of the past by scoring against the Super Eagles in Dhaka.

"I score easily for Barcelona,'' said the 24-year-old. "In the national team, I try in a number of ways and most of them I cannot score."Maybe I have to be calm enough to change this, and not feel pressure to score.''Tomorrow's friendly will be Argentina's last official encounter before they open their 2014 World Cup qualifying campaign against Chile on October 7.

CLICK HERE TO WATCH

A home-based side will then play two friendlies against Brazil - on October 14 in Cordoba, Argentina, and a fortnight later in Belem, Brazil.New coach Alejandro Sabella accepts the qualifying campaign will not be easy, even without the threat of of 2-14 hosts Brazil."Chile's football at present is the best ever,'' he said. "They are first place in South American football. Argentina and Brazil have decreased a little bit.

"Uruguay are enjoying their best moment in 20 years. Venezuela have improved a lot. Colombia are alive again and we should respect both Ecuador and Paraguay even though their form dipped at the Copa America.''Manchester City defender Pablo Zabaleta has been impressed by the impact made by Sabella since his appointment.

"To start a new coaching campaign is good,'' he said. "We played a tough Venezuelan side and did good things so in the upcoming game we have to repeat them.''

The last friendly between Argentina and Nigeria saw the African side win 4-1 in June and they head into this match buoyed by 2-0 win over Madagascar yesterday which got their African Nations Cup qualifying campaign back on track.Skipper Joseph Yobo and Obinna Nsofor netted the goals for the Super Eagles, who have collected 10 points from five matches.Everton striker Victor Anichebe picked up a groin injury towards the end of the game and is unlikely to feature tomorrow.

"It is very sad for him,'' said coach Samson Siasia. "He was huge for us (in the Madagascar game). He did all the rights things, played well and unfortunately had to come off in the last three minutes with an injury. But that's football."It's very unfortunate, but I hope he gets well soon so he can continue to feature for his club. That pitch was not very good and we are lucky our players did not get serious injuries.''

Argentina Vs Nigeria Live Streaming International Friendly From Bangladesh Independent tv Channel will telecast the match Tuesday, September 6, 2011.Argentina Vs Nigeria Live Streaming International Friendly From Bangladesh Independent tv Channel will telecast the match Tuesday, September 6, 201 