About a year ago I wrote an article titled 'Winning The War On
Sp^m'. Unfortunately, the war on sp^m is not being won at all.

In fact, the problem is now so serious that sp^am is shaping up
to be the greatest threat to online marketing.

The threat comes not from sp^mmers themselves, but from the
filters that are being used to block them.

These filters are hitting hard at the very core of ecommerce -
Ezine Publishing.

Anti-sp^m filters operate at two levels: (i) client-side
programs that reside on individual computers and (ii)
server-side programs that ISPs are using to block incoming sp^m.

The problem is that the filters are now so sensitive they are
blocking even the most innocent of Newsletters.

For example, if your Newsletter contains the words 'remove',
'unsubscribe' or 'click here' it will trigger anti-sp^m filters
in many of the programs that are now being used by ISPs.

The result?

Your Ezine is zapped, deleted - and a large percentage of your
subscribers will think you have stopped publishing your
Newsletter.

What can you do about it?

Here are some tips to avoid sp^m filters:

(1) Post your Newsletter online and then email your subscribers
to tell them that the latest issue is now available online.

(2) In your Newsletter carefully avoid (both in the subject line
and the body text) all words that are likely to trigger
anti-sp^m filters. Use the free service listed at the end of
this article - it will flag any words in your Newsletter that
trigger anti-sp^m filters.

(3) Instead of saying 'to unsubscribe' (which is a phrase
commonly found in sp^m), say 'If you no longer wish to
receive...' or 'If you wish to leave this mailing list...' or
'To take yourself off this list...'

(4) If there are trigger words that you simply cannot avoid, you
can disguise them using carets (^) or other symbols. The 'F'
word would become fr^e and the 'U' word would become
uns^bscribe.

(5) Include the word 'Newsletter' in the subject line of your
email - this will help the filters identify your email as
non-sp^m.

(6) Avoid whole words in upper case. In many Newsletters the
headers are capitalized - this will trigger the filters.

(7) If your Newsletter contains ads, scrutinize them carefully -
ezine ads, by definition, contain words frequently used by
sp^mmers.

Here is a fr^e service that will help you avoid sp^m filters.
Before you mail out your Newsletter, just send a copy of it to
the email address below with TEST in the subject line:
mailto:spamcheck@sitesell.net

Within a few seconds you'll receive a report that analyses your
Newsletter and gives you a score (0 to 5=no problems 12-16=over
the limit for most ISPs).

If you write articles, it's worth submitting them to this test
as well, together with your Resource Box (I just sent this
article to Sp^mCheck and got a score of 4.6).

Sp^mCheck is operated by Sp^mAssassin, a filter that is widely
used by ISPs - so this is a good test of whether your Newsletter
will get through to your subscribers. 
When you decide that you would like to go into business for yourself,
the first step is deciding on a type of business that fits your idea
of "comfortable" and "fun". After all, the whole reason you want to go
into business for yourself is the fact that what you are doing right
now is "uncomfortable", and "not fun".

So, the first thing you should do is make a personal assessment of who
you are. For instance, what do you like? What are your favorite
hobbies? Do you like working with or around people? Or, are you a
homebody? Do you have any skills that could help you (such as typing,
office skills, organizational skills, etc.)? What do you dislike?

Yes, what you dislike is as important as what you like. Without
knowing what your dislikes are, you are liable to turn your projects
into something that you don't want to do, but end up stuck with.
Figuring out what you dislike before-hand will enable you to plan
accordingly, and make sure that what you dislike does not interfere
with what you are trying to build. Dislikes help you decide policies
and procedures that you normally would not think of when writing out
your business plan.

For instance: Do you like or dislike knocking on stranger's doors? Are
you comfortable or uncomfortable talking to strangers face to face?
How do you feel about telephones? Do you feel differently about emails
or letter writing through postal mail?

If you are comfortable talking to people face to face, then you should
start out with products that you believe in, and go for the direct
selling technique. However, if you are more comfortable with writing,
you may want to consider a mail order type business, or an internet
business.

Whatever type of business you choose, it will be up to you to decide
the best marketing strategies to fit your needs. You will be making
list after list of what works, what doesn't work, and why you feel it
failed, and how you think you could have improved the methods. After
all, whatever business you decide to get yourself into will be up to
you to promote. If it fails, it will be because either the market
wasn't there, or the promotion wasn't there. Both reasons will be your
own responsibility to account for.

While deciding what is "comfortable" and "fun" will help alleviate the
worry and dread of working at what you enjoy, we must remember that
running your own business is work -- and sometimes it requires
breaking a sweat in order to make a profit. So, once you have decided
what is "comfortable" and "fun", you will need to decide what skills
you are best at that will help you manage and promote your business.

Test your targeted market by using several methods, at first, to
promote your business. Find the one that works best for you, and then
be consistent. When you are doing something you enjoy doing, doing it
every day doesn't seem so hard. 
Customer Service starts with the customer... in applying
just a little thought. Let me try a scenario...

You see an ad in your local newspaper for a new home-
delivery pizza service, so you decide to give it a try. You
call them, you order the one with all the trimmings and they
give you the usual response that your pizza will arrive in
10 minutes. Sixty minutes pass slowly and still no pizza.

You're getting hungry, so do you?

A. Call the pizza parlour

B. Call the newspaper that ran the ad

If you answered B, then you have chosen what a LOT of
people are, increasingly, doing online. Would you expect
the newspaper to be able to tell you where your pizza is?

Of course not!

Even if the pizza parlour's phone was engaged, or out of
order, you still wouldn't call the newspaper, I'm sure.

Then why do people expect the publisher of a newsletter
to be able to answer questions about an order placed at the
web site of an independent, third-party advertiser?

Perhaps it is because publishers are accessible? Whatever
the reason, it's an inattention to the details that really
matter and a pure lack of thinking.

Most publishers I know are very willing to help, but I think
you'll agree that they can really only be expected to answer
questions about their own products and services, ordering
processes and other technical what-have-you.

A minor point, you say? The publisher can just pass your
message on. Yeah and they probably have to do EXACTLY what
I'm about to describe to be able to do so. Maybe they could
tune your car and sweep your yard at the same time?

Self Service Solutions...

Do you FULLY read what you are responding to? Do you really
look at the site (and it's location), from which you are
buying? Do you even look for contact information?

(If there isn't any, you should SERIOUSLY question whether
you should risk making that purchase in the first place.)

Remember, ads are just that, ads. In all cases it is up to
YOU, the BUYER, to beware and do your own due diligence.
Even if you trust the person who made the recommendation.

Often a simple remedy, if you are at an internal page of
a site where there isn't a direct link to contact the folks
at the site you actually purchased from, is to go to the
front page of that site and look for the information.

Lets say you are at:

http://www.somevendor.com/product.html

Well then, stick your cursor in the address bar of your
browser, use the backspace/erase key to wipe out the
product.html bit so all you have left in there is:

http://www.somevendor.com

Then click GO. Betcha you'll find something which says
*contact* or *email us* or *customer service* even that
leads you to the information you want and a means to
contact the RIGHT people with your question or query.

It should be obvious that you'll get a faster and better
answer if you'll just take 30 seconds to help yourself.

If you are a merchant, you would do well to review your site
and ensure that there is contact information, or at the very
least a link to a page where it is displayed, from EVERY
page of your site. Make life dead simple for your customer.

If you operate an affiliate scheme, any number of people
could be advertising for you. You will not necessarily know
where and when. Likewise, those affiliates cannot know how
to answer questions about your ordering process, so don't
require them to by hiding your contact information, such
that customers write to the affiliate advertiser instead.

If you are the affiliate, you need to LOOK closely at the
site you are advertising. Yet another reason why you should
be a customer before you promote something. What do you
look like when your referrals suffer problems?

If you are doing business online, then likely you'll fall
into all categories of seller, advertiser and buyer. If you
get poor quality answers -- and thus PERCEIVED poor quality
service -- because you ask poor quality questions or pose
your questions to the wrong people, this does nothing for
anyone's credibility. Least of all your own!

How daft would that newspaper editor think you are, if you
ring him at 10.30 p.m. to ask where your pizza is?
Self-employed people are consistently searching for new and
innovative methods to get clients. Inevitably, one comes
across a company or service that offers to serve as a
project broker for free agents, independent consultants,
contractors, and clients. This article explains how these
services work, the experience I had, and items to consider
when evaluating these companies and services.

Why are independent consultants, free agents, and
freelancers drawn to these companies and services? There
are two main reasons.

First, these people either do not know how or do not like to
market their services to others. The idea of potential
clients coming to them is very enticing since it requires
little effort. You just have to sit back and wait for the
assignments to be posted. When you see an assignment that
fits your experience and expertise, all you have to do is
submit a proposal and then wait for a decision.

Second, these companies offer a means to broaden your
exposure in the marketplace. The thinking goes that if
enough people are aware of the services I offer, I'll get a
client.

Now, let's talk about how these services work.

In order to view a list of projects, submit proposals, and
ultimately get clients, you need to "join" or "sign up" with
a particular company or service. Generally, this process
requires 3 things:

1. You provide detailed information about your expertise and
the services you offer. This information is placed on a web
site and is accessible to potential clients and other free
agents looking for joint venture partners or subcontractors.

2. You pay a fee that is billed either monthly or annually.
This fee gives you access to the database of projects that
are currently listed. For each assignment you get through
the company or service, you may have to pay a percentage of
your project's total cost as a "finder's fee."

3. You provide references that potential clients can contact
to inquire about your work. The company or service you join
may want to verify your references to make sure you're as
competent as you describe. There is a possibility your
references may have to fill out a questionnaire or
participate in a phone survey regarding your work and
professionalism too.

Once you've provided all the relevant information about your
expertise and services, your references are verified, and
you've paid the appropriate fees, the "sign-up" process is
complete. You are now free to search the current project
database, submit proposals, and hopefully get clients!

Some years ago I signed up with one of these services for
one year. I will not disclose the company's name but here's
what I learned:

1. You can sign up with these services or companies even if
you don't meet all of their stated requirements. When I was
contemplating joining a particular company, I didn't have
enough previous clients the company required. However, when
I explained my situation, I was permitted to join.
Remember, the organization doesn't make money if they turn
you away.

2. Don't be fooled by the advertising hype touting thousands
of available projects. If 95% of the projects listed are
not in your area of expertise or industry, that sure doesn't
help you get a client.

3. You may not get any clients. During my year's time, only
one project somewhat fit my skills and experience. I had to
partner with another consultant in order to meet the
project's requirements. Together, we submitted a proposal
but didn't get the project.

4. For each project, you compete against a group of people
that provide similar services. This competition further
reduces the probability you'll get the project. However, if
you get clients through people you know or through a
friend-of-a-friend, the competition doesn't exist.

5. It can take a long time to get a project. The person I
partnered with on my lone proposal said it took him 3 years
to get a project through this company. While his project
more than made up for the cost he incurred up to that point,
he was strongly considering not renewing his account.

6. Some of the projects submitted are only ploys to test the
marketplace for a particular kind of service. Others are a
means to satisfy a company's policy that requires
"competition" for each project. The reality is a free agent
was selected before the "competition" search began.
However, this should not deter you from submitting
proposals. You never know if you'll get a project unless
you submit a proposal.

Here are some thoughts to consider when evaluating the
various project broker services:

1. Are there a sufficient number of projects listed in your
industry that match your skills and experience? If a large
portion of the projects involve unfamiliar industries, be
cautious.

2. Can you get your money back if you are not completely
satisfied within 30 days?

3. Is there a clause that you get your money back if you
don't get a project within the first year? This way you
can't lose. The worst that happens is the company uses your
money free for one year.

4. Does the company or service perform marketing in the
offline world? Just because you are in cyberspace doesn't
mean your potential clients reside there too. Exposure in
the real world through press releases, magazine ads in
appropriate industry publications and trade journals are a
good indication the company is getting the word out.

If you are a new free agent or if you haven't had many
clients, it is best to spend your time strengthening your
local relationships. These contacts are an excellent means
to get your first few clients. Consider joining these
services when you become more experienced, have an adequate
client list, and can afford the risk.
Imagine a computer with no operating system. If you can do that,
you can imagine a computer that is extremely difficult to hack
into. A computer that is almost immune to viruses. A computer
that rarely crashes.

Too good to be true? No, such a computer has been invented.

Eric Hauk and Eric Uner, 2 former Motorola engineers, invented
this computer. They became so frustrated and annoyed by hack
attacks and by all the time they wasted installing software patches,
that they decided to change their server. Instead of an operating
system, they designed a chip storing a "kernel" of only about
4 Kilobytes of code. They founded Bodacion Technologies Inc.
(http://www.bodacion.com) to market their computer, which is
called Hydra.

This is essentially the same idea that is used for medical devices
and for game-playing machines like Nintendo. Nintendo rarely
breaks down even though young hackers are constantly trying.

Why is an operating-system-less computer more sturdy than one
with an operating system? What do many viruses do? Once they
get into the system they manage to modify operating-system instructions
to kill the whole system. But if operating-system instructions
do not exist, or rather they exist in hardware, they cannot be
modified. Result: a computer you can depend on.

Of course, this tremendous reliability comes at price. Why does
the operating system have millions of lines of code? To increase
the flexibility of the computer. This is why such computers are
called general purpose computers. Without the O.S., the computer
loses this flexibility and becomes one that is tailored for a
given purpose.

Producing many tailored non-O.S. computers is now worthwhile
in order to achieve greater reliability.

It seems to me that this new technology is better than it appears
to be at first blush. It may even be used to make general purpose
computers more resistant to viruses. If a non-O.S. computer were
used as an input-output device for a conventional O.S. computer,
it could kill viruses before they reach the conventional computer.

I believe that non-O.S. computers have a great future! 
This article is for all those who have asked "how do I get
my business online?" or have just plain been putting it off
because you dont know where to start or who can help or how
much it will cost.

Why should I put my business online? Well, there are several
reasons why you should.

Firstly, its a great 'connection point' between you and your
customers or partners. They can visit your website at
anytime that suits them to find out more about you, your
products, ordering, or just get more information. Previously
they would have had to physically visit you or use the
telephone and actually speak to you. They can contact you
with questions, complaints, recommendations or just to gauge
how helpful/efficient you are at anytime without speaking to
you or being face-to-face with you. Its another way to deal,
communicate and interact with you. It puts the emphasis on
the customer and their needs and removes the pushy salesman
from the process. This level of anonymity encourages the
customer to get what they want more than ever before or go
somewhere else where they will get it.

Secondly, the Internet enables the customer to shop around
much more easily and cheaply than ever before. It is as easy
to research and buy a product that is sold in another
country as it is to do it for one in your own country and
all for the cost of a local call. Timezones are largely
irrelevant on the Internet.

Thirdly, a website is entirely flexible and can be designed
from scratch specifically for your business and customers,
regardless of the industry you are in and the size of your
business.

Fourth, it is low cost. You can build a website to meet your
budget.

What do you need to do?

Get a web address - often called a domain name/URL. When
someone types in your web address i.e. http://www.youraddress.com
into their Internet enabled computer, they see your website.
Get a name that is easily remembered by your customers.
You'll need to renew it regularly to keep the name.

Get some webspace - often called hosting. A company (the
host) will rent you space on its computer. You store your
website in that space. Your web address will point here so
that when the web address is typed in by the customer, they
will be directed to your website automatically. Make sure
you get a fast and reliable host and therefore your website
is always available and quickly. Read host reviews or ask
people you know to recommend a host.

Research - before doing anything else do some research. Look
at other websites, styles, navigation, content, functions,
etc. What do you like? What dont you like? What do your
customers want? What dont they want? What are your
competitors doing? What arent they doing? Set some clear
objectives for your site. Write them down in order of
priority and work towards them throughout the project.

Content - The most important of all. Whether its text,
images, functions, data or anything else, spend some time
getting it right. It must of course, all meet your clear
objectives.

Design and build your website - you can do this yourself but
I dont recommend it unless you are confident you can do it
well and have enough time to do it. Hire someone to do it
all for you. Make sure you are happy to deal with them and
that they dont just want to design a pretty website for
their portfolio. They should make all the right noises about
how the website will fit into your business and how your
customers will benefit from it. Again, remember your clear
objectives.

Evaluation - check your website meets all your objectives.
Check everything works as it should and is easy to
understand and use by your customers. Do you need to make
any improvements/changes?

Publish - put your new website into your webspace.
Congratulations your business is online!

Finally, review your website initially and regularly
thereafter to make sure it is still meeting your customers
requirements and to see if it can be improved or developed
further.

Good luck and dont forget to let me know how you get on. 
These days we are all busy and under pressure to squeeze
ever more into our working day. Often, we are so busy
working and earning a living that we lose sight of our
goals. This is especially true when you run your own
business. You are so busy actually running your business
that you lose sight of the reasons that you started it in
the first place and the goals you want to achieve. The
problem is that all the time you are not absolutely focused
and working towards your goals, you and your business are
going in another direction altogether. The wrong direction!
How do you get back on track and heading in the right
direction?

Okay, admit it, when was the last time you actually
scheduled some quality time to identify your goals and a
direction for your business? Last week, last month, last
year, never? If you are like most busy business people, you
probably havent done it for some time at least. Well, today
I'm here to tell you to STOP! Yes, STOP RIGHT NOW and take a
breather. Renew that vision, that passion, that excitement.
Take some time out and put yourself and your business back
on track. Its not difficult to do, it just takes a little
investment of your time thats all.

Start by getting out of your usual work environment
altogether. Go somewhere relaxing like a coffee bar or a
park. Now, think about what you and your business do and how
you do it. Reassess all aspects of your business and work
life. Try to think creatively and of the bigger picture
rather than your usual point of view. Consider how others
fit into the picture. Ask yourself some difficult questions
and explore your answers a little. Write your answers and
thoughts down as you work through them - it makes it easier
to see them clearly.

Here's some questions to consider and get you started in the
right area. Add other questions as you feel necessary:

Why did you start your business?
How do you do things now?
How could you do things better?
How do your competitors compare?
What do you offer that is unique?
What direction are you going in?
What direction do you want to go in?
What are your goals?
What steps are you taking to reach those goals?
What opportunities are you missing?
What opportunities do you want?
What position do you want to be in 5, 10, 15, 20 years time?

Spend some time thinking through your answers and reflecting
on them. The more you do that the more your business will
benefit. Dont forget to keep writing things down for clarity
and future reference. Now with those things in mind make
some important decisions and identify two things:

1. the precise goals you want to achieve,
2. the time frame you want to achieve them within.

Write them down. Now all you need is a good plan to achieve
those goals. Break the goals down into smaller more
manageable tasks and schedule them over your specified time
frame. Break them down into weekly and daily tasks. Write
those daily and weekly tasks into your diary and number them
in priority order, number 1 being highest priority. Do the
highest priority tasks first each day and tick off each task
as you complete it. If you dont complete a task that day put
a cross next to it and reschedule it onto another day.

Doing it this way helps you stay focused in the right
direction at all times and aware of using your time
effectively. Keep focused on your goals and work to your
plan every single working day, throughout the day. I arrange
my whole weeks schedule on Sunday evening, so that i know
what i must be doing at all times throughout the week. At
the end of the week you can review what you completed and
plan the next week accordingly.

You now have a plan that is taking you in the direction you
want to go in - towards your goals. The more focused you are
the more effective you are. Use this new opportunity and
focus to renew your concentration and double your efforts.
Every time you complete a task you are another step nearer
your goal. What are you waiting for? Get started right now
and build the future you've always wanted. You can do it.

Good luck! 
The first thing required for successful communication - be it in sales or something
else - is to find a common interest.

Success is achieved when two individuals agree they have the same goal and are
discussing which of them is going to do what in order for them to reach their
common goal faster, easier and with greater certainty.

If the person you are talking with feels, even slightly, that he has been cheated
or that you took advantage of him - by him being your means to reaching your
goals - he folds from the game. Often, this other person could be a customer
who feels your greatest desire is selling your product - without considering
whether that product will meet his needs or desires.

If you don't first harmonize, by finding a common interest, you end up creating
a situation wherein each party is engulfed in defending their interests: one
is proving why something is good and beneficial to the other and the other is
defending himself by proving why that same thing is of no use to him and doesn't
suit his needs.

By doing this, you presume:

1) You will convince the other party to accept your truth, or worse...

2) You can make the other party feel so "good" about the purchase that they will
be back to buy more from you!

This is often impossible. Sure, your prospects may actually buy, sometimes -
but this doesn't come even close to securing a long-term relationship with them
and ensure they will repeatedly purchase from you.

The solution is somewhere else, and a very simple one at that: once you discover
the common goals you and your prospect share (such as ensuring greater success
for your prospect's company), you help him realize those goals.

Mr. Ron is a sports shoe importer. He was always having problems negotiating
with his suppliers. Then he changed something. Before he sat down at the table
again to negotiate with his supplier, he said:

"Look, we all have the same goal - getting your top-notch sport shoes to the
public. Let's not waste time arguing and fighting over petty issues. Why don't
we imagine there's a customer standing here in front of us right now. Let's all
put our suggestions on the table and discuss how each one of us can help make
this customer's decision easier and faster and what we can do to make him want
to return more often and buy more of your shoes from me."

Just saying these few sentences placed him and his supplier on equal and common
ground to negotiate. A few days later, he sent me a note saying this was the
best and fastest deal he ever made. And it was so simple...

>> How an Importer Cultivates Loyalty From His Customers � Even When �The Competion
Offers Higher Percentages�

How do you �negotiate� in the real world? How can you convince your prospects
to buy something from you and keep buying it over and over again? The easiest
and most successful aproach is helping the store (in any way possible) sell your
goods as fast and easy as possible so that they will see buying from you as an
opportunity and not like purchasing from you is a liability.

That said, the best starting place for negotiating is: develop an efficient marketing
system for your product (purchasing, logistics, marketing, sales, after-sales
activities, follow up, etc.), test it in the real world and then offer it to
the store along with the product.

This way you're not just selling your product as if you were saying: �Here it
is, now make the best of it... and by the way, we're not through yet; whether
you buy something from me today or not, I'll be back soon to sell you this product
(if you decide against purchasing it today) or a new product...�

Offer the tool and the solution. The fabric and the scissors.

When would you rather buy an unknown product from someone to sell? Would you
choose the untested product or the one that that has been market tested, comes
with a case study that precisely shows the marketing system they used and how
to handle its marketing, sales, product education, market approach and similar?


And what if they could even forecast the actual and approximate sales success
for this product, on the basis of previous experience, based on your sales team
working according to the suggested system (in other words: if you already knew
approximately how much risk the product presents for your company)? Or, what
if they even showed you how all these procesess work in practice? Or even further,
what if they offered you sales team training along with the product?

If you offered all this, you really wouldn't need to have any polished �negotiating
skills� to generate the client's interest � you are already offering them exactly
what they want and need... and more. If you did all this consistently and as
part of your work ethic, you would find yourself in the desirable situation of
you being able to choose whom to trust to sell your product.
The sales people would be seeking you out instead of the other way around!

This is negotiating for the �new era� that is not only marked by greater sales
success, but also by deeper and more friendly human relationships, an excellent
flow of information, the ability to act without fear or bad feelings, and above
all, alot of satisfaction, pleasure, respect and joy. This is what happens when
you solve problems where they begin: at their cause! 