A successful online business can be built at reasonable cost. Don't have a
product? That's okay. A topical affiliate site might be the answer for you.
This means you take your passion or hobby and turn it into profit. You don't
keep inventory; you don't have to deliver or ship products; you just
maintain your web site & enjoy being with your family. Even if you do have a
product, you many want to consider filling out your web site with other
affiliate products that relate to your site's theme.

I'm sure you've seen some grossly blatant affiliate sites with banners
everywhere & pop-ups that just won't stop popping. These are not the way to
make money - they just end up being kind of offensive.

Like I said, take your passion. For example, say you are really into
photography. You don't have to be an expert, but since you are passionate,
you will have a good knowledge base. You'll be surprised at what you learn
from building your site around this idea. Include photography tips and
articles. Build a newsletter and have your readers make submissions. Give
your customers a reason to come to your site - outside of purchasing your
products.

You will make commission from the affiliate programs, but don't simply paste
banners on your site - you need to include these products (whether it be
cameras, software, courses, books, magazine subscriptions etc.) in the
context of your site. Do editorials on the various products and services -
that way people will already be interested in the product before they click
on the links.

Yes, you will likely spend some money promoting your site, but you can
certainly do it on a budget. There are numerous free ways to promote your
site. Just think of the money you save in gas, postage, paper and time by
having an online business. The time alone is worth it! 
How to age well is quite the topic these days. One thing that's often debated is whether one should live in a retirement community or not.

This is so much a matter of personal preference. You can be happy and have good experiences anywhere (or not). The main thing is that you keep going and growing. In my coaching practice, I have many people over the age of 60. Let me share some of the things I've learned.

Who you hang with matters a lot at any time in life. A retirement community can give you commiseration for things - someone to talk with about Vietnam, and what's wrong with the government, and what helps arthritis. More importantly, people who can share your frustration. Like going shopping and having to wade through 50 cheese choices instead of 3. People who, when the discussion turns to the fact that there may be social security in 20 years, remember the time before there was social security and know that life goes on - which is irritating for youngsters to hear. That sort of thing, and you should always keep people around who share your history

However, this can be too much of a good thing. It is healthy at any time in life to associate with people who are very different from you--in age and in every other way. I coach emotional intelligence, I should add, and we're talking here about things that research has shown help us age better.

There's the famous "new toys, new playmates" study with the mice. The ones who were given a steady supply of new and stimulating toys in their cages, and got to meet new little mice did a lot better. So if you live in a retirement community, be sure you get out of it quite often.

You see, we cannot form new brain cells as we age, but we can form new neuronal connections, and to do this, we need new experiences. Take the analogy of marriage. It's great to be in love and have a great spouse. However, to keep the relationship alive and interesting, you both need to go out and meet new people and do new things, and bring that back to the relationship.

So wherever you choose to live, make sure you keep going - mentally, physically and emotionally. Learning something new is one of the best things you can do. I mean SO new that you're totally lost. Where you can feel the brain working to try and get around it, and not really having anything to hang it on. I mean learning to play the violin when you are (or were) a physics professor. Or getting a job if you never worked outside the home. Or moving to a new place where you have to learn how to get around on the highways. If you're reading this with a parent in mind, encourage this as well. Keep asking, "What's new?"

One reason people grow through crises is because it's something you can't get your mind around. Some people, of course, do not GROW through a crisis, they just GET through it and then, sometimes, harden and grow brittle. Things are not going to adjust to YOU, you must adjust to THEM. You can learn resilience, BTW, it's an emotional intelligence competency, as is the sort of frustration tolerance it takes to sit in the back of the classroom and know nothing at all. Now there's a new experience for a senior! Best thing in the world.

Also pay close attention to where you go for counsel. Whether it's a coach, therapist, or clergy, don't ever stick with someone who seems to have no ideas or enthusiasm for you and your life, or who doesn't keep pushing you to your growing edge. You always have a growing edge, no matter how old you are. Unless you decide you don't, in which case you are right! Check out Yvonne Dowlen, figure skating at the age of 80+: http://www.dailyherald.com/galleries/benskate/index.HTML. "If you don't move," she says, "you can't move." This applies to the mental and the emotional as well as the physical. This woman has real spirit. She had a car accident and her doctor told her to give up skating and she took that as a challenge.

Good role models? Oh, there are the obvious ones, like Art Linkletter, James Brown, Jack Lalanne, Luciano Pavarotti and Colonel Sanders, but that's like looking at movie stars. There are things we know about their lives, and things we don't and they sort of live on another plane anyway.

Let me share with you some real life examples, some real life heroes. They're the best kind. Names and a few details changed for confidentiality.

Julie is 63. She tore a core muscle last year and had some bad months where she could hardly walk, but she was determined to get back to her - yes - rollerblading, and she is. She also became fluent in Russian and German in the past 5 years.

Maureen lost her adult son when she was 60. This might crater a person, and who would blame them. Instead Maureen moved to a big city and got a job downtown, with a 4 hour commute in some of this nation's worst traffic and in a new field. She says it's keeping her young.

Raymond, a retired math professor is 70 and his wife died last year. He is enthusiastically looking on the Internet sites and dating. He travels to one of his kids' homes every month, and just got back from an Alaskan cruise - his 10th.

Annie, 55, lost her husband 5 years ago and went into a shell. Well not with good coaching you don't! With encouragement, she's over her fibromyalgia, started playing tennis again and got back into her size 6s. She's dating on the Internet and just bought a new home.

On my last river cruise to Russia was Amanda, 87 years old, on her own. She said she hadn't had time to before then. She fell in Moscow, and got some bandages but she refused to even talk about it, just kept smiling. She said she was there to have a good time, and wanted the rest of us to. What a woman! After the 2-week cruise, she was staying over in St. Petersburg for 2 weeks at a hotel.

Nancy is over 60 and speaks on cruises. Like many people of an age, she knows a lot and always has topics of interest. She stays current on the Internet. She pays a small per diem, and her companion travels free. This makes her very popular! No, she's not a retired college professor, she's just a dynamic and great speaker with the wealth of information one can have at this age.

Edward, 85, was someone I trained to be a coach. Coaching is a great late-in-life profession because clients come to you and want your advice and listen to you, good clients that is. Edward said he felt wanted and needed and that his own kids wouldn't listen to him, so this was fun! And BTW, he had to learn how to do a website. Not a problem to this guy!

One last one, Peter the successful attorney, 60. He signed up for a film course and just made his first movie. It's very artsy. "I needed that," he said.

60 is the new 40, so 80 must be the new 60. Wherever you decide to live, keep yourself surrounded by the good old things, but be sure and give yourself a nice supply of new playmates, new experiences, and new toys. 
SD: I love all music (except acid rock and rap). I live for music, that's why I founded Club Vivo Per Lei. But my least favorite kind of music is jazz. I feel that's a deficit. You love jazz, Moreen. What can you tell me to get me started?

MM: Jazz has been called "the sound of surpise". So, like all surprises, it takes some getting used to. For me, I learned about jazz sort of by osmosis. My brother Colin, who plays bass trombone, started my interest when he was learning his instrument in the high school band. I couldn't help listening to the albums that were around. He started with rock bands like Chicago and Blood Sweat and Tears and also bands from the big band era--people like Glen Miller and Tommy Dorsey (trombone players and bandleaders, both). My parents had also been exposed to jazz in their youth through big bands which were really the popular music of the day.

SD: But all that squeaking and squawking...

MM: I've heard that before! To be honest there is that component to it, but so much of it is based around standards - beautiful and timeless melodies. As for the dissonant sounds...

SD: Thanks for reframing that for me. Actually I'm an opera buff and I hear that about screeching sopranos...

MM: You're welcome. Now as for those dissonant sounds, those can be from hard bop to free jazz--which can be an acquired taste. I myself like the bebop period which ranges from the mid forties into the fifties, the heyday of musicians such as Miles Davis, Dizzy Gillespie, Charlie Parker and Thelonius Monk. Remember, jazz encompasses a lot of eras and styles from trad jazz (think of New Orleans and Louis Armstrong) to swing (big band era) to bebop to cool, Latin and fusion (rock and jazz). A few players even went through several styles, Miles Davis, for instance.

SD: Well with the surprise and the dissonance, how do I dip my toe in?

MM: The easiest way for most people to ease into jazz is through vocalists. Modern day artists like Diana Krall and the wonderful Diane Reeves, Bobby McFerrin and my personal favourite, Kurt Elling. (Here is Kurt singing in Rio: http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2Z6VV3w1Pp8 ) Earlier vocalists include the inimitable Billie Holliday, fabulous Ella Fitzgerald, Dinah Washington, Nat King Cole (yes, Nat started out as a jazz pianist), Frank Sinatra, and the list goes on.

SD: I think I'd like to approach it chronologically for some reason. Probably for the same reason I don't like the surprise.

MM: LOL. Well, Ken Burns' documentary on Jazz is a good place to start. It goes through jazz history chronologically - a course in jazz if you will. (Here is the link: http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ITbuFIG4Xvc )

SD: What did you do to learn more and help spread the word?

MM: I love jazz so much I volunteer at Canada's Premier Jazz Station. I have had a proud affiliation with them as a volunteer. This past year I have had the opportunity of meeting, greeting and scheduling jazz music students from four schools: University of Toronto, Humber College, Mohawk College and York University - the next generation of jazz greats. I also have been volunteering with jazz festivals for a number of years and I go the Clubs.

SD: What kind of people generally like jazz?

MM: The demographics? Jazz listeners comprise about 3% of the population, a very select group. Generally older, male, well educated and affluent.

SD: Ah hah. So if you're a woman looking for a rich, older, well-educated guy you might want to hang out at jazz clubs?

MM: I've seen some there. Super nice guys, too. If possible, the best way to experience jazz is go out to hear it LIVE! In a club, at a festival, in a restaurant. Especially if you happen to live in a city like New York or Chicago or Toronto, where I live. There is a wealth of music out there every night!

SD: Can you recommend a CD to start my jazz collection?

MM: Sure, glad to. Kind of Blue by Miles Davis. This is a must for any collection. It still sounds fresh more than 50 years after it was recorded. The band DID NOT REHEARSE - they recorded each track as they played it. Amazing!

SD: And now for the plug. What's that station you love to volunteer at?

MM: http://www.jazz.fm - you can listen online, 24/7.

SD: Well thanks for the tips.

MM: You're welcome. I hope this has intrigued you a little bit and that you will explore my favourite kind of music!

SD: One last thing. What's in that stuff? A random check on jazz news at Jazz91 FM's site mentioned Honest Ed Mirvish dying at 91; news of George Mely, 80, and that pianist Ahmad Jamal, 77, had received France's highest artistic award recently.

MM: Some of them did, it's true, but there were also tragically young deaths like ___________. That's probably true in any field.

SD: Still, such long-lived men. As a Life Coach, I know what music does for stress levels. Maybe there's something special about jazz that might be worth looking in to. Thanks Moreen for this helpful and informative introduction to jazz.

Moreen Murray lives in Toronto Canada and regularly volunteers at Canada's premier jazz station, Jazz 91 FM.
When you call to find out what's playing, she might be the one who answers the phone. Moreen is a frequent contributor to
Club Vivo Per Lei/I Live for Music. 
With typical marketing hyperbole, Mikel Jollett's article, "The Miracle of Ice," about a new surgical technique involving induced hypothermia, is summed, presumably by the editor, with "the only catch: it kills you before it saves you."

This could be applied to most of the things in our lives that nearly 'kill' us; the slings and arrows of fortune we are all heir to. They either kill us, or we have a new life. But I digress.

Yes, there is a surgeon having great success using induced-hypothermia when operating on the brains of stroke victims. This is the story of a new-OLD procedure that involves cooling the body, but this is for hours, not minutes; and a surgeon gutsy enough to use his common sense and go with something that works. I'm not mentioning his name for a reason. He's the SUNG hero, but there's an UNsung hero in this story.

20 years ago, induced hypothermia was used only as a last resort, when there was nothing to lose, like surgery on a stopped heart. The body would be chilled by a combination of techniques, to 18 degrees C (64 F); scary, as there are potentially lethal side-effects such as frostbite, shock, pneumonia, and death.

How did we discover the use of this procedure?
It was thanks to Raul Busto, a research assistant at the University of Miami, way back in 1987.

The wonder of this story is that Jollett found this piece of information when researching the article, and thought to include it.

Raul didn't get to write an article in the prestigious JAMA about his discovery. He didn't get invited to address the national convention of brain surgeons. He didn't get promoted to head of the department or have a chair named for him at a medical center. I don't know the facts, but he probably didn't even get a raise or bonus.

Busto, observant guy that he was, simply noticed that even when blood flow was cut off to a section of the brain in certain rats, they didn't have a stroke, and this in rats whose body temps were only a few degrees below normal.

Raul then had the presence of mind to connect the dots on what he observed. The wonder is that his presumably small voice was heard.

There are people who lack the credentials, by choice, by chance or by lack of opportunity, who are making tremendous contributions to our lives all the time. The diagnosis by the grandmother down the street, the perceptive comment of the nail technician, a caring neighbor or teacher who notices something, the mechanic tinkering in his garage or the nascent genius in the computer or medical lab.

Examples? I hear many from clients.

Bill and Mary, with combined IQs of 300, were told by their son's teacher that he needed glasses. When he got them, the child exclaimed, "There are leaves on trees! Look, I can see trash in people's yard."

Susan got her son into drug rehab just in time because her colleague at work met the teenager and suggested to Susan that those red eyes and that runny nose weren't "allergies."

Liquid paper was invented by some secretary who had a brain and was able to think outside the box.

The glue on post-it notes was a lab failure for a permanent glue, but the researcher had common sense, and thought a temporary bond might have an application. (Could we live without our post-it notes?)

Martha found out her baby had a tumor because when her mother was changing the baby's diapers, she noticed what the younger mother couldn't differentiate.

And my client in Venezuela gave me the key to another client I couldn't fathom. "They're mountain people," she said. "You know." I did not. But in Venezuela one knows the difference between those who live in the mountains, those who live in the plains, and those who live by the sea.

It's a shame that we have a system set up where only the PhDs and MDs get the recognition - and are granted the veracity.

I coach and consult in emotional intelligence (which includes common sense), and I often find in offices the quiet suggestions of the smaller players have been ignored and are quite valuable. Why should a lawyer listen to his secretary when she says they're getting milked by their web designer? No credentials. Why should the CEO listen to the accounting clerk who predicts the trend toward a product they could easily produce? Not his field. Why should the 'suits' in Miami listen to a coach who says that cruise passengers would attend lectures on self-help, astrology or engineering? Because everyone in Miami "knows" that all ALL cruise passengers want is to drink and gamble.. except for the coach who cruises a lot and listens to the actual guests - - wondering about the ships engines, the stars they see in the romantic night sky over the ocean, and, yes, Virginia they do not leave their problems at home when they cruise, they come right along with them, sometimes in person, sometimes in their thoughts and hearts.

The first thing I did when I was sent to a troubled apartment complex, back in my property management days, was to interview the people who actually worked on the property daily, so were forced to deal in real life with the problems at hand. The leasing agent, the maintenance man, even the mailman could tell me the simple truth, from their emotional intelligence, and observations, that told me what the problems AND THE SOLUTIONS were. They made me look good.

I had the credentials, but thank you Mildred Mannigan for greeting me at the door of Concord Square Apartments with, "If they would simply ____, this apt. complex would be full tomorrow. Will you please TELL someone." If you're the 'they' -- listen.

All sing the unsung hero. Wherever you are, Raul Busto, thank you.

Thank you for all the lives that will be saved because of you. And thanks to the "suit" that listened to Raul when he told what he knew.

Now go out and apply this! 
First decision: date and time.
Your best shot for getting lots of guests is to pick a not-prime time. Try something the Saturday before Valentine's Day, for instance, or Sunday, the day after. Also an off-time, such as brunch of lunch instead of cocktail or evening party. Check to make sure "key players" can come. Also a time when you'll have the week before to do the work.

Guest List
Write down whom you want to invite and take a count. This determines everything from cost to venue to refreshments.

Where will you have it?
Your home? A romantic outdoor patio restaurant? A restaurant with a fireplace and strolling violinist? The rec room at your apartment complex? If you're going to rent, call ahead and find out how many people they can accommodate, if the place is available that day, how much it will cost, what's included in the rental fee, and what other services are available. If you're renting a place, go there and talk to the catering decorator, walk around and take a tour. Questions will occur to you that might not otherwise:
* Can you bring your own food and drinks?
* What about decorating?
* Are there separate fees for room rental, security, maintenance, waiters, insurance, etc.?
How's the parking and public transportation. This can make a big difference in your guests desire to come, for instance on a rainy night.
What's the theme?
Well, Valentine's, but romantic? Light-hearted? Formal? Casual? Choose your theme and then plan your tableware, decorations, invitations, party favors, music.

Schedule of Party "Events"
* Plan a time for mingling, with drinks and hors d'oeuvres before a dinner - that's how people "warm up"
* If you're having honorary speeches or some such (20 minutes is plenty of time to allot for this), allow time afterwards, because the conversation will be primed
* Provide background music according to the tone of your event - rock band, romantic piano, harp, etc.

Now coordinate what you've decided on so far: time, place, theme and cost. Here are some adjustments you can make:

* Hard liquor, mixed drinks are expensive. If you're having lots of people, switch to beer and wine, or make an alcoholic punch.
* To cut costs, try something thematic like a bottle of Valentine wine, that is, from the Valentine Vineyards, in Southern Mendocino County (http://www.valentinevineyards.com/oh.html ) - The labels on the bottle are cool for a Valentine's Party!
You can buy party trays at Sam's or at Local Fancy Catering Boutique or you make them. Making them is probably going to cost more than Sam's, but it has it's virtues,
Caterers can be very pricey, but then there's no work for you to do.
Ordering a decorated cake is a good way to handle dessert for a crowd. It brings everyone around, is festive, and easy to manage.
Music can be live (more expensive) or your radio or CDs (no cost).
Will you want a maid? The day before to clean? The day of the party to serve and clean up? Both? (Be sure and check out her uniform. You could provide a cute Valentine's apron for her.)
Need a bartender? Also check on his uniform. You don't want any surprises.
Arrange for photography - stills, candids, videos, a professional photographer?
Decorations - floral arrangements are the most expensive, but they can sure dress up a table.
You can go to a party store and look around according to your theme, if you're going with paper goods.
If you have your own china, crystal, etc. start polishing them up.
If you want to purchase permanent tableware, visit a store like Tuesday Morning and see what they have. (Tip: Shop right after holidays, buy things on sale, and be ready for the next year.)

Elegant Doesn't Have to be More Expensive
People instinctively cut back when the goods are pricey, i.e., if you serve Beluga Prime from Caviarteria in New York (price $750/lb.), your guests won't be expecting to make a meal of it, and who can eat more than a dab of caviar anyway? If you're providing Krug Clos du Menil from Sherry-Lehmann in New York ($1,400 a case), no one's going to be chugalugging it. Tell them it's Kobe beef (up to $500/lb.) and they'll be too horrified to ask for seconds. Make Julia's Child classic chocolate cake, all of 1" high, and one small sliver suffices even the piggiest eater. It's richer even than a Starbuck's brownie. These things titillate your senses other than raw hunger and so are very satisfying in another sort of way. Have a classic piano in the background, and people naturally move into refined slow-motion.
However, if you've got bins of queso dip and tortilla chips, everyone will have that no-holds-barred approach to the buffet table. If JC and the Sunshine Band are cranking it out, well all impulses are on "go"!

Brunches are Quite Economical!
Call those pancakes crepes - no, really, it's a separate recipe and divine, serve a light fruit punch or Bloody Mary's, some bacon and sausage, a light salad. won't cost much at all. I recommend Julia Child's crepe recipe, and definitely the flaming orange crepes. They nearly put your tongue to sleep, and again, these things are so "rich," no one wants more than a taste. A little trick thrifty hostesses learn!

Entertainment
Live entertainment adds a really special note to a home party. Local talent is probably available that isn't expensive. Check with universities, colleges, high schools, and churches - the choral directors, the music or dance department. Check the yellow pages. There may be several children's dance groups, and they are always charming, because children can do no wrong, entertainment wise. Check the ballet and tap schools and see if you have a boys' choir.
Make decisions and book it. Also get a babysitter for the kids - or send them all over to your sister's with a sitter over there. Book your hair and nails. Send out the invitations. (Want to do something cute online? Try here: http://www.evite.com. Put all your "details" in a notebook. Start cleaning, cooking ahead, getting glasses out, freezing, and cleaning the farther corners of the house

The Little Touches
Now have some fun. Look on the Internet for things like Valentine's candles and Valentine's soap for your guest room, and a Valentine's wreath for your door, and maybe a heart-shaped doormat. These are little touches you CAN add, not things you MUST have.
If it's in your home, always have something hot to serve that's in the oven as the guests arrive and smells divine.
Tip: Always use candlelight if you can. It hides a multitude of "sins," i.e., dust bunnies and carpet stains, and sets a gentle ambience.
If you want a good turnout, do your PR work. Talk up the party with friends as you see them, or give them a call to see if they got their invitation. Drop a hint about the Clos du Menil, or the Big Band.
That should get you started. 
When I was a child, my Dad read me the story of "Heidi," by Johanna Spyri. I doubt there were many illustrations in the book, but the pictures in my own mind were vivid. Heidi was my age, I was sure, and lived with Grandfather in the Alps. There were goats. Then she had to go live in the city. She "pined" for Grandfather and grew sick and finally a doctor said it was because she missed Grandfather and the mountains, and she needed to back.

The best cover illustration of "Heidi" is this one:
http://www.geocitiesz.com/EnchantedForest/Glad/8905/home.html. It captures what Heidi was pining for.

We can miss and pine for people, places, things or ideas/beliefs.

PINING FOR HOMELAND

Rachmaninoff's music reflects his deep longing to return to his
homeland, Russia. Stravinsky also pined for his homeland and former circumstances, being so poor at one point, he agreed to compose music for Barnum and Bailey for the circus.

PINING FOR IDEAS

We can miss mountains and also mountains to climb. Ray Garrett, Jr.
reached the top of his law career, then went to serve as Chairman of the SEC, where he turned around the stock market it its biggest decline since the Depression, deregulating commissions in 1970. That having been accomplished, he resigned, went back to his hometown, and died about a year later.

"Pining" is an old word that isn't used much any more. It's too bad because we have lost the word that best defines that feeling when we lose something of great value, something which we suffer without. It comes from Old English "pinian" which is from the Latin "poena", punishment. It means to lose vigor, health or flesh (as through grief); to languish; to yearn intensely and persistently especially for something unattainable.

"Languish" is another old word. It means drooping or flagging from or as if from exhaustion; weak; heavy; lacking vigor or force.

Languid from an aching heart is not "as if", it is "because of." Grief brings a host of chemical and hormonal changes, that bring an exhaustion as real as the results of a 2 mile run, only without the good feelings. The slumped shoulders, the sunken eyes, the sighs all attest to the fact that the loss of something emotionally important is a physiological event for us humans.

PINING FOR PEOPLE

Doctors finally had to come up with a name to describe an ER scenario -
- an individual would come in with all the signs (and symptoms) of a heart attack, but some of the chemistry was different, they had no signs of prior heart disease, they recovered well usually with no harm done, and, it turned out, had just suffered the loss of someone they loved, or a shock of that sort.

Sometimes with a long-married couple, when one dies, the other follows shortly thereafter.

PINING FOR THINGS

We can feel a pang of grief over the loss of something like a car - if it is stolen for instance, but that's replaceable. We will feel it more strongly when it's something like our photographs. We also pine when we lose our wealth, because there are a lot of changes around that. The more you define yourself by what you have, the more you will suffer when you lose things.

One reason we take it so hard, and pine, is because a loss has a domino effect. When your husband has an affair and you divorce, you lose him, but many other things as well. Perhaps your house, some friends, maybe even your job and community if you must move.

PINING FOR "FOREVER AFTER"

When we are betrayed by our spouse, we lose something else very precious - our beliefs. What we thought the world and people are like, and our ideas of what might happen to us. We may come fact-to-face for the first time that bad things happen to good people (like us), that people don't keep their word or mean what they say, and that you can't count on what you thought you could. Betrayal is hard to deal with because it hits us in our core beliefs.

RESILIENCE

Being able to bounce back from loss, defeat, rejection and betrayal requires dealing with some of these issues. It may come down to, "Can I live in a world where - - where a wife cheats on her husband, where a trusted employee steals from you, where your beloved daughter marries against your will and, you fear, is going to trash her life... We realize there are some very important things we cannot control.

Resilience, an emotional intelligence competency, is about bouncing back - sooner or later - with enthusiasm and hope. It means learning the lesson, but not OVER-learning it. We do have losses, rejections and defeats; but not always and hopefully not too often. We do lose people we love; the pain we feel afterward is the price we pay for the love we enjoyed.

Resilience means bolstering yourself against the negative emotions so you can enjoy the positive ones. When we stuff down one emotion, we stuff them all down. You can stay safe, of course, not investing in anyone or anything, but what kind of life is that?

Part of Resilience is turning your face back to the sun and owning all the things you have to be grateful for. There are other skills, and it can be learned. Develop your emotional intelligence because it's like building muscle, muscle that you will need if you intend to have a long, full life.

Intentionality, BTW, is another emotional intelligence competency. 
Women who have lost partners to both death and divorce say divorce is harder. It is devastating to lose someone you love, but with death, you know it is permanent. There is no hope of getting the relationship back and there is nothing to figure out. In Greek and Roman mythology, Pluto (god of the underworld) was the only god to whom there was no altar, i.e., it is pointless to pray, to plead, or to bargain. There are also no answers to be given.

When someone you love breaks up with you in a sloppy manner, it's especially hard. We see this most in men who can't commit. They can't commit TO you, but they also can't commit to leaving you. The rough ride you had in the relationship, lurches on to the same sort of conclusion.

If your lover has low EQ, he may start to disengage, calling less, seeing you less often, or not being fully present when he is with you - just when the relationship should be moving toward commitment. Or he may simply disappear. Like an MIA, Missing in Action, you don't know if he's "alive" or "dead" so you are left in limbo, stuck, and unable to move on. To be the object of someone else's ambivalence is hell.

It is cruel for someone to put you on the spit of their own confusion and indecision. To sever the relationship, which is of course anyone's right, and it happens, they don't make a surgery of it, a clean cut; they saw away leaving a messy wound that can't heal and body pieces lying all over the place.

What keeps a man from making a respectful, well-thought out, Intentional and definitive exit? Low EQ, I'm afraid, and probably the spectre of Fatal Attraction and The Fisher King. If the relationship was new and still on a high, or he was playing a game and you were not, and he breaks it off, you have been lied to and betrayed, and also have had snatched from you one of the most pleasurable things in life - the love affair on the ascendant. His reason could be boredom or fear of commitment. If he anticipates you will be angry (FA), he is correct. If he feels guilty, and tries to assuage, he's right to feel guilty, but twice-damned to keep leading you on.

Note that if a mature man feels you are just not the one, there usually has been a slower pace, no promises that can't be kept, and it isn't a total surprise. If the reason is that he never intended any relationship in the first place, he will generally give reasons that criticize you, but make no sense.

If it was a long-term relationship, over many years, the breakup can bring depression, grief and dysfunction (FK). The abandoned party will be devastated. In a honest relationship, he cared enough about you at one time not to want to hurt you, but prolonging the agony by misplaced "kindness" is not the answer.

Once you've gotten the word, and get over the initial shock, there's a bargaining process that's torture. Your hope may remain alive indefinitely unless (1) you make him make it clear; (2) you fall in love with someone else; or (3) you end it ritually on your own.

Here's what the bargaining stage looks like:

1. Refusing to believe it. "He didn't mean it." "We've had fights before, he'll come back, he always does." "He'll come to his senses."

2. Trying to make sense of his version of reality, i.e., "He says I'm 'hysterical,' but he's the one who was always yelling," or "He says we never really got along. To me, it was the best 10 months of my life."

3. Trying to figure out what you can do to get him back and these are often desperate, and sometimes degrading measures, i.e., promising to "get along" with his selfish, drug-addicted daughter, promising to lose 30 lbs. One woman even got a breast augmentation which she paid for herself in order to try and win her guy back.

4. Asking friends for advice. They'll either talk from their own reality, attack your sense of judgment, or offer pity, none of which is helpful.

5. Changing a core belief or value, i.e., agreeing to let him have affairs.

Many men who fear "confrontation" (which makes them per se bad partners), will make YOU end it, especially painful as its against your wishes. They will send you an email to their new lover "by mistake," or arrange for you to catch them in bed with someone else, or provoke a scene that makes you "the bad guy."

If you are left in a state of ambivalence, when you get sick and tired of being sick and tired, then turn the tables. End it with a ritual, and then tell him next time he writes or calls that it is over and there is no hope.

This is far more high EQ than carving the "A" word on his car with your key, or turning him in for tax evasion. These are things that may feel good at the time, but that afterwards make you think less of yourself - for good reason. Then vent your pain and anger to a friend, coach, or your journal, not to him. Sadly, he doesn't care about your feelings, or he would still be around. It's a time to take care of yourself and keep your self-esteem intact by acting with high EQ; let what goes around come around and take care of him.

To ritualize your ending, collect everything he gave you, and every reminder of him - photos, jewelry, emails, phone messages, poems and letters. If there is something of monetary value, sell it or return it to him. The rest, get a big-enough fireproof container, take it out in the back yard and have a bonfire. Then remove his number from your cell phone, block his emails, don't answer his phone calls, and erase all his messages WITHOUT listening to them. If you're tempted to give in on any of these things, call your coach!

I can guarantee you that one day, if you keep those things, they will be meaningless, so you might as well get rid of them. You will, one fine day, be able to look at the photo of him and you in Hawaii and feel nothing. And his letters... if you're like one of my clients who had the misfortune of finding his love letter to his new girlfriend, and seeing the exact same words he had written to her - you will attach no value to those, either.

It's rough, kiddo, but the life you save will be your own. You will get to keep the good things from the relationship and he can become another woman's problem, while you can go on to find a man who loves and values you and wants a relationship with you. A sloppy, uncaring quasi-ending is indicative of the man's overall style, and one day you will be grateful that if he couldn't end it, even though you didn't want to, you could, and did. 
The magnificent painting, "Burlaks on the Volga River", is now in the public domain. Most of us have heard the Russian folk song, "The Volga Boatmen," and welcome a look at what the song is about. The song is often sung like a dirge, and you will see why when you look at this painting by Repin: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Image:Burlaks_on_volga_by_repin.jpg.

Now, to refresh your memory, you can click here http://www.youtube.com/v/WufB-eeSPB4 to hear the song sung, in an old Nelson Eddy movie. The lyrics to the refrain are:

Mighty stream so deep and wide
Volga Volga you're our pride
Heave ho, heave ho

Now, you can do this exercise I use in my Emotional Intelligence training, and in courses and seminars. In this painting, we see a team at work, doing manual labor. You can probably identify some of the people in the painting. Who is the young golden boy? The one at the rear who seems about to collapse? The leader in the front, old, but apparently doing fine? Which one is you?

Now, on a blog entitled "Volga Boatman," a member of the clergy writes:

"Thinking about liturgical music, the Volga boatmen came to mind. Somewhere in the dim recesses of my mind is an image of men on a towpath, dragging a boat through a canal, accompanied by 'Yo, heave, ho.' And there are times when I feel like one of the guys on the rope line. Dragging the congregation through a Mass, dragging a choir through a new hymn or setting. But those are nothing compared to the way it's going to feel when we try to move forward from what many refer to as 'the four-hymn Mass' to 'ritual music.'

"Anyone who works in the church music world knows that after almost every Mass, someone comes up and tells you that she loves the music because it's strong/tender/enlivening/comforting/'real Catholic music'/up-to-date, etc.

That individual is followed by someone who hates it. It's too loud/soft/fast/slow/traditional/modern/hard-to-sing,etc.

[I used to be the Outreach Director for a church and greeted people as they came in the sanctuary. I would hear, "It's too hot in here/just right in here for once/freezing cold in here." Everyone should have this experience in order to understand what "leadership" is all about.]

However, that's not my point here. I have a few questions for you, actually.

1. Do you find it odd the clergyman didn't see himself as the man on the boat in the orange shirt? 2. Would there be anything 'wrong' if the leader were on the boat, not hauling?
3. What about if he were pitching in? He appears to see himself perhaps as the man in the front right. Dragging them forward.
4. If you were the man in the orange shirt directing this whole thing, would you feel guilty?
5. Did you even see the man on the boat in the orange shirt?

It's about the big picture:
--Not letting your emotions get in the way of your perceptions,
--About what you 'read into' a painting. We all do this. That's why there are paintings, and why we love them. (The great arts [culture] BTW, are an important component of emotional intelligence).
--The experiences you have had, and the emotions around them that you bring to apainting become your reality.
--Your beliefs and attitudes about labor, i.e., all work is slave labor and you are condemned to do it... or think-work is lazy, manual labor is "honest labor"
--How much you identify with the people in a painting and why
--How much you know about Czarist Russian and if you can distance yourself to get intellectual; or, conversely, if you automatically intellectualize your emotions
--Your attitudes toward paintings - worthless nonsense, "not for me," "what's the purpose? - why are you 'making' me look at a painting?"

Some people identify with the Volga boatmen, and immediately start talking about "slave labor." Others identify with the suffering in general (especially if they are familiar with this time period in Russia's history) and they usually fail to see the men on the boat, or to remember them. Some who are leaders see themselves as the man in the orange shirt, while others who are leaders see themselves as the man front left. Others might start fantasizing about never having to work.

There are many reactions you can have.

One suggestion for the New Year, if you see yourself on your current job as one of the Volga boatmen - slave labor, and heave ho, heave ho - it may be time for a new job? 
Dear EQ Coach:

My husband and I have been together for 10 years. We have 4 kids, his and mine. I love his youngest one like she were mine, but the oldest one I just can't stand. He's favored her in the past, which irks me, and she'll always doing things that get on my nerves. She excludes me in a sneaky way. She arranged her wedding shower so I couldn't come, and whenever I offer to take care of her baby, she finds some excuse. It puts an unpleasant atmosphere when we get-together. Usually I have everyone over for Christmas Eve, but I'm really having trouble this year. It breaks my husband's heart that we don't get along and he tells me just to get over it, but I don't know how.

How am I going to get through this dinner, and the next one, and the next one. I'm desperate. This woman is ruining my holidays.

Desperate Step-Mother

Dear Desperate Step-Mother,

Being Step-Parenting Expert for a major website, the letters start flooding in right after Thanksgiving. It's so predictable, I created an Internet course on how to handle difficult people, focusing on family and step-family issues. You love them, now learn how to get along with them is the theme. Nothing is worse than these family squabbles. If there is one thing that is predictable in the mental health field, it's that psychologists' offices will fill up in December.

What a pity.

I'll grant you that step-parenting and family-blending is hard work, but when you think about it, you don't get to choose your own kids, or your own parents, or your own siblings, so my advice is pretty general. There may be issues about the "step" but if it isn't that, it will be something else.

Accidents also escalate this time of the year. We're stressed with extra work to do. Preoccupied with these thoughts about how to get along with these people and still have a decent Christmas, Hanukkah or whatever. Our emotions cloud our thinking so we become more careless, both physically and emotionally. In fact the people who can't admit to themselves that they're stressed or upset are the most likely to have an accident, because that's the only way their Inner Wisdom can deal with it.

So getting conscious is the first step.

COMPONENTS OF EMOTIONAL INTELLIGENCE

Then I would advise you take a course that teaches you the components of emotional intelligence. It demystifies the whole thing - why the tension, how to say things that keep you safe and don't escalate, how to let go, how to disarm the aggressive, and how to cope. Do it now and get prepared for the Christmas get-together. Family patterns are deeply entrenched and intensely emotional. They don't change overnight and if you keep taking the bait, they'll keep baiting the hook. You also need to see when your actions or reactions make YOU the "difficult person" and learn to do something different. When you change, your life changes.

TAKE CARE OF YOURSELF

You live in a body, and your body (brain) generates emotions. Too much sugar and alcohol? You're set up to spin out. It's SAD (seasonal affective disorder) season, so depression-like lethargy contributes. You're either hyper, or would like to hibernate. Keep our routine, eat right, get your sleep and exercise. Take an immune system supplement, because "5 minutes of anger suppresses your immune system for up to 6 hours," and "mad" isn't the only emotion that does that, or that you're going to be feeling - more intensely than usual.

With a healthy body, you're more able to adjust your attitude, and that's the next step. It's an emotional time of year for everyone, and people aren't at their best. People who are vulnerable to begin with, really take a dive. Any issue that's been percolating is likely to boil over, unless you are aware. Emotional intelligence starts with self-awareness. Know yourself, and what sets you off. Then avoid it.

LOWER YOUR EXPECTATIONS

Neutral expectations are best. If you are fantasizing about a perfect family get-together, you are setting yourself up for depression. It's the law of emotions - what goes up, must come down. If you demand perfection or that things go your way or you won't be happy, you put an energy out that almost guarantees the opposite of what you want.

ADMIT HOW YOU FEEL, TO YOURSELF.

You don't need to share this with people involved; vent with a coach or someone objective. I don't know about other coaches, but I plan my own Christmas way ahead to block off coaching time in December and January. (After-Christmas blues is about as bad.) Admit you don't like this woman and she gets on your nerves. If you fight it, you give it energy. Admit at the same time though, that how you handle this is a choice. You can let the fact that you have to be with someone you don't like ruin your get-together, or you can accept that you'd rather it were otherwise, but it isn't, so you're going to find a way to enjoy yourself, or just get through it and not add your misery, temper, volatility, etc. to the mix. I'm sure your husband would appreciate if you acted like everything was fine. You may not be able to "get over it" inside, but if you act like you have, you'd be surprised what will happen. A coach can give you specific tips on what to say and not say, how to answer, how to defuse, and how to stay out of trouble. When you see how you are contributing to the situation, and what you can do differently, you'll be relieved. That's what most people tell me who learn how to handle themselves in situations like this. "I was relieved. It was like a boulder was lifted off my shoulders."

The thing is, nobody every taught us this stuff.

BE FLEXIBLE, CHANGE, and CREATE

Lastly, here's a novel idea. Flexiblity and creativity are two of the components of emotional intelligence. It's nice to have traditions; they make us feel secure, and frame our lives with memories. However, they can become a prison. I'm thinking of my friend who is terribly upset right now because she can't make fruitcake this year. I won't go in to why, but in her reality, this is a major trauma. As an observer, I just can't get in to it. I have never made fruitcake, and I have survived many years. It may be that you're holding on to something like that.

If it's really awful, just say no. Go on a cruise with your husband over Christmas. Yes, the world would still turn. If that's too radical, start with something smaller, but understand that you can change a tradition at any time. When they're changed for us, with the death of a parent, for instance, we manage to create something new. It's more pleasant when you control the change.

Learning to let go, managing your emotions and those of others, handling difficult people and stressful times, and managing change are part of emotional intelligence, one of the best things you can put under the Christmas tree. 
I love Mr. Mafioso on AskMen. "Look, college boy," he writes, "there are certain lessons that all the books in the world couldn't teach you."

Strikes a chord with me. I came out of college quite the college girl. It was a college in rural Minnesota, very academic, very intellectual. How academic? How intellectual? More students pass the MedCATS from this school than any in the nation, or did at last count. It produces doctors and lawyers, but not necessarily rich ones; more typically labor lawyers and inner- city clinic doctors, or med and law-school professors.

I think it attracts more than its share of NFs - Idealists (only 8-10% of the population). Whatever job the Idealist has, it's a mean to an end: saving the world. This is the college boy Mr. M. is talking about, and the college girl who has to learn to put on her Big Girl Panties, because one can never save the world, but one can lose one's job.

When I left that ivory tower and landed my first job, they saw me coming. Determined to be honest, brave and true (and believing that others were), I got all the extra work, my "job description" expanding to match the infinite boundaries of my naivete; I got the worst equipment; I interviewed students in a closet; and of course I was ostracized just for good measure. Eating lunch alone, I read a copy of "How to Survive in the Real World." J.K.

What I did was get street smart. You know how someone in the office is doing better than they ought to considering their education, and you can't figure out why. Then you notice - she's got street smarts... she always lands on her feet, she knows the score, she reads between the lines, she gets out when the getting's good, she can smell a rat, she knows a good thing when she sees it?

It's Emotional Intelligence; what Mr. Mafioso talks about in "Street Lessons."

He begins with the litany that all idealistic intellectuals can't accept: "The world isn't fair. It isn't nice. Nobody cares if you get stiffed, if your feelings get bruised or how hungry you are." We're all in the same boat, he alerts us, and it's a rough ride. "Everybody's trying to get a piece of the action, trying to survive. And the street is equally cruel to everyone."

I had to experience this many times before I was willing to let go of how I thought the world should be, or wished it were. Eventually I quit telling my co-workers that I really didn't know what I was doing, etc. after getting shot enough times with a gun I had loaded and handed to someone.

Mr. Mafioso then tells us the thing we least want to hear - that it's out-of-control: You can be on top one day, wondering what the big deal is, then get bagged. "By any of a number of things: family, work, health, divorce, tainted spinach--"

His rules?

1. Keep your guard up. This gels with EQ's "trust radius?" A component of Emotional Intelligence is "trust until proven otherwise." It's not seeing the "otherwise" that gets us in trouble.

2. Stay out of arguments. Wait, he says, until they've worn each other out, and you can see who the winner's going to be. As I put it in my How to Handle Difficult People course, only "fools rush in where angels fear to tread." That quote was from a book I'd read in college. Once I got it aligned with reality, I was fine. Before that, typically I rushed in because I thought I could not BE a fool; I had a college degree.

3. Meet only when necessary. Mr. Mafioso thinks only girls enjoy meeting just to talk; that Real Men meet only to make a decision. Everyone knows that... except your boss, right? The one with the M. B. A. from Harvard.

4. Know people. But, he adds, that doesn't mean they need to know YOU. Having friends means connections, opportunities, and information, all good things; but don't disclose anything superfluous.

5. Don't be too proud to retreat. The next sentence is one that hangs up the Idealists, and is often difficult to dispel. Sometimes it's the single goal of my coaching, to get them to quit fighting on principle. If you can't win, he says, give up, back down, go into witness protection (ha ha); having a strategy beats bravery. I think he means "bravado." And "discretion is the better part of valor." Sometimes a college education IS an advantage.

Mr. Mafioso ends that it's back on the bricks for him, "learning everything the hard way and hoping my kid doesn't have to do the same. There's no cure for this thing called life, so it's best to learn certain things early on. Nothing can truly prepare you for it, but if you keep your head on a swivel, you'll suffer fewer 'unfair' surprises."

KEY POINTS here about the kid. When teaching your child emotional intelligence:

1. You're teaching it whether you want to or not, so get conscious and teach GOOD Emotional Intelligence, not BAD Emotional Intelligence.
2. You are never through learning Emotional Intelligence. Get coaching.
3. Let them learn their lessons, don't rescue them unless the house is on fire.
4. Better yet, set up the lessons so they can learn them while they're still under your protection.
5. Connect the dots for them about what you're teaching.

Don't forget to do this; it's the part most parents leave out. Like most of us ask our kids, "How would you feel if Bobby did that to you?" and "How do you think Bobby feels now that you spit on him?" But we fail to tell them we are teaching Empathy - understanding that you have feelings and so does everyone else. Labeling helps to de-mystify the things that mystify us most in life - emotional things.

Tell them you are going to teach them stewardship, give them 3 months allowance at one time, tell them it has to last, and then be there when they spend it all at once and have nothing left. Connect the dots for them, giving it language. It's easier to learn this when you have a net.

Now, back to my NF client that I'm coaching in Emotional Intelligence.

"I can't do that," she says, "it's against my principles." She is preparing to self-sabotage...again.

"Look, college girl," I tell her. "Just put on your Big Girl Panties," aka stress tolerance, creativity, flexibility, resilience, interpersonal skills and the other components of Emotional Intelligence.

It keeps your head on a swivel. 