WATER
Because of its scarcity, water plays a central role in Middle Eastern politics and society.
Nowhere in the world is water more important than in the Middle East and North Africa. In no other region do so many people strive so hard for economic growth on the basis of so little water: here is found 5 percent of the world's population but only 1 percent of its fresh water. Of the ten nations with the least water per capita, six are in this region. No wonder that both Jewish and Muslim scriptures are full of references to water.
Role of Climate
The more heavily populated parts of the Middle East are semiarid, with rainfall of 10 to 29 inches (250 to 750 mm) per year. However, low rainfall is less of a problem than variability in rainfall. The great bulk of the rain falls in four winter months, with none falling during the rest of the year. Rainfall also changes rapidly with distance, from more than 20 inches (500 mm) on the coast of Lebanon to 8 inches (200 mm) in the Biqa, only an hour away by road but across the Lebanon mountains.
Seasonal and spatial variations in rainfall are sharp but predictable. What makes planning difficult is the sharp variation from one year to the next. Reliable flow in the rivers (the flow that can be expected nine years out of ten) is only 10 percent of the average. In northern latitudes, water planning can be built around statistical averages; here, it must be built around extremes.
This already difficult water situation will likely get worse. Population growth rates are high, and most climate change models suggest higher temperatures, lower rainfall, and more frequent droughts for the region.
Role of History
Development in the Middle East and North Africa has always been more dependent on water than on any other resource, including oil. By the fourth millennium b.c.e., the Sumerians had built a paradise in what is now Iraq through intricate canals for irrigating crops; two millennia later it had largely collapsed because of salinization of the soil. Ancient cities, such as Palmyra in Syria, were possible only because of carefully engineered tunnels, called qanats (foggaras in Iran), to bring water from springs tens of kilometers away.
Over the years, the peoples of the Middle East have made water a preoccupation, and each nation has a central agency, typically a full ministry, to deal with water. Many of the principles for good water management were worked out in the Middle East—although just as often they were ignored for political, financial, or social reasons.
Water Sources
The Middle East includes two of the mightiest river systems in the world. The Nile has two main branches: The White Nile originates in Uganda, and the larger Blue Nile (together with the Atbara) originates in Ethiopia; they join near Khartoum and flow northward through Egypt to the Mediterranean. The Tigris and Euphrates both originate in Turkey and flow south-southeastward through Syria and Iraq before joining and flowing into the Persian Gulf via the Shatt al-Arab, at the Iranian border.
The region also includes numerous mediumsized rivers, such as the Jordan, which flows from three springs through the Sea of Galilee (one of the few natural lakes in the region) and into the Dead Sea, 415 meters below sea level. Only Turkey has an 
abundance of river water, but its big rivers are only found in the eastern part of the nation. Finally, there are small coastal rivers (many of them ephemeral), and a few major wetlands, such as the marshlands in southern Iraq and the Sudd swamp in southern Sudan.
The construction of new dams and pipelines to deliver water from major rivers in the Middle East will cost two or three times as much per unit of water as current supplies, and if construction occurs in upstream countries, such as Ethiopia and Turkey, it will reduce flows downstream. Therefore, the region will increasingly shift toward the use of underground water, which has the great advantage of not evaporating. (Lakes and reservoirs in the region lose meters of water per year to evaporation.)
Historically, underground water was tapped by shallow wells dug in unconsolidated materials to get small flows of water. Today, much larger volumes of water are extracted from wells drilled tens to hundreds of meters into aquifers, which are rock layers with pores that contain water. Renewable aquifers are replenished (generally slowly) by rainfall; non-renewable, or fossil, aquifers contain water trapped in sediments laid down millions of years ago.
Just more than 10 percent of the water supply for the region comes from aquifers, but in Israel and Jordan the share approaches 50 percent, and in Kuwait and parts of the Arabian Peninsula it approaches 100 percent (apart from desalination). Libya's Great Man-Made River pumps water from fossil aquifers in the south of the country and moves it 930 miles (1,500 km) to farms and cities in the north.
The third most important source of water in the Middle East is recycled sewage, which is treated and reused, mainly for irrigation. Despite common 
belief (shared by both Muslims and non-Muslims), there is no objection in Islamic law to the reuse of sewer water provided it is properly treated.
More than half of the world's desalination capacity is found in the region, mainly in the oil-producing nations of the Arabian peninsula with lots of by-product natural gas that was formerly flared. (Desalination is an energy-intensive process.) Costs for desalination have fallen to a level that makes it feasible as a source of potable water but still too expensive for irrigation.
Other sources of water are individually small but collectively provide sizable amounts of water. Water harvesting gathers rain that falls over a wide area and directs it to one field through small channels and micro-barrages. The technique can allow crops in areas where rainfall is only 4 inches (100 mm) per year. Rainwater is also collected from rooftops and stored in cisterns. If handled carefully, rooftop water can be used for drinking.
Uses of Water
By far the largest share of water in the region goes to agriculture—as much as 90 percent of total water use in some countries, and 60 percent in the more industrialized countries. 
Drinking requires only a relatively small volume of water, but it must meet higher standards than that used for irrigation. Thirty liters of potable water per person-day is generally regarded as the minimum for drinking, cooking, and washing. 
Industrial water use is low. Food and beverage processing are the largest industrial consumers. More is withdrawn for cooling but most of this water is recycled or returned to the watercourse. 
A hidden but critical amount of water must be left in place to support fisheries and hydropower, as well as to protect habitat. This use is typically neglected by governments when they drain swamps, canalize rivers, or extend land. As a result, not only has the environment been degraded, but fish catches have declined and the salinity of groundwater has increased.
Problems 
The nations of the Middle East all face three overlapping sources of stress in their water management: 1) quantity, which has been a source of stress since history began; 2) quality, which is a newer stress but increasingly important; and 3) equity, which occurs when the same water is subject to competing demands.
Quantity. Iran, Iraq, Lebanon, Sudan, Syria, and Turkey are fairly well endowed with water, with more than 1 million cubic meters (Mcm) per capita; Algeria, Egypt, Israel, Morocco, and Palestine form a middle group; and Jordan, Libya, Tunisia, and the countries of the Arabian Peninsula are least well endowed, with less than 500 Mcm per capita. However, water availability is declining in every nation, which means that current patterns of water use are not sustainable. Some projections for the Jordan River basin suggest that by 2025 household and industrial uses will require all the fresh water, leaving none for farmers. Most nations are also drawing down their renewable aquifers and mining fossil ones. Some have annual water deficits of several thousand Mcm.
Water quantity problems in the region can be resolved in small part by exploiting additional freshwater withdrawals by country and sector estimates for 2000.
People in the region use less water than those elsewhere in the world, but as a result of poor management and misguided economic policies conservation here (as in most other parts of the world) remains far short of its potential. Many nations lose half the water put into municipal systems to leaks, and they typically deliver piped water at low (or no) price. Cost-effective savings of 25 to 50 percent are possible in most uses. 
Moreover, every country in the region provides water to farmers at highly subsidized prices. Under the influence of higher prices, Israeli scientists developed drip irrigation systems that have cut water use per hectare by 40 percent. However, drip irrigation is expensive and not appropriate for all crops. Lower-cost sprinkler systems, used at night to minimize evaporation, can also increase irrigation efficiency, as can irrigating only at times critical to plant growth.
Most analysts find that water is tens of times more valuable in industrial or household uses than in agriculture. Therefore, crops grown in the region will gradually be replaced by imports. It takes roughly a thousand tons of water to produce one ton of wheat. Using that ratio, Middle Eastern nations already import grains with a virtual water content equal to the flow of the Nile.
Quality. Much of the limited fresh water in the Middle East is polluted from growing volumes of human, industrial, and agricultural waste. Three problems stand out: 1) Overpumping of wells causes a decline in the water table—by as much as a meter a year in some areas. This decline adds to pumping costs and permits lower-quality water (or, if near the coast, seawater) to flow inward and contaminate the aquifer. The only way to avoid the problem is to match pumping rates to inflow. 2) Agricultural runoff is the major non-point source of water pollution—mainly sediment, phosphorus, nitrogen, and pesticides. Better farming methods, such as conservation tillage, contour planting, and terracing can control soil erosion and cut pollution by half or more. 3) Urban sewage systems have either begun to deteriorate or cannot handle the growing loads placed on them. Large investments are needed to improve their physical infrastructure.Equity. Most of the larger rivers in the region cross an international border—some cross several borders—or form a border. No tabulation exists for aquifers that underlie national borders, but there are many.
Despite many statements suggesting that the next war in the Middle East will be over fresh water, there is little evidence for this. Not a single war has been fought over water for hundreds of years, but many treaties dealing with water have been signed. Water will be a source of conflict, but the conflicts will mainly be intranational rather than international. Likely sources of conflict include rural and urban users contending for the same water and rising demands from poor farmers, who are often disadvantaged in their access to water, and from women, who typically want more water for their households while men prefer to use it to grow cash crops. Israeli control of water in the West Bank is contentious, but even here experts have shown that compromise is feasible. 
None of the three stresses on water in the Middle East will be easily resolved. Most of the nations in the region have already reached or are fast approaching the limits of their indigenous water supplies. Although higher prices for water and technological advances may defer the crisis, the only long-term solutions involve much greater efficiency in use, full reuse of wastewater, and gradual shifts of water from agriculture to other sectors. All of the nations of the Middle East and North Africa must revise their water policies to provide for a sustainable future, and they must find equitable ways to share water within and between nations.
WATER ISSUES 
Water is precious for many reasons. It is an essential resource for sustaining human, animal, and vegetable life. Agriculture is absolutely dependent on water to produce food crops and livestock. Water is crucial to tourism, navigation, and industry. Enormous amounts are used to generate power, mine materials, and produce goods. Water is an ingredient, a medium, and a means of conveyance or cooling in most industrial processes. Water supplies a vital habitat for many of Earth's creatures, from the whale to the tadpole. There are entire ecosystems that are water-based. 
All these competing uses put an enormous strain on Earth's water supply. Overall, the amount of water on Earth remains constant, simply passing from one stage to another in a circular pattern known as the hydrologic cycle. Water in the atmosphere condenses and falls to Earth as precipitation, such as rain, sleet, or snow. Precipitation seeps into the ground, saturating the soil and refilling underground aquifers; it is drawn from the soil by vegetation for growth and returned into the air by plant leaves through the process of transpiration; and some precipitation flows into surface waters such as rivers, streams, lakes, wetlands, and oceans. Moisture evaporates from surface water back into the atmosphere to repeat the cycle. 
Humans have interrupted the cycle to accommodate the many water demands of modern life. Flowing rivers and streams are dammed up. Groundwater and surface water are pumped from their sources to other places. Water is either consumed or discharged back to the environment, usually not in the same condition. Water quality becomes increasingly important. There are two primary issues when it comes to water: availability and suitability. 
WATER AVAILABILITY 
Even though water covers nearly three-fourths of the planet, the vast majority of it is too salty to drink or nourish crops and too corrosive for many industrial processes. In general, saline water is defined as water that contains at least one thousand milligrams of salt per liter of water. No cheap and effective method for desalinating large amounts of ocean water has been discovered. This makes freshwater an extremely valuable commodity. Even though the overall water supply on Earth is enormous, freshwater is not often in the right place at the right time in the right amount to serve all the competing needs. 
Overall Water Use in 2000 
For reporting purposes, water use in the United States is classified as in-stream or off-stream. In-stream use means the water is used at its source, usually a river or stream, for example, for the production of hydroelectric power at a dam. Off-stream use means the water is conveyed away from its source, although it may be returned later. 
WATER SUITABILITY 
Water is a fundamental need in every society. Families use water for drinking, cooking, and cleaning. Industry needs it to make chemicals, prepare paper, and clean factories and equipment. Cities use water to fight fires, clean streets, and fill public swimming pools. Farmers water their livestock, clean barns, and irrigate crops. Hydroelectric power stations use water to drive generators, whereas thermonuclear power stations need it for cooling. Water quality is important to all users, as differing levels of quality are required for different uses. Even though some industrial users can tolerate water containing high levels of contaminants, drinking water requirements are extremely strict. 
Clean Water Act 
On June 22, 1969, the Cuyahoga River in Cleveland, Ohio, burst into flames, the result of oil and debris that had accumulated on the river's surface. This episode thrust the problem of water pollution into the public consciousness. Many people became aware—and wary—of the nation's polluted waters, and in 1972 Congress passed the Federal Water Pollution Control Act, commonly known as the Clean Water Act. 
The objective of the Clean Water Act was to "restore and maintain the chemical, physical, and biological integrity of the nation's waters." It called for ending the discharge of all pollutants into the navigable waters of the United States to achieve "wherever attainable, an interim goal of water quality which provides for the protection and propagation of fish, shellfish, and wildlife and provides for recreation in and on the water." 
Section 305(b) of the Clean Water Act requires states to assess the condition of their waters and report the extent to which the waters support the basic goals of the Clean Water Act and state water quality standards. Water quality standards are designed to protect designated uses (such as recreation, protection and propagation of aquatic life, fish consumption, and drinking water supply) by setting criteria (e.g., chemical-specific limits on discharges) and preventing any waters that do meet standards from deteriorating from their current condition. 
Each state reports to the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) data indicating:
The water quality of all navigable waters in the state
The extent to which the waters provide for the protection and propagation of marine animals and allow recreation in and on the water
The extent to which pollution has been eliminated or is under control
The sources and causes of the pollution 
The act stipulates that the states must submit this information to the EPA on a biennial basis (every two years). Under Section 303(d) of the Clean Water Act, states are required to submit to the EPA a separate list of waters considered impaired and requiring pollution controls.
International Convention for the Prevention of Pollution from Ships 
Established in 1973, the International Convention for the Prevention of Pollution from Ships regulates many materials that are dumped at sea. The international treaty has been in effect in the United States only since its ratification in 1998. Even though eighty-three countries have ratified the treaty, they have not necessarily complied, as evidenced by the current level of marine debris.
Ocean Dumping Act 
Congress enacted the Marine Protection, Research, and Sanctuaries Act in 1972 to regulate intentional ocean disposal of materials and to authorize research. Title 1 of the act, known as the Ocean Dumping Act, contains permit and enforcement provisions for ocean dumping. Four federal agencies have authority under the act: the EPA, the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, and the U.S. Coast Guard. Title 1 prohibits all ocean dumping, except that allowed by permits, in any ocean waters under U.S. jurisdiction by any U.S. vessel or by any vessel sailing from a U.S. port. The act bans dumping of radiological, chemical, and biological warfare agents, high-level radioactive waste, and medical wastes. In 1997 Congress amended the act to ban dumping of municipal sewage sludge and industrial waste. 
Oil Pollution Act 
In 1989 the oil freighter Exxon Valdez ran into a reef in Prince William Sound, Alaska, spilling more than eleven million gallons of oil into one of the richest and most ecologically pristine areas in North America. An oil slick the size of Rhode Island killed wildlife and marine species. A $5 billion damage penalty was levied against Exxon, whose ship captain was found to be at fault in the wreck. 
In response to the Valdez oil spill, Congress passed the Oil Pollution Act of 1990, which went into effect in 1993. The law requires companies involved in storing and transporting petroleum to have standby plans for cleaning up oil spills on land or in water. Under the act a company that does not adequately take care of a spill is vulnerable to almost unlimited litigation and expense. The law makes the Coast Guard responsible for approving clean-up plans and procedures for coastal and seaport oil spills, whereas the EPA oversees clean-ups on land and in inland waterways. The law also requires that oil tankers be built with double hulls to better secure the oil in the event of a hull breach. 
DRINKING WATER 
Drinking Water Legislation 
Almost any legislation concerning water affects drinking water, either directly or indirectly. The following pieces of legislation are aimed specifically at providing safe drinking water for the nation's residents. 
The Safe Drinking Water Act (SDWA) of 1974 mandated that the EPA establish and enforce minimum national drinking water standards for all public water systems—community and noncommunity—in the United States. The law also required the EPA to develop guidelines for water treatment and to set testing, monitoring, and reporting requirements.To address pollution of surface water supplies to public systems, the EPA established a permit system requiring any facility that discharges contaminants directly into surface waters (lakes and rivers) to apply for a permit to discharge a set amount of materials—and that amount only. It also created groundwater regulations to govern underground injection of wastes.Congress intended that, after the EPA had set regulatory standards, each state or U.S. territory would run its own drinking water program. The EPA established the Primary Drinking Water Standards by setting maximum contaminant levels (MCLs) for contaminants known to be detrimental to human health. All public water systems in the United States are required to meet primary standards. Secondary standards cover nonhealth-threatening aspects of drinking water, such as odor, taste, staining properties, and color. Secondary standards are recommended but not required. 
1986 amendments to the sdwa
1986 amendments to the sdwa. The 1986 amendments to the SDWA required that the EPA set maximum containment levels for an additional fifty-three contaminants by June 1989, twenty-five more by 1991, and twenty-five every three years thereafter. The amendments also required the EPA to issue a maximum contaminant level goal (MCLG) along with each MCL. An MCLG is a health goal equal to the maximum level of a pollutant not expected to cause any health problems over a lifetime of exposure. The EPA is mandated by law to set MCLs as close to MCLGs as technology and economics will permit. 
The 1986 amendments banned the use of lead pipe and lead solder in new public drinking water systems and in the repair of existing systems. In addition, the EPA had to specify criteria for the filtration of surface water supplies and to set standards for the disinfection of all surface and groundwater supplies. The EPA was required to take enforcement action, including filing civil suits against violators of drinking water standards, even in states granted primacy if those states did not adequately enforce regulations. Violators became subject to fines up to $25,000 daily until violations were corrected.
water quality control act of 1987 
water quality control act of 1987. Section 304 (1) of the revised Clean Water Act of 1987 determines the state of the nation's water quality and reviews the effectiveness of the EPA's regulatory programs designed to protect and improve that water quality. Section 308—known as the Water Quality Control Act—requires that the administrator of the EPA report annually to Congress on the effectiveness of the water quality improvement program. 
The main purpose of the Water Quality Control Act is to identify water sources that need to be brought up to minimum standards and to establish more stringent controls where needed. States are now required to develop lists of contaminated waters as well as lists of the sources and amounts of pollutants causing toxic problems. In addition, each state is required to develop "individual control strategies" for dealing with these pollutants. 
lead contamination control act of 1988
lead contamination control act of 1988. The Lead Contamination Control Act of 1988 strengthened the controls on lead contamination set out in the 1986 amendments to the SDWA. It requires the EPA to provide guidance to states and localities in testing for and remedying lead contamination in drinking water in schools and day care centers. The act also contains requirements for the testing, recall, repair, and/or replacement of water coolers that have lead-lined storage tanks or parts containing lead. It attaches civil and criminal penalties to the manufacture and sale of water coolers containing lead. 
The ban on lead states that plumbing must be lead-free. In addition, each public water system must identify and notify anyone whose drinking water may be contaminated with lead, and the states must enforce the lead ban through plumbing codes and the public-notice requirement. The federal government gave the EPA the power to enforce the lead ban law by authorizing the agency to withhold up to 5% of federal grant funds to any state that does not comply with the new rulings. 
reinventing drinking water law—1996 amendments to the sdwa 
reinventing drinking water law—1996 amendments to the sdwa. In 1996 Congress passed a number of significant amendments to the SDWA. The law changed the relationship between the federal government and the states in administering drinking water programs, giving states greater flexibility and more responsibility. 
The centerpiece of the law is the State Revolving Fund (SRF), a mechanism for providing low-cost financial aid to local water systems to build the treatment plants necessary to meet state and federal drinking water standards. The law also requires states to train and certify operators of drinking water systems. If they do not, states risk losing up to 20% of their federal grants. The law requires states to approve the operation of any new water supply system, making sure it complies with the technical, managerial, and financial requirements. The 1996 SDWA gives the EPA discretion in regulating only those contaminants that may be harmful to health, and it requires the EPA to select at least five contaminants every five years for consideration for new standards. A further change is that the EPA, when proposing a regulation, must now determine—and publish—whether or not the benefits of a new standard justify the costs. 
Furthermore, the law affirms Americans' right to know the quality of their drinking water and mandates notification. Water suppliers must promptly (within twenty-four hours) alert consumers if water becomes contaminated by something that can cause illness and must advise as to what precautions can be taken. In 1998 states began to compile information about individual systems, which the EPA now summarizes in an annual compliance report. As of October 1999 water systems have been required to make that data available to the public. Large suppliers have to mail their annual safety reports to customers, whereas smaller systems can post the reports in a central location or publish them in local newspapers. 
Sources of Drinking Water—Public and Private Supply 
According to the EPA, there were 156,675 public water supply systems in operation in fiscal year 2006, serving 301.7 million people. (See Table 9.4.) These included systems that served homes, businesses, schools, hospitals, and recreational parks. Those who did not get their water from a public system were for the most part in rural areas and got their water from private wells. Even though most systems obtain their water from ground-water, most people receive drinking water from surface water sources. This is because a relatively small number of public systems using surface water sources serve large metropolitan areas
Safety of Water
The understanding that some water caused disease while other water sources did not has long prompted human civilizations to attempt to make water safe to drink. Sanskrit medical lore from around 2000 B.C.E. mentions boiling foul water, exposing it to sunlight, and filtering through charcoal. It is possible that the Asian custom of drinking tea made with boiling water was an early method to make water safe to drink. Cyrus the Great in the sixth century B.C.E. took vessels of boiled water with his troops when they traveled to do battle. Residents of Alexandria, Egypt in 50 B.C.E. drank Nile River water brought to the city through a series of underground aqueducts to cisterns where it was clarified by sedimentation. Other parts of the Egyptian empire used single, double, and even triple filtration to purify water. Sextus Julius Frontinus, water commissioner of Rome in 97 C.E., wrote the first detailed description of a public water system in his Two Books on the Water Supply of the City of Rome. While these early water engineers had no understanding of bacteria and were probably treating water to decrease its cloudiness and improve its looks and taste, they nevertheless developed the earliest water treatment systems.
In one of the earliest cases to link a specific disease to the water supply, Dr. John Snow demonstrated in 1855 how cholera spread through water pumps during a large outbreak of the disease in London. He noticed that people who obtained their water from a particular well were more likely to become ill than those drawing their water from another well. He persuaded city officials to remove the pump handle from that particular well, forcing inhabitants to draw water from another well, and the number of cholera cases dropped immediately.
The U.S. Water Supply 
In 1799 Philadelphia became the first U.S. city with a public water system that pumped water from a surface source and distributed it through a series of pipes to residents. By 1900 there were more than 3,000 public water systems in the United States. Rather than guaranteeing a safe water supply, some of those systems actually contributed to major disease outbreaks in the early 1900s. If the water supplies were contaminated, the pumped and widely distributed water provided a means for spreading bacterial disease throughout communities. Federal regulation of the nation's drinking water began in 1914 when the U.S. Public Health Service (PHS) imposed bacteriological standards for drinking water. These standards were revised in 1925, 1946, and 1962 and were eventually adopted by all fifty states. After World War II, industrialization and the use of fertilizers on crops began to pollute the quality and safety of the nation's water. A 1969 survey showed that only 60 percent of water systems delivered water that met PHS standards. A study in 1972 detected thirty-six chemicals present in already treated water taken from the Mississippi River. This increased awareness of the problems with the water supply led to the passage of federal environmental and health laws dealing with polluted water, hazardous waste, and pesticides. 
Current water use in the United States averages about 100 gallons per person per day, more than just about any other country. A very small proportion of this, approximately two gallons, is actually used for drinking and cooking. Drinking water comes from either surface water or groundwater. Surface water includes rivers, lakes, and reservoirs, while groundwater is pumped up from wells drilled into aquifers, underground geologic formations that contain water. Over half the nation gets its drinking water from groundwater sources. 
The more than 170,000 water systems in the United States are either private or public. Private water systems do not draw water from a public water supply and serve only one or a few homes. Public water systems include community water systems and those at schools, factories, campgrounds, and some restaurants that have their own water supply. Community water systems deliver water to people year-round in their homes. In most community water systems, a network of underground pipes transports water under pressure to smaller pipes that then enter individual homes.
Hazards to the Water Supply and Treatment Methods 
Because water is the universal solvent, many chemicals and other materials easily dissolve in it. Water supplies become contaminated through many different channels—chemicals can migrate from disposal sites; animal wastes and pesticides may be carried to lakes and streams by rainfall runoff; human wastes may be discharged to receiving waters that ultimately flow into water used for drinking. Other sources of contamination include discharge from industry, erosion of natural deposits, corrosion of household plumbing systems, and leaching from septic tanks. Nitrates, inorganic compounds that can enter water supplies from fertilizer runoff and sanitary wastewater discharges, are especially harmful to young children. Naturally occurring contaminants are also found in drinking water. For example, the radioactive gas radon-222 occurs in certain types of rock and can seep into groundwater. It would be impossible to remove all contaminants from our water supply. It would also be unnecessary since at very low levels many contaminants are generally not harmful. 
Most outbreaks of waterborne disease are due to contamination by bacteria and viruses, mostly from human or animal waste. Two pathogens commonly associated with drinking water are Cryptosporidium parvum and Giardia lamblia. Both are protozoa that cause gastrointestinal illness and have cysts that are difficult to destroy. Cryptosporidium in particular may pass through water treatment filtration and disinfection processes in sufficient numbers to cause health problems. Cryptosporidium was first documented as posing a threat of infection to humans in 1976. A 1993 outbreak of cryptosporidiosis in Milwaukee, Wisconsin, is the largest outbreak of waterborne disease to date in the United States. Milwaukee's water supply, which comes from Lake Michigan, is treated by filtration and disinfection. Due to an unusual combination of circumstances during a period of heavy rainfall and runoff, water treatment was ineffective. An estimated 403,000 persons were affected by the disease, 4,400 were hospitalized, and at least 50 died. The original source of contamination is still unknown. Although Cryptosporidium had previously been found in surface water, it was not expected to appear in treated water from a municipal water supply that met state and federal standards for acceptable water quality. Increased awareness of the parasite has led to increased testing for it, and, not surprisingly, increased prevalence has been discovered. In addition to drinking-water outbreaks, Cryptosporidium is associated with swimming pools and amusement park wave pools. This is particularly important as Cryptosporidium is highly resistant to chlorine and other chemical disinfectants. This is a new parasite showing up in new environments with new resistance capabilities. 
Runoff from farms is another source of hazards to the nation's drinking water. In 1994 the Environmental Working Group released Tap Water Blues, a report in which the group identified over ten million individuals who had been exposed to five herbicides at levels above the Environmental Protection Agency's (EPA) negligible cancer risk standard of one additional case per million individuals. A second report in 1995, Weed Killers by the Glass, analyzed herbicides in the tap water of twenty-nine Midwestern cities. Again, their results show that Americans are exposed to harmful pesticides in their drinking water at levels far above federal health standards. 
The Centers for Disease Control (CDC), the EPA, and the Council of State and Territorial Epidemiologists collaborate to maintain a surveillance system that collects data on waterborne disease outbreaks (WBDOs) from drinking and recreational water. This program seeks to determine what pathogens in the water supply cause illness, how many people become ill, and how and why outbreaks occur. The data are submitted on a voluntary basis and most likely underestimate the true incidence of WBDOs. More WBDOs occur in the summer months, and the cause is often unidentified. WBDO outbreaks peaked between 1979 and 1983 and have been declining ever since. This decrease could be due to improved implementation of water treatment regulations, increased efforts by many water utilities to produce drinking water substantially better than EPA standards require, and efforts by public-health officials to improve drinking-water quality. Of the waterborne disease outbreaks reported to the CDC from 1974 to 1996, about 12 percent were caused by bacterial agents, 33 percent by parasites, 5 percent by viruses, 18 percent by chemical contaminants, and 31 percent by unidentified agents. 
During 1997 and 1998 there were seventeen outbreaks in drinking water, resulting in 2,038 people becoming ill. Six (35.3 percent) of the illnesses were caused by parasites (4 by Giardia, 2 by Cryptosporidium); four (23.5 percent) by bacteria (three by E. coli O157:H7 and one by Shigella sonnei ); five (29.4 percent) were of unidentified origin; and two (11.8 percent) were attributed to chemical poisoning. Both chemical poisonings were from copper. Eight (47.1 percent) of the seventeen WBDOs were associated with community water systems. Of these eight, three were caused by problems at water treatment plants, three were the result of problems in the water distribution systems and plumbing of individual facilities, and two were associated with contaminated, untreated groundwater. Five (29.4 percent) of the seventeen WBDOs were associated with noncommunity water systems; all five were from groundwater (i.e., a well or spring) systems. The four outbreaks (23.5 percent) associated with individual water systems were also from groundwater. 
Also during 1997 and 1998, eighteen outbreaks associated with recreational water caused 2,138 people to become ill. Nine (50 percent) were caused by the parasite Cryptosporidium. The other outbreaks were due to E. coli O157:H7 (three outbreaks or about 16.7 percent), Shigella sonnei (one outbreak or 5.6 percent), Norwalk-like viruses (two outbreaks or 11.1 percent), and unknown causes (three outbreaks or 16.7 percent). Slightly over half (55.6 percent) occurred in treated water—pools, hot tubs, or fountains; the others occurred in fresh-water lakes, rivers, or hot springs. 
Depending on the conditions and types of contaminants likely to be found in a particular water source, most water suppliers use a combination of two or more treatment processes. Major water treatment processes are: 
Flocculation/sedimentation. Flocculation is the process of getting small particles to combine into heavier particles called floc. The heavier particles can then be removed by letting them settle out as sediment. Once settled, the particles combine to form a sludge that is later removed. 
Filtration. Filtration removes particles from water by passing the water through a permeable fabric or porous bed of materials. Groundwater is naturally filtered as it flows through porous layers of soil. Some filtration processes can remove very small particles, including microorganisms. 
Ion exchange. Ion exchange processes remove inorganic constituents such as arsenic, chromium, excess fluoride, nitrates, radium, and uranium if they cannot be removed adequately by filtration or sedimentation. Electric current is used to attract negative and/or positive ions to one side of a treatment chamber for removal. 
Adsorption. Adsorption involves making organic contaminants that cause undesirable color, taste, or odor stick to the surface of granular or powdered activated carbon. 
Disinfection. Disinfection refers to killing harmful microorganisms. The three most commonly used methods of disinfection are chlorination, ozonation, and ultraviolet treatment. Chlorination is the method most often used in the United States while ozonation is very common in Europe.
Chlorination. Chlorine kills bacteria by forming hypochlorus acid, which attacks the respiratory, transport, and nucleic acid activity of bacteria. Most bacteria are very susceptible to chlorine while viruses are less so. Cysts from Giardia lamblia are very resistant to chlorine, and Cryptosporidium cannot be readily killed by chlorination. Of concern with this method of disinfection are the by-products (DBPs), particularly trihalomethanes (THMs), formed when chlorine reacts with organic matter that is in the water. Long-term exposure to some DBPs may increase the risk of cancer or have other adverse health effects. THMs are cancer group B carcinogens, which means they have been shown to cause cancer in laboratory animals. EPA regulations limit the amount of these by-products allowed in drinking water. 
Ozonation. Ozone is created by passing air through an electric current. The ozone gas is then dissolved in water, where it acts as an oxidant to destroy microorganisms. The ozone is removed before the water is used. As there is no residual antimicrobial effect, it is still necessary to chlorinate the water after ozone treatment. Ozone has received increased attention because it appears to be the only disinfectant that is effective against Cryptosporidium.
Ultraviolet light. Ultraviolet light (UV) does not actually kill bacteria. Instead, it effectively sterilizes them, making it impossible for them to reproduce. The use of ultraviolet light is only practical for small water systems due to the need for the microorganisms to be close to the radiation source. UV does not inactivate Giardia or Cryptosporidium cysts. 
With so many different bacteria that can cause illness, it is not possible to test the water supply for each of them separately. Instead, indicator organisms are used. Coliform bacteria are the most popular indicator organisms for drinking water as they are easily detected in water. Coliforms are a group of bacteria common in the environment and in the digestive tracts of humans and animals. While these organisms are themselves harmless, their presence indicates possible contamination with human and/or animal waste. The effectiveness of disinfection is judged by analyzing water supplies for total coliform bacteria. Presence of coliform bacteria is not acceptable in public water supplies and is a sign that disinfection is required.
Regulation
Local governments, public water systems, the states, and the EPA work together to ensure that all public water supplies are safe. Local governments have a direct interest in protecting the quality of their drinking-water source, be it groundwater or surface water. Part of the governments' job in protecting the water supply is to oversee land uses that can affect the quality of untreated source water. State public health and environmental agencies have the primary responsibility for ensuring that federal drinking-water quality standards, or more stringent ones required by the state, are met by each public water supplier. Municipal water systems test their own water systems for residues but do not regulate or test private wells. For households on private wells, state and local health departments usually have some standards for the drinking water, but it is generally up to the homeowner to maintain the quality of the drinking water. 
An increased awareness of the vulnerability of the nation's water supply led to the passage of the 1974 Safe Drinking Water Act (SDWA). Prior to 1974 each state ran its own drinking-water program and set local standards. As a result, drinking-water protection standards differed from state to state. The act authorized the EPA to establish national enforceable health standards for contaminants in drinking water, encouraged federal-state partnerships in protecting the nation's water supply, and required notification to alert customers to water-system violations. In 1986 the act was strengthened through the Surface Water Treatment Rule, which requires public water systems to filter and disinfect all surface-water supplies. In 1996 amendments to the act extended the protection of drinking water from source to tap. Provisions in the 1996 amendment include the following:
Consumers must receive more information about the quality of their drinking-water supplies. Water suppliers must notify customers within twenty-four hours of violations of EPA standards "that have the potential to have serious adverse effects on human health as a result of short-term exposure." If such a violation occurs, the system must announce it through the media and provide information about potential adverse effects on human health, steps taken to correct the violation, and the need to use alternative water supplies (such as boiled or bottled water) until the problem is corrected. When microorganisms such as those that indicate fecal contamination are found in drinking water, water suppliers may be required to issue "boil water notices." At least 725 communities, including New York City and the District of Columbia, have issued boil water notices affecting over 10 million people.
The SDWA amendments also require public water systems to prepare Consumer Confidence Reports. These are to inform consumers about the source of their water supply, contaminant levels detected in their water, and the health effects of contaminant levels that are above the established safety limit. Beginning in 1999, systems are to prepare and distribute the reports annually.Under the new amendments, each state must develop a program to identify potential contamination threats and determine the susceptibility of drinking-water sources to activities that may harm the source water.The 1996 SDWA Amendments provides up to $9.6 billion over six years to improve drinking-water infrastructure. Water systems can apply for low-and no-interest loans to upgrade their facilities and ensure compliance with drinking-water standards. Other sources of funding are also available to water systems through the U.S. Department of Agriculture's Rural Utility Service (RUS). As part of the Water 2000 initiative, which is aimed at providing clean, safe, and affordable drinking water to all rural homes, RUS administers a water and wastewater loan and grant program. Under the RUS programs, rural areas and small cities and towns can receive loans or grants to restore a deteriorating water supply, upgrade a water or wastewater facility, or develop new systems.The EPA Office of Water sets standards for pesticides and other chemicals in drinking water and issues Maximum Contaminant Levels (MCLs), which limit the amount of each substance that can be present in drinking water, for more than eighty contaminants. Scientists use a process called risk assessment to set drinking-water quality standards. When assessing the cancer and non-cancer risks from exposure to a chemical in drinking water, the first step is to measure how much of the chemical could be in the water. Next, scientists estimate how much of the chemical the average person is likely to drink. This amount is called the exposure. In developing drinking-water standards, the EPA assumes that the average adult drinks two liters of water each day throughout a seventy-year life span. MCLs are set at levels that will limit an individual's risk of cancer from that contaminant to between one in 10,000 and one in 1,000,000 over a lifetime. For non-cancer effects, risk assessment provides an estimate of an exposure level below which no adverse effects are expected to occur. The EPA also takes into account the ability of various technologies to remove the contaminant, their effectiveness, and the cost of treatment.To comply with MCLs, public water systems may use any state-approved treatment. According to 1996 statistics, 7 percent of community water systems, or 4,151 systems, reported one or more MCL violations, and less than 2 percent (681 systems) reported violations of treatment technique standards. The table shows the major groups of contaminants and the minimum frequency with which water systems must test for them.Finally, Healthy People 2010, a national health-promotion and disease-prevention initiative, has two goals for water quality:Increase the proportion of persons served by community water systems who receive a supply of drinking water that meets the regulations of the Safe Drinking Water Act. The current baseline is 73 percent; 2010 goals are to increase that to 95 percent.educe waterborne disease outbreaks from drinking water among persons served by community water systems. Currently an estimated six outbreaks per year originate from community water systems. The goal is to decrease that to two outbreaks per year.
Water as a Resource 
The central role played by water in the origin of life has long been acknowledged. As early as the seventeenth century, geologists recognized the extent to which water shaped and reshaped the landforms on the earth's surface. More recently, it has been argued that water plays a fundamental role in the formation of stars (Nisini, "Water's Role in Making Stars"). According to this account of the process of star formation, water may be present in two of its physical states, ice (a solid), and water vapor (a gas) in the earliest stages of the birth of a new star. During this phase, ice on the surface of dust particles contributes to the cooling of circumstellar gases by removing excess energy released during protostellar collapse. At the same time, water vapor serves as a reservoir of oxygen in the warmer sectors of accumulating mass. Certain of the peculiar physical and chemical properties of water to be discussed later make water uniquely qualified to participate in this seminal cosmological event. Since stars form as the result of the gravitational collapse of dense molecular clouds, almost all of the water present in its earliest stages is found in the ice coats of dust grains. A small amount, however, is produced as vapor through a series of reactions beginning with H3+ and O and resulting in the formation of H2OandO2. As star formation proceeds and gravitational collapse accelerates, increasing amounts of radiation energy are released. Consequently, the ambient temperature rises dramatically, and the temperature of the dust grains attains a level where water is released by evaporation. As the temperature continues to rise, all available atomic oxygen is rapidly transformed to water by the following reactions:
As the process of star formation moves into its later stages, these equations are reversed with the release of OH and atomic oxygen. However, some of the water produced is deposited on dust grains in the form of ice, where it may remain while planets are formed. Thus, newly formed planets have continued access to water during their evolution. Within our own solar system, there is considerable evidence that liquid water was abundant at some earlier stage in the history of Mars. The erosion patterns still visible on the planet's surface bear a striking resemblance to some found on earth. Many astronomers are also convinced that liquid water is still present on Saturn's moon, Titan, and under a deep layer of ice on Jupiter's moon, Europa.
The Reshaping of Landforms 
Geologists have long been aware of the role water plays in the reshaping of the earth's surface. The uniformitarian theory of the earth's history explicated by Charles Lyell in the early nineteenth century recognized that the surface of the earth is essentially a chronicle of its reshaping by water erosion. Some of the most informative strata for the reconstruction of past events are those that contain sedimentary deposits. These deposits, formed in lake beds and ocean floors, often contain fossils of species extant at a specific time, and can therefore be used, along with chronometric methods, to estimate the age of a given deposit and its contemporaneity with other deposits bearing similar fossils. 
The formation of sedimentary deposits provides one of the bases for determination of relative dating sequences through the comparison of fossil inclusions. However, it is the gradual wearing down of mountains and other landforms by rain and snowfall and the transport of particles of rock and soil to the sea that are continually altering earth's topography. Water erosion, combined with tectonic forces at work beneath the earth's crust, is ultimately responsible for environmental changes that occasionally trigger major evolutionary events. In some areas, such as the Grand Canyon of Arizona, long sequences of the earth's history can be reconstructed through examination of strata exposed by the action of Colorado River water. 
When major geological events such as the collision of tectonic plates occur, marine deposits sometimes end up in mountains, while other segments of the sea floor may be returned to the magma layer in zones of subduction. Mountain building may have profound effects on rainfall patterns. Under the appropriate circumstances, alterations in atmospheric conditions associated with major events such as the collision of the plates that joined the Indian subcontinent to the Asian landmass have the potential to trigger significant climatic changes. Changes in rainfall patterns, glaciations, and altered temperature gradients may be implicated in the onset of epochal events such as the Pleistocene "Ice Age," with worldwide effects on the evolution of plant and animal species.
Water and Weather 
The possibility of a worldwide change in climate associated with the rapid building of a major mountain range arises from the central role that the oceans of the earth play in the distribution of heat energy received from the Sun. Approximately 70 percent of the earth's surface is covered by water. Because of the tilt in the earth's axis, the waters of the equatorial zone receive the Sun's radiation more directly than areas in the higher latitudes. Consequently, more of the wavelengths of solar radiation that are subject to reflection, scatter, or absorption in the atmosphere actually reach the earth's surface in the tropics. Much of their energy serves to warm the oceans. The energy so received sets up warm ocean currents that flow away from the equatorial zone. Ultimately, the warm currents flowing out of the tropics mix with colder currents originating in the polar regions, but not before heat energy has been widely distributed over the oceans and landmasses of the temperate zones.The warming of the oceans in the equatorial zone has the additional effect of evaporating ocean water. Thus, water vapor enters the atmosphere. In the tropics, some of the moisture-bearing warmed air rises until it is sufficiently cooled to form precipitation. The result is the return of fresh water to the surface. The circulation of moisture-bearing atmosphere through the action of thermal gradients and prevailing winds allows some of it to flow to the cooler, drier areas at higher latitudes as well. Thus, the supply of fresh water is continuously replenished on the continental landmasses of both the Northern and Southern Hemispheres. The large number of plant and animal species that require access to fresh water for survival is evidence that the distribution of fresh water through the atmosphere has played a major role in the evolutionary process.The mixing of ocean waters and the direction of currents produce a complex pattern that is influenced by factors beyond the dissipation of heat energy absorbed in the tropics. The salinity of seawater varies from one area to another according to the amount and composition of the silt emptied into the oceans by rivers and streams. Since very salty water is heavier than fresh water, streams of water flowing away from the mouths of rivers tend to sink. This tendency sets up a network of crosscutting currents that affect the temperature of water at various depths. Temperature and salinity both affect the mix of marine organisms present in the ocean biome (ecological community). Generally, estuaries are some of the richest and most diverse of the marine habitats. Exploitation of fisheries such as the one that formerly produced abundant catches of sardines in the Mediterranean Sea off the mouth of the Nile River provided local human populations with an important source of dietary protein for many millennia. Other areas, such as the zone of nutrient upwelling off the west coast of South America, are illustrative of the way in which the combination of geological factors and ocean currents can create a major source of food for human populations that have learned how to exploit them.Although the vast majority of the earth's water is too salty to drink for many animals, including humans, evaporation and precipitation provide a constantly renewing source of fresh water. In addition, the atmospheric recirculation of water modifies the climate in the higher latitudes to such an extent that life can exist in areas that would otherwise be uninhabitable. Moreover, along with rainfall, atmospheric circulation plays an important role in the carbon cycle and nitrogen fixation, both essential to the maintenance of life.
The Physical and Chemical Properties of Water 
Through its role in the formation of stars, the reshaping of the earth's surface, the absorption and release of solar energy, and the provision of marine and aquatic habitats, water is essential for the existence of life as we know it. However, as important as each of these factors has been in shaping the evolutionary pathways that produced contemporary species, the physical and chemical properties of water have resulted in a much more intimate relationship between water and the processes of life than the mere provision of an appropriate environment. Water molecules and the molecules of living organisms interact in ways that would make the existence of life, as we know it, inconceivable in the absence of water. Understanding the nature of certain properties of water provides important insights into the nature of life itself, since organisms can quite properly be categorized as aqueous chemical systems. 
Water has an unusually high boiling point, melting point, and heat of vaporization. Thus, the transition from solid to liquid and liquid to gaseous phases requires a high energy input. Functionally, this attribute makes water an effective heat absorber. The aforementioned capture and distribution of solar energy by the oceans is one result of this attribute. Moreover, the density of water is greatest when it is in its liquid phase. Therefore, ice floats. The formation of a layer of ice on the surface of a lake or pond serves as insulation for the water beneath it, with the result that aquatic life can continue even through the long, cold winters of the higher latitudes. While it is certainly possible for small bodies of water to freeze solid during prolonged periods of severe cold, most large, deep lakes and rivers sustain a thriving population of fish and other aquatic species through even the most severe winters. 
Water molecules have a strong attraction for each other. Therefore, water has surprisingly high surface tension and exhibits the properties of cohesion and adhesion. Its ability to form hydrogen bonds is extraordinary. This ability comes into play in a variety of ways during many biochemical reactions. Water's tendency to adhere to a surface and to attract other molecules underlies the biologically important process of capillary action whereby water has the capability of moving against the force of gravity under certain circumstances. An illustration of this capability is seen in the capillary action that pulls water from soil through the roots and ultimately to the leaves of even the tallest trees.Water is also a very effective solvent. In fact, it is so effective in the dissolution of other substances that it is only rarely present in the pure, unadulterated state. The solvent properties of water have significance in both the geochemical and biochemical context. The nature and rate of erosion occurring in different kinds of rock will produce changes in the physical geography of the land as well as the chemical nature of silt borne by rivers and streams. The dissociation of mineral compounds can be of special significance when the solute is one of a number of salts that dissociate into ions in water. Ionization of salts converts water into an effective conductor of electricity. Many biological processes, including transmission of nervous impulses and contraction of muscle fibers, depend upon a mild salt solution's ability to conduct an electrical current under controlled conditions.The explanation for the extraordinary properties of water can be found in its previously mentioned unparalleled ability to form hydrogen bonds. Structurally, an individual water molecule is made up of two hydrogen atoms covalently bonded to one oxygen atom. That is, each hydrogen atom shares a pair of electrons with the oxygen atom. As a result, the molecule has a nonlinear shape and has electrical polarity because of a net positive charge on the hydrogen atoms and a net negative charge on the oxygen atom, creating a dipole moment. Water can serve as both a hydrogen donor and a hydrogen acceptor during hydrogen-bond formation, with each water molecule having the potential to form four hydrogen bonds. The intermolecular attraction inherent in this property accounts for water's high boiling point, melting point, heat of vaporization, and surface tension. The hydrogen bonds between water molecules are relatively weak and are continually broken and reformed with different partners. In liquid water, the average lifetime of the hydrogen bond between two water molecules is only 9.5 × 10-12 seconds (Garrett and Grisham, 1999). As a result, there is dynamism in a water solution that intensifies the diffusion of the products of dissociation. This continuous movement of water molecules enhances its solvent effect. Water also forms hydrogen bonds with a wide range of polar solutes. This permits nonionic but polar molecules such as sugars also to dissolve effectively in water. 
Certain nonpolar substances, categorized as hydrophobic, interact with water much differently than the hydrophilic ones discussed up to this point. When such substances are dissolved in water, the surrounding water molecules reorganize to encapsulate the solute molecules in a hydration shell. Hydrophobic molecules trapped in these structures are attracted to each other. The tendency of fats and oils, both hydrophobic in nature, to form closed aggregations when submerged in water arises from this tendency. On the other hand, the tendency for oil to spread out into a thin film when poured on the surface of water reflects its hydrophobic nature in a situation where the lowest free energy state occurs when each molecule has minimum contact with neighboring water molecules. The composition of cell membranes, which characteristically combine a hydrophobic phospholipid bilayer with hydrophilic protein and carbohydrate receptors, provides an example of the manner in which the presence of an aqueous environment can be used to govern the movement into and out of the cell's interior.
Life Requires the Presence of Water 
All living organisms require the presence of water to satisfy their metabolic needs. Even in such simple organisms as bacteria, metabolic processes requiring maintenance of solute concentrations inside the cell membrane that differ from those outside are essential to survival. In more complex organisms, the ability of water to absorb and diffuse solutes, create a potential electrical charge, and diffuse heat energy involves a variety of tissues, organs, and organ systems. These systems must communicate and support each other to satisfy the demands created by greater size and differentiation. Each organism, whether simple or complex, is dependent upon the unique properties of water to metabolize, survive, and reproduce. So intimate is the relationship between water and the structure and function of living organisms that the phenomenon of life as found on this planet is inconceivable in the absence of water. There is no concrete evidence of life anywhere else at this time. However, there is good evidence that water is abundant in the universe. Therefore, it is likely that if living organisms are ever found elsewhere, they will share many characteristics with those found here on earth, because of the inextricable relationship between life and water.
The water molecule
Water, H2O, is involved in a plethora of Earth processes because of its unique nature and unusual properties. The remarkable qualities of H2O are exhibited, in part, by its existence in three physical states at the Earth's surface: as solid (ice and snow): liquid (often referred to simply as ‘water’); and gas (water vapour, steam). Each state is stable over a range of pressure (P) and temperature (T) conditions, as shown by the phase diagram for the H2O-system (Fig. 1). For a given pressure–temperature (P–T) regime within the region labelled ‘liquid’, water exists only in the liquid state: similar considerations apply to regions of solid and gas. The solid region is subdivided because solid water is a mineral, ice, and crystallizes into different structures according to the P–T conditions. Separating these major regions are phase boundaries that mark the abrupt transition from one state to another and delineate the marked change in physical properties of H2O. At P–T conditions on a boundary, two phases coexist in equilibrium. At the surface of the Earth, H2O is commonly observed along a two-phase boundary: water vapour over ice on glacial fields traces the solid–gas boundary; water ponding on a frozen lake lies along the liquid–solid boundary; and water vapour hanging over a lake represents the liquid–gas boundary (Fig. 1). All three states coexist in equilibrium at the triple point for H2O near 0.01 °C (273K), 0.006 bar (0.0006 MPa) (Tr. pt, Fig. 1). Cirrus clouds form at triple-point conditions. At °C and surface pressure, liquid water freezes to become solid. Along the solid (ice I–liquid) boundary, increasing pressure causes liquid water to freeze at a lower temperature. Conversely, ice skaters glide effortlessly over the ice as their weight (P) induces melting; beneath their blades a two-phase region develops: a thin film of water over ice. Along the vapour–liquid boundary, water vaporizes at higher temperatures as pressure increases. Increasing T to 100 °C at surface pressure causes water to boil as is crosses the phase boundary from liquid to gas. An example of this transition is commonly seen when steam rises from kettles. Liquid water has a narrow range of thermal stability at the Earth's surface. The two-phase liquid vapour boundary continues until the critical endpoint is attained. For pure H2O, the critical point is at about 374 °C (647K), 220 bar (22 MPa) (Fig. 1). Extreme values in many thermodynamic and transport properties of water occur at this point. In natural systems, thermal springs in the mid-ocean ridges emanate fluids near critical-point conditions. At higher temperatures, a discrete vapour and liquid phase no longer exist; instead phase properties vary continuously. Water in this P–T region is referred to as a supercritical fluid; aqueous fluids typical of metamorphic and igneous environments.The P–T stability of water is also an indication that it has unique bonding characteristics. This uniqueness is derived from the nature of the water (H2O) molecule, which consists of two hydrogen atoms (H) bonded to one oxygen atom (O) in a V-shaped configuration, with the oxygen atom at the apex (Fig. 2). The two H are separated by an angle of about 104.5°. Although the molecule is symmetrical, it has an asymmetrical charge distribution. The oxygen side of the molecule has a local negative charge whereas the hydrogen side has a local positive charge. This non-coincidence of charge centres imparts the property of polarity to H2O: water is a polar molecule. Liquid water is associated because the positive hydrogen atom of one water molecule attracts the negative oxygen atom of another. This polar association is responsible for many of the properties of water, including: low vapour pressure, high boiling-point, and high heats of fusion and vaporization. High energy is required to break the hydrogen bonds holding the polar molecules together. Its capacity to bind both positively and negatively charged ions is also a consequence of it polarity. Liquid water is a universal solvent, behaving as an acid and a base, although it is a poor solvent for non-polar molecules. Water has an abnormally high dielectric constant, which is responsible for its ability to form complexes with other substances.
As mentioned above, solid H2O, ice, is also a mineral. The most common form of ice (ice I, Fig. 1) crystallizes in the hexagonal crystal system (Fig. 3). This is readily apparent on examination of individual snowflakes. No matter how small and intricate, these ice crystals have symmetrical sixfold shapes. In the crystal structure of ice, each oxygen atom is surrounded by four hydrogen atoms attached by hydrogen bonds and two by electron-pair bonds (Fig. 3). This arrangement results in an open structure and explains the low density of ice. H2O is also unusual in that this solid form is less dense than its liquid form. On melting, the hydrogen bonds are broken, the open structure collapses, and the water molecules move more closely together because of the intermolecular forces of polarity. This closer packing results in liquid water being nearly incompressible and having a higher density than ice. Thus, ice floats in water (there is a two-phase boundary). The maximum density for liquid water is at about 4°C, the temperature of ocean bottom waters. Water vapour is much less dense than liquid, and occupies a volume about a thousand times greater than liquid.
Water in geological processes
Erosion, weathering, and alteration processes caused by water at the Earth's surface are observed in every climatic regime. The erosional capacity of water is expressed in features ranging from smooth water worn stones and sculpted rock faces, to enormous sedimentary deposits at the base and sides of mountains. V-shaped valleys carved by moving water are transformed into broad U-shaped valleys by the movement of glacial ice. Silt deposits from floods and boulders far from their source attest to the transport capacities of water. Water is a primary modifier of landscape.
Within the Earth, water is found in all rock-types, as a constituent of minerals or as interstitial or pore water contained within pore space between mineral grains until the void space becomes vanishingly small at depth. Groundwater is a general term used for water contained in the pore spaces of rocks, typically in the upper portion of the Earth's crust. Although this water is a minor component within the crust, it contributes significantly to the chemical, mechanical, and thermal development of the crust because of its superb ability to transfer heat and solutes and to do mechanical work. Water dramatically enhances rates of chemical reactions and mineral transformations. Water is an excellent inorganic solvent. It reacts with both metals and with nonmetals to dissolve rocks. All minerals exhibit some degree of solubility in water. When water flows, it carries the dissolved constituents in solution and redeposits them elsewhere. Ore deposits are the remnants of former metal-bearing water-rich fluids. The migration, emplacement, and destruction of hydrocarbons depend on the movement and presence of aqueous pore fluids. Water alters the mechanical properties of rocks; it reduces rock strength and the effective stress but enhances the ductility of the rock.
Water can also be dissolved within magmas. Upon crystallization, the magmatic water is expelled as bubbles which later form vescicles or microlitic cavities in the rock, or it infiltrates into the surrounding country rocks. These hot igneous intrusions also produce hydrothermal water by heating pore fluids contained in adjacent rocks. Because water expands when it is heated, water pressure may increase, if the water is in a confined area, to overcome the effective strength and fracture the rock. Hydrofracturing is a method by which water does mechanical work (fractures rock) in response to a driving force and creates passageways through which it can migrate. Hydrothermal waters are excellent transporters of heat and mass, and are responsible for much of the chemical alteration of the crust. If large convection cells of the thermally heated water find pathways to the surface, geysers erupt or the fluids emanate at the surface as hot springs.
Structural water (H2O) or hydroxyl ions (OH) may form an integral portion of the structure of a mineral and be necessary for its formation. In some minerals, water occurs in structural cavities and is only loosely bound to the crystal structure. It readily enters and leaves the mineral, as in some swelling clays and zeolites. The ‘fire’ in opals is due to the reflection of light from water residing in the interstices of the silica spheres. If these minerals are heated, they will dehydrate and lose their water of hydration. During metamorphism, as the rocks are subjected to higher temperatures and pressures, hydrous minerals (e.g. muscovite, amphiboles) are exposed to conditions outside their stability range and are converted to more stable anhydrous phases. Water and hydroxyl ions bound within the crystal are released, forming metamorphic aqueous fluid as the minerals devolatilize and dehydrate.
Water types
In addition to the physical state in which it exists, water is described and classified by several features. One of the prevalent classification schemes is based on chemical attributes of water.All natural waters contain some quantity of dissolved substances. The total amount of dissolved solids, TDS measured in milligrams per litre (mg l−1), provides one basis for the chemical description of water types. (TDS is determined by evaporating a specific quantity of water and measuring the material remaining). The ultimate source of fresh water is unpolluted rainwater. Meteoric water, derived from the atmosphere, originates and falls to the Earth as precipitation. Some of this precipitation infiltrates into the ground through porous sediments and becomes groundwater, the most desirable source of drinking water. Pure water is a tasteless, odourless, colourless substance and is not for human consumption. Fortunately, the water molecule has an atomic configuration that solvates rock-forming elements and contaminates itself on the continents into a compositional range on which we thrive. Fresh water contains small quantities of solids, less than 1000mgl−1 TDS, and most is potable. Minor amounts of dissolved gases and salts in the water provide the taste. Small quantities of organic compounds can produce an unpleasant taste, and a few hundred parts per million (ppm) of salt will cause water to taste salty. As the TDS increases to c. 1000–20 000 mg l−1 TDS, brackish water becomes too saline for consumption by humans. These waters have lower salinities than sea water, which has an average salinity of 35 000mgl−1TDS or more. Brines are chemically variable but contain extremely high concentrations of TDS, at least ten times the salinity of sea water. Sea water and sedimentary brines are volumetrically more important that fresh waters, but are unfit for human consumption. In areas of active volcanism, some lakes have water which is extremely acidic because of dissolved gases. The range of water composition on which humans can survive is a narrow one, and that range approximates that of average river water.
As water moves and chemical reactions occur, the chemistry of the water changes and its properties are altered. Incorporation of dissolved ions makes water a better conductor of electricity. Continued contamination by metals makes the ores on which we depend.Specific chemicals dissolved in water or constituting the water also give rise to descriptive terms. Heavy water results when the heavy isotope of hydrogen, 21H, deuterium, D, combines with oxygen to form D2O. These waters occur naturally and are also produced in atomic energy plants, where they are used to slow nuclear chain reactions. Hard water, which leaves an insoluble residue and cleans poorly, results from an abundance of dissolved calcium (Ca) with lesser magnesium (Mg). Conversely, soft water has lower concentrations of calcium ions and gives the sensation that it cannot be washed off the skin.The elements of which water is composed, hydrogen and oxygen, both have stable isotopes. The origin of a water sample can thus be determined by use of oxygen and hydrogen isotopes. Meteoric, magmatic, metamorphic, formation, and exotic waters all have definite isotopic signatures that vary in a systematic fashion, as summarized by S. M. F. Sheppard. Formation water resides in the pore spaces within deeply buried sediments. Exotic water is a catch-all term which indicates that water has been introduced into a system and was externally derived. Organic water is water that results from the transformation of organic materials. The use of isotopes as tracers has become important in understanding fluid flow, contaminant transport, and alteration of the crust.Water holds a special place in several respects. It is used as a standard for the determination of numerous physical constants. It has profoundly influenced the evolution of the Earth. It is the substance that is required to sustain life. It also provides a source of power and for recreation. As our reserves of fresh water diminish and hazardous wastes become increasingly abundant, water quality is now of the utmost concern. The groundwater on which so much of the world's population depends is essentially a non-renewable resource. In most areas infiltration rates are so slow that consumption far outstrips replacement. As demands increase, more and more stress is placed on our planet's ever-dwindling supplies of potable water.